Revelation

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22

The Revelation to John

1

1 This is the Revelation of Jesus Christ,[*] which God gave him to show to his servants the things which must happen soon, which he sent and made known by his angel[†] to his servant, John, 2 who testified to God’s word and of the testimony of Jesus Christ, about everything that he saw.

3 Blessed is he who reads and those who hear the words of the prophecy, and keep the things that are written in it, for the time is near.

4 John, to the seven assemblies that are in Asia: Grace to you and peace from God, who is and who was and who is to come; and from the seven Spirits who are before his throne; 5 and from Jesus Christ, the faithful witness, the firstborn of the dead, and the ruler of the kings of the earth. To him who loves us, and washed us from our sins by his blood— 6 and he made us to be a Kingdom, priests[✡] to his God and Father—to him be the glory and the dominion forever and ever. Amen.

7 Behold,[‡] he is coming with the clouds, and every eye will see him, including those who pierced him. All the tribes of the earth will mourn over him. Even so, Amen.

8  “I am the Alpha and the Omega,[§]” says the Lord God,[*] “who is and who was and who is to come, the Almighty.”

9 I John, your brother and partner with you in the oppression, Kingdom, and perseverance in Christ Jesus, was on the isle that is called Patmos because of God’s Word and the testimony of Jesus Christ. 10 I was in the Spirit on the Lord’s day, and I heard behind me a loud voice, like a trumpet 11 saying,[†]“What you see, write in a book and send to the seven assemblies:[‡] to Ephesus, Smyrna, Pergamum, Thyatira, Sardis, Philadelphia, and to Laodicea.”

12 I turned to see the voice that spoke with me. Having turned, I saw seven golden lamp stands. 13 And among the lamp stands was one like a son of man,[✡] clothed with a robe reaching down to his feet, and with a golden sash around his chest. 14 His head and his hair were white as white wool, like snow. His eyes were like a flame of fire. 15 His feet were like burnished brass, as if it had been refined in a furnace. His voice was like the voice of many waters. 16 He had seven stars in his right hand. Out of his mouth proceeded a sharp two-edged sword. His face was like the sun shining at its brightest. 17 When I saw him, I fell at his feet like a dead man.

He laid his right hand on me, saying, “Don’t be afraid. I am the first and the last, 18  and the Living one. I was dead, and behold, I am alive forever and ever. Amen. I have the keys of Death and of Hades.[§] 19  Write therefore the things which you have seen, and the things which are, and the things which will happen hereafter. 20  The mystery of the seven stars which you saw in my right hand, and the seven golden lamp stands is this: The seven stars are the angels[*] of the seven assemblies. The seven lamp stands are seven assemblies.

2

1  “To the angel of the assembly in Ephesus write:

“He who holds the seven stars in his right hand, he who walks among the seven golden lamp stands says these things:

2  “I know your works, and your toil and perseverance, and that you can’t tolerate evil men, and have tested those who call themselves apostles, and they are not, and found them false. 3  You have perseverance and have endured for my name’s sake, and have [*] not grown weary. 4  But I have this against you, that you left your first love. 5  Remember therefore from where you have fallen, and repent and do the first works; or else I am coming to you swiftly, and will move your lamp stand out of its place, unless you repent. 6  But this you have, that you hate the works of the Nicolaitans, which I also hate. 7  He who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies. To him who overcomes I will give to eat from the tree of life, which is in the Paradise of my God.

8  “To the angel of the assembly in Smyrna write:

“The first and the last, who was dead, and has come to life says these things:

9  “I know your works, oppression, and your poverty (but you are rich), and the blasphemy of those who say they are Jews, and they are not, but are a synagogue of Satan. 10  Don’t be afraid of the things which you are about to suffer. Behold, the devil is about to throw some of you into prison, that you may be tested; and you will have oppression for ten days. Be faithful to death, and I will give you the crown of life. 11  He who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies. He who overcomes won’t be harmed by the second death.

12  “To the angel of the assembly in Pergamum write:

“He who has the sharp two-edged sword says these things:

13  “I know your works and where you dwell, where Satan’s throne is. You hold firmly to my name, and didn’t deny my faith in the days of Antipas my witness, my faithful one, who was killed among you, where Satan dwells. 14  But I have a few things against you, because you have there some who hold the teaching of Balaam, who taught Balak to throw a stumbling block before the children of Israel, to eat things sacrificed to idols, and to commit sexual immorality. 15  So also you likewise have some who hold to the teaching of the Nicolaitans.[†] 16  Repent therefore, or else I am coming to you quickly and I will make war against them with the sword of my mouth. 17  He who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies. To him who overcomes, to him I will give of the hidden manna, [‡] and I will give him a white stone, and on the stone a new name written which no one knows but he who receives it.

18  “To the angel of the assembly in Thyatira write:

“The Son of God, who has his eyes like a flame of fire, and his feet are like burnished brass, says these things:

19  “I know your works, your love, faith, service, patient endurance, and that your last works are more than the first. 20  But I have this against you, that you tolerate your[§] woman Jezebel, who calls herself a prophetess. She teaches and seduces my servants to commit sexual immorality and to eat things sacrificed to idols. 21  I gave her time to repent, but she refuses to repent of her sexual immorality. 22  Behold, I will throw her and those who commit adultery with her into a bed of great oppression, unless they repent of her works. 23  I will kill her children with Death, and all the assemblies will know that I am he who searches the minds and hearts. I will give to each one of you according to your deeds. 24  But to you I say, to the rest who are in Thyatira—as many as don’t have this teaching, who don’t know what some call ‘the deep things of Satan’—to you I say, I am not putting any other burden on you. 25  Nevertheless, hold that which you have firmly until I come. 26  He who overcomes, and he who keeps my works to the end, to him I will give authority over the nations. 27  He will rule them with a rod of iron, shattering them like clay pots,[✡] as I also have received of my Father; 28  and I will give him the morning star. 29  He who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies.

3

1  “And to the angel of the assembly in Sardis write:

“He who has the seven Spirits of God and the seven stars says these things:

“I know your works, that you have a reputation of being alive, but you are dead. 2  Wake up and strengthen the things that remain, which you were about to throw away,[*] for I have found no works of yours perfected before my God. 3  Remember therefore how you have received and heard. Keep it and repent. If therefore you won’t watch, I will come as a thief, and you won’t know what hour I will come upon you. 4  Nevertheless you have a few names in Sardis that didn’t defile their garments. They will walk with me in white, for they are worthy. 5  He who overcomes will be arrayed in white garments, and I will in no way blot his name out of the book of life, and I will confess his name before my Father, and before his angels. 6  He who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies.

7  “To the angel of the assembly in Philadelphia write:

“He who is holy, he who is true, he who has the key of David, he who opens and no one can shut, and who shuts and no one opens, says these things:

8  “I know your works (behold, I have set before you an open door, which no one can shut), that you have a little power, and kept my word, and didn’t deny my name. 9  Behold, I make some of the synagogue of Satan, of those who say they are Jews, and they are not, but lie—behold, I will make them to come and worship before your feet, and to know that I have loved you. 10  Because you kept my command to endure, I also will keep you from the hour of testing which is to come on the whole world, to test those who dwell on the earth. 11  I am coming quickly! Hold firmly that which you have, so that no one takes your crown. 12  He who overcomes, I will make him a pillar in the temple of my God, and he will go out from there no more. I will write on him the name of my God and the name of the city of my God, the new Jerusalem, which comes down out of heaven from my God, and my own new name. 13  He who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies.

14  “To the angel of the assembly in Laodicea write:

“The Amen, the Faithful and True Witness, the Beginning[†] of God’s creation, says these things:

15  “I know your works, that you are neither cold nor hot. I wish you were cold or hot. 16  So, because you are lukewarm, and neither hot nor cold, I will vomit you out of my mouth. 17  Because you say, ‘I am rich, and have gotten riches, and have need of nothing,’ and don’t know that you are the wretched one, miserable, poor, blind, and naked; 18  I counsel you to buy from me gold refined by fire, that you may become rich; and white garments, that you may clothe yourself, and that the shame of your nakedness may not be revealed; and eye salve to anoint your eyes, that you may see. 19  As many as I love, I reprove and chasten. Be zealous therefore, and repent. 20  Behold, I stand at the door and knock. If anyone hears my voice and opens the door, then I will come in to him and will dine with him, and he with me. 21  He who overcomes, I will give to him to sit down with me on my throne, as I also overcame and sat down with my Father on his throne. 22  He who has an ear, let him hear what the Spirit says to the assemblies.”

4

1 After these things I looked and saw a door opened in heaven; and the first voice that I heard, like a trumpet speaking with me, was one saying, “Come up here, and I will show you the things which must happen after this.”

2 Immediately I was in the Spirit. Behold, there was a throne set in heaven, and one sitting on the throne 3 that looked like a jasper stone and a sardius. There was a rainbow around the throne, like an emerald to look at. 4 Around the throne were twenty-four thrones. On the thrones were twenty-four elders sitting, dressed in white garments, with crowns of gold on their heads. 5 Out of the throne proceed lightnings, sounds, and thunders. There were seven lamps of fire burning before his throne, which are the seven Spirits of God. 6 Before the throne was something like a sea of glass, similar to crystal. In the middle of the throne, and around the throne were four living creatures full of eyes before and behind. 7 The first creature was like a lion, the second creature like a calf, the third creature had a face like a man, and the fourth was like a flying eagle. 8 The four living creatures, each one of them having six wings, are full of eyes around and within. They have no rest day and night, saying, “Holy, holy, holy[*] is the Lord God, the Almighty, who was and who is and who is to come!”

9 When the living creatures give glory, honor, and thanks to him who sits on the throne, to him who lives forever and ever, 10 the twenty-four elders fall down before him who sits on the throne and worship him who lives forever and ever, and throw their crowns before the throne, saying, 11 “Worthy are you, our Lord and God, the Holy One,[†] to receive the glory, the honor, and the power, for you created all things, and because of your desire they existed and were created!”

5

1 I saw, in the right hand of him who sat on the throne, a book written inside and outside, sealed shut with seven seals. 2 I saw a mighty angel proclaiming with a loud voice, “Who is worthy to open the book, and to break its seals?” 3 No one in heaven above, or on the earth, or under the earth, was able to open the book or to look in it. 4 Then I wept much, because no one was found worthy to open the book or to look in it. 5 One of the elders said to me, “Don’t weep. Behold, the Lion who is of the tribe of Judah, the Root of David, has overcome: he who opens the book and its seven seals.”

6 I saw in the middle of the throne and of the four living creatures, and in the middle of the elders, a Lamb standing, as though it had been slain, having seven horns and seven eyes, which are the seven Spirits of God, sent out into all the earth. 7 Then he came, and he took it out of the right hand of him who sat on the throne. 8 Now when he had taken the book, the four living creatures and the twenty-four elders fell down before the Lamb, each one having a harp, and golden bowls full of incense, which are the prayers of the saints. 9 They sang a new song, saying,

“You are worthy to take the book

and to open its seals,

for you were killed,

and bought us for God with your blood

out of every tribe, language, people, and nation,

10 and made us kings and priests to our God;

and we will reign on the earth.”

11 I looked, and I heard something like a voice of many angels around the throne, the living creatures, and the elders. The number of them was ten thousands of ten thousands, and thousands of thousands, 12 saying with a loud voice, “Worthy is the Lamb who has been killed to receive the power, wealth, wisdom, strength, honor, glory, and blessing!”

13 I heard every created thing which is in heaven, on the earth, under the earth, on the sea, and everything in them, saying, “To him who sits on the throne and to the Lamb be the blessing, the honor, the glory, and the dominion, forever and ever! Amen!”[*]

14 The four living creatures said, “Amen!” Then the[†] elders fell down and worshiped.[‡]

6

1 I saw that the Lamb opened one of the seven seals, and I heard one of the four living creatures saying, as with a voice of thunder, “Come and see!” 2 Then a white horse appeared, and he who sat on it had a bow. A crown was given to him, and he came out conquering, and to conquer.

3 When he opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature saying, “Come!” 4 Another came out, a red horse. To him who sat on it was given power to take peace from the earth, and that they should kill one another. There was given to him a great sword.

5 When he opened the third seal, I heard the third living creature saying, “Come and see!” And behold, a black horse, and he who sat on it had a balance in his hand. 6 I heard a voice in the middle of the four living creatures saying, “A choenix[*] of wheat for a denarius, and three choenix of barley for a denarius! Don’t damage the oil and the wine!”

7 When he opened the fourth seal, I heard the fourth living creature saying, “Come and see!” 8 And behold, a pale horse, and the name of he who sat on it was Death. Hades[†] followed with him. Authority over one fourth of the earth, to kill with the sword, with famine, with death, and by the wild animals of the earth was given to him.

9 When he opened the fifth seal, I saw underneath the altar the souls of those who had been killed for the Word of God, and for the testimony of the Lamb which they had. 10 They cried with a loud voice, saying, “How long, Master, the holy and true, until you judge and avenge our blood on those who dwell on the earth?” 11 A long white robe was given to each of them. They were told that they should rest yet for a while, until their fellow servants and their brothers,[‡] who would also be killed even as they were, should complete their course.

12 I saw when he opened the sixth seal, and there was a great earthquake. The sun became black as sackcloth made of hair, and the whole moon became as blood. 13 The stars of the sky fell to the earth, like a fig tree dropping its unripe figs when it is shaken by a great wind. 14 The sky was removed like a scroll when it is rolled up. Every mountain and island was moved out of its place. 15 The kings of the earth, the princes, the commanding officers, the rich, the strong, and every slave and free person, hid themselves in the caves and in the rocks of the mountains. 16 They told the mountains and the rocks, “Fall on us, and hide us from the face of him who sits on the throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb, 17 for the great day of his wrath has come, and who is able to stand?”

7

1 After this, I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth, holding the four winds of the earth, so that no wind would blow on the earth, or on the sea, or on any tree. 2 I saw another angel ascend from the sunrise, having the seal of the living God. He cried with a loud voice to the four angels to whom it was given to harm the earth and the sea, 3 saying, “Don’t harm the earth, the sea, or the trees, until we have sealed the bondservants of our God on their foreheads!” 4 I heard the number of those who were sealed, one hundred forty-four thousand, sealed out of every tribe of the children of Israel:

5 of the tribe of Judah twelve thousand were sealed,

of the tribe of Reuben twelve thousand,

of the tribe of Gad twelve thousand,

6 of the tribe of Asher twelve thousand,

of the tribe of Naphtali twelve thousand,

of the tribe of Manasseh twelve thousand,

7 of the tribe of Simeon twelve thousand,

of the tribe of Levi twelve thousand,

of the tribe of Issachar twelve thousand,

8 of the tribe of Zebulun twelve thousand,

of the tribe of Joseph twelve thousand, and

of the tribe of Benjamin twelve thousand were sealed.

9 After these things I looked, and behold, a great multitude which no man could count, out of every nation and of all tribes, peoples, and languages, standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes, with palm branches in their hands. 10 They cried with a loud voice, saying, “Salvation be to our God, who sits on the throne, and to the Lamb!”

11 All the angels were standing around the throne, the elders, and the four living creatures; and they fell on their faces before his throne, and worshiped God, 12 saying, “Amen! Blessing, glory, wisdom, thanksgiving, honor, power, and might, be to our God forever and ever! Amen.”

13 One of the elders answered, saying to me, “These who are arrayed in the white robes, who are they, and where did they come from?”

14 I told him, “My lord, you know.”

He said to me, “These are those who came out of the great suffering.[*]They washed their robes and made them white in the Lamb’s blood. 15 Therefore they are before the throne of God, and they serve him day and night in his temple. He who sits on the throne will spread his tabernacle over them. 16 They will never be hungry or thirsty any more. The sun won’t beat on them, nor any heat; 17 for the Lamb who is in the middle of the throne shepherds them and leads them to springs of life-giving waters. And God will wipe away every tear from their eyes.”

8

1 When he opened the seventh seal, there was silence in heaven for about half an hour. 2 I saw the seven angels who stand before God, and seven trumpets were given to them.

3 Another angel came and stood over the altar, having a golden censer. Much incense was given to him, that he should add it to the prayers of all the saints on the golden altar which was before the throne. 4 The smoke of the incense, with the prayers of the saints, went up before God out of the angel’s hand. 5 The angel took the censer, and he filled it with the fire of the altar, then threw it on the earth. Thunders, sounds, lightnings, and an earthquake followed.

6 The seven angels who had the seven trumpets prepared themselves to sound.

7 The first sounded, and there followed hail and fire, mixed with blood, and they were thrown to the earth. One third of the earth was burned up,[*] and one third of the trees were burned up, and all green grass was burned up.

8 The second angel sounded, and something like a great burning mountain was thrown into the sea. One third of the sea became blood, 9 and one third of the living creatures which were in the sea died. One third of the ships were destroyed.

10 The third angel sounded, and a great star fell from the sky, burning like a torch, and it fell on one third of the rivers, and on the springs of water. 11 The name of the star is “Wormwood.” One third of the waters became wormwood. Many people died from the waters, because they were made bitter.

12 The fourth angel sounded, and one third of the sun was struck, and one third of the moon, and one third of the stars, so that one third of them would be darkened; and the day wouldn’t shine for one third of it, and the night in the same way. 13 I saw, and I heard an eagle,[†] flying in mid heaven, saying with a loud voice, “Woe! Woe! Woe to those who dwell on the earth, because of the other blasts of the trumpets of the three angels, who are yet to sound!”

9

1 The fifth angel sounded, and I saw a star from the sky which had fallen to the earth. The key to the pit of the abyss was given to him. 2 He opened the pit of the abyss, and smoke went up out of the pit, like the smoke from a[*] burning furnace. The sun and the air were darkened because of the smoke from the pit. 3 Then out of the smoke came locusts on the earth, and power was given to them, as the scorpions of the earth have power. 4 They were told that they should not hurt the grass of the earth, neither any green thing, neither any tree, but only those people who don’t have God’s seal on their foreheads. 5 They were given power, not to kill them, but to torment them for five months. Their torment was like the torment of a scorpion when it strikes a person. 6 In those days people will seek death, and will in no way find it. They will desire to die, and death will flee from them.

7 The shapes of the locusts were like horses prepared for war. On their heads were something like golden crowns, and their faces were like people’s faces. 8 They had hair like women’s hair, and their teeth were like those of lions. 9 They had breastplates like breastplates of iron. The sound of their wings was like the sound of many chariots and horses rushing to war. 10 They have tails like those of scorpions, with stingers. In their tails they have power to harm men for five months. 11 They have over them as king the angel of the abyss. His name in Hebrew is “Abaddon”,[†] but in Greek, he has the name “Apollyon”.[‡]

12 The first woe is past. Behold, there are still two woes coming after this.

13 The sixth angel sounded. I heard a voice from the horns of the golden altar which is before God, 14 saying to the sixth angel who had the trumpet, “Free the four angels who are bound at the great river Euphrates!”

15 The four angels were freed who had been prepared for that hour and day and month and year, so that they might kill one third of mankind. 16 The number of the armies of the horsemen was two hundred million.[§] I heard the number of them. 17 Thus I saw the horses in the vision and those who sat on them, having breastplates of fiery red, hyacinth blue, and sulfur yellow; and the horses’ heads resembled lions’ heads. Out of their mouths proceed fire, smoke, and sulfur. 18 By these three plagues, one third of mankind was killed: by the fire, the smoke, and the sulfur, which proceeded out of their mouths. 19 For the power of the horses is in their mouths and in their tails. For their tails are like serpents, and have heads; and with them they harm.

20 The rest of mankind, who were not killed with these plagues, didn’t repent of the works of their hands, that they wouldn’t worship demons, and the idols of gold, and of silver, and of brass, and of stone, and of wood, which can’t see, hear, or walk. 21 They didn’t repent of their murders, their sorceries,[*] their sexual immorality, or their thefts.

10

1 I saw a mighty angel coming down out of the sky, clothed with a cloud. A rainbow was on his head. His face was like the sun, and his feet like pillars of fire. 2 He had in his hand a little open book. He set his right foot on the sea, and his left on the land. 3 He cried with a loud voice, as a lion roars. When he cried, the seven thunders uttered their voices. 4 When the seven thunders sounded, I was about to write; but I heard a voice from the sky saying, “Seal up the things which the seven thunders said, and don’t write them.”

5 The angel whom I saw standing on the sea and on the land lifted up his right hand to the sky 6 and swore by him who lives forever and ever, who created heaven and the things that are in it, the earth and the things that are in it, and the sea and the things that are in it, that there will no longer be delay, 7 but in the days of the voice of the seventh angel, when he is about to sound, then the mystery of God is finished, as he declared to his servants the prophets.

8 The voice which I heard from heaven, again speaking with me, said, “Go, take the book which is open in the hand of the angel who stands on the sea and on the land.”

9 I went to the angel, telling him to give me the little book.

He said to me, “Take it and eat it. It will make your stomach bitter, but in your mouth it will be as sweet as honey.”

10 I took the little book out of the angel’s hand, and ate it. It was as sweet as honey in my mouth. When I had eaten it, my stomach was made bitter. 11 They[*] told me, “You must prophesy again over many peoples, nations, languages, and kings.”

11

1 A reed like a rod was given to me. Someone said, “Rise and measure God’s temple, and the altar, and those who worship in it. 2 Leave out the court which is outside of the temple, and don’t measure it, for it has been given to the nations. They will tread the holy city under foot for forty-two months. 3 I will give power to my two witnesses, and they will prophesy one thousand two hundred sixty days, clothed in sackcloth.”

4 These are the two olive trees and the two lamp stands, standing before the Lord of the earth. 5 If anyone desires to harm them, fire proceeds out of their mouth and devours their enemies. If anyone desires to harm them, he must be killed in this way. 6 These have the power to shut up the sky, that it may not rain during the days of their prophecy. They have power over the waters, to turn them into blood, and to strike the earth with every plague, as often as they desire.

7 When they have finished their testimony, the beast that comes up out of the abyss will make war with them, and overcome them, and kill them. 8 Their dead bodies will be in the street of the great city, which spiritually is called Sodom and Egypt, where also their Lord was crucified. 9 From among the peoples, tribes, languages, and nations, people will look at their dead bodies for three and a half days, and will not allow their dead bodies to be laid in a tomb. 10 Those who dwell on the earth will rejoice over them, and they will be glad. They will give gifts to one another, because these two prophets tormented those who dwell on the earth.

11 After the three and a half days, the breath of life from God entered into them, and they stood on their feet. Great fear fell on those who saw them. 12 I heard a loud voice from heaven saying to them, “Come up here!” They went up into heaven in a cloud, and their enemies saw them. 13 In that day there was a great earthquake, and a tenth of the city fell. Seven thousand people were killed in the earthquake, and the rest were terrified and gave glory to the God of heaven.

14 The second woe is past. Behold, the third woe comes quickly.

15 The seventh angel sounded, and great voices in heaven followed, saying, “The kingdom of the world has become the Kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ. He will reign forever and ever!”

16 The twenty-four elders, who sit on their thrones before God’s throne, fell on their faces and worshiped God, 17 saying: “We give you thanks, Lord God, the Almighty, the one who is and who was,[*] because you have taken your great power and reigned. 18 The nations were angry, and your wrath came, as did the time for the dead to be judged, and to give your bondservants the prophets, their reward, as well as to the saints and those who fear your name, to the small and the great, and to destroy those who destroy the earth.”

19 God’s temple that is in heaven was opened, and the ark of the Lord’s covenant was seen in his temple. Lightnings, sounds, thunders, an earthquake, and great hail followed.

12

1 A great sign was seen in heaven: a woman clothed with the sun, and the moon under her feet, and on her head a crown of twelve stars. 2 She was with child. She cried out in pain, laboring to give birth.

3 Another sign was seen in heaven. Behold, a great red dragon, having seven heads and ten horns, and on his heads seven crowns. 4 His tail drew one third of the stars of the sky, and threw them to the earth. The dragon stood before the woman who was about to give birth, so that when she gave birth he might devour her child. 5 She gave birth to a son, a male child, who is to rule all the nations with a rod of iron. Her child was caught up to God and to his throne. 6 The woman fled into the wilderness, where she has a place prepared by God, that there they may nourish her one thousand two hundred sixty days.

7 There was war in the sky. Michael and his angels made war on the dragon. The dragon and his angels made war. 8 They didn’t prevail. No place was found for them any more in heaven. 9 The great dragon was thrown down, the old serpent, he who is called the devil and Satan, the deceiver of the whole world. He was thrown down to the earth, and his angels were thrown down with him.

10 I heard a loud voice in heaven, saying, “Now the salvation, the power, and the Kingdom of our God, and the authority of his Christ has come; for the accuser of our brothers has been thrown down, who accuses them before our God day and night. 11 They overcame him because of the Lamb’s blood, and because of the word of their testimony. They didn’t love their life, even to death. 12 Therefore rejoice, heavens, and you who dwell in them. Woe to the earth and to the sea, because the devil has gone down to you, having great wrath, knowing that he has but a short time.”

13 When the dragon saw that he was thrown down to the earth, he persecuted the woman who gave birth to the male child. 14 Two wings of the great eagle were given to the woman, that she might fly into the wilderness to her place, so that she might be nourished for a time, times, and half a time, from the face of the serpent. 15 The serpent spewed water out of his mouth after the woman like a river, that he might cause her to be carried away by the stream. 16 The earth helped the woman, and the earth opened its mouth and swallowed up the river which the dragon spewed out of his mouth. 17 The dragon grew angry with the woman, and went away to make war with the rest of her offspring,[*] who keep God’s commandments and hold Jesus’ testimony.

13

1 Then I stood on the sand of the sea. I saw a beast coming up out of the sea, having ten horns and seven heads. On his horns were ten crowns, and on his heads, blasphemous names. 2 The beast which I saw was like a leopard, and his feet were like those of a bear, and his mouth like the mouth of a lion. The dragon gave him his power, his throne, and great authority. 3 One of his heads looked like it had been wounded fatally. His fatal wound was healed, and the whole earth marveled at the beast. 4 They worshiped the dragon because he gave his authority to the beast; and they worshiped the beast, saying, “Who is like the beast? Who is able to make war with him?”

5 A mouth speaking great things and blasphemy was given to him. Authority to make war for forty-two months was given to him. 6 He opened his mouth for blasphemy against God, to blaspheme his name, his dwelling, and those who dwell in heaven. 7 It was given to him to make war with the saints and to overcome them. Authority over every tribe, people, language, and nation was given to him. 8 All who dwell on the earth will worship him, everyone whose name has not been written from the foundation of the world in the book of life of the Lamb who has been killed. 9 If anyone has an ear, let him hear. 10 If anyone is to go into captivity, he will go into captivity. If anyone is to be killed with the sword, he must be killed.[*] Here is the endurance and the faith of the saints.

11 I saw another beast coming up out of the earth. He had two horns like a lamb and it spoke like a dragon. 12 He exercises all the authority of the first beast in his presence. He makes the earth and those who dwell in it to worship the first beast, whose fatal wound was healed. 13 He performs great signs, even making fire come down out of the sky to the earth in the sight of people. 14 He deceives my own[†] people who dwell on the earth because of the signs he was granted to do in front of the beast, saying to those who dwell on the earth that they should make an image to the beast who had the sword wound and lived. 15 It was given to him to give breath to the image of the beast, that the image of the beast should both speak, and cause as many as wouldn’t worship the image of the beast to be killed. 16 He causes all, the small and the great, the rich and the poor, and the free and the slave, to be given marks on their right hands or on their foreheads; 17 and that no one would be able to buy or to sell unless he has that mark, which is the name of the beast or the number of his name. 18 Here is wisdom. He who has understanding, let him calculate the number of the beast, for it is the number of a man. His number is six hundred sixty-six.

14

1 I saw, and behold, the Lamb standing on Mount Zion, and with him a number, one hundred forty-four thousand, having his name and the name of his Father written on their foreheads. 2 I heard a sound from heaven like the sound of many waters and like the sound of a great thunder. The sound which I heard was like that of harpists playing on their harps. 3 They sing a new song before the throne and before the four living creatures and the elders. No one could learn the song except the one hundred forty-four thousand, those who had been redeemed out of the earth. 4 These are those who were not defiled with women, for they are virgins. These are those who follow the Lamb wherever he goes. These were redeemed by Jesus from among men, the first fruits to God and to the Lamb. 5 In their mouth was found no lie, for they are blameless.[*]

6 I saw an angel flying in mid heaven, having an eternal Good News to proclaim to those who dwell on the earth—to every nation, tribe, language, and people. 7 He said with a loud voice, “Fear the Lord, and give him glory, for the hour of his judgment has come. Worship him who made the heaven, the earth, the sea, and the springs of waters!”

8 Another, a second angel, followed, saying, “Babylon the great has fallen, which has made all the nations to drink of the wine of the wrath of her sexual immorality.”

9 Another angel, a third, followed them, saying with a great voice, “If anyone worships the beast and his image, and receives a mark on his forehead or on his hand, 10 he also will drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is prepared unmixed in the cup of his anger. He will be tormented with fire and sulfur in the presence of the holy angels and in the presence of the Lamb. 11 The smoke of their torment goes up forever and ever. They have no rest day and night, those who worship the beast and his image, and whoever receives the mark of his name.

12 Here is the perseverance of the saints, those who keep the commandments of God and the faith of Jesus.”

13 I heard a voice from heaven saying, “Write, ‘Blessed are the dead who die in the Lord from now on.’ ”

“Yes,” says the Spirit, “that they may rest from their labors, for their works follow with them.”

14 I looked, and saw a white cloud, and on the cloud one sitting like a son of man,[✡] having on his head a golden crown, and in his hand a sharp sickle. 15 Another angel came out of the temple, crying with a loud voice to him who sat on the cloud, “Send your sickle and reap, for the hour to reap has come; for the harvest of the earth is ripe!” 16 He who sat on the cloud thrust his sickle on the earth, and the earth was reaped.

17 Another angel came out of the temple which is in heaven. He also had a sharp sickle. 18 Another angel came out from the altar, he who has power over fire, and he called with a great voice to him who had the sharp sickle, saying, “Send your sharp sickle and gather the clusters of the vine of the earth, for the earth’s grapes are fully ripe!” 19 The angel thrust his sickle into the earth, and gathered the vintage of the earth and threw it into the great wine press of the wrath of God. 20 The wine press was trodden outside of the city, and blood came out of the wine press, up to the bridles of the horses, as far as one thousand six hundred stadia.[†]

15

1 I saw another great and marvelous sign in the sky: seven angels having the seven last plagues, for in them God’s wrath is finished.

2 I saw something like a sea of glass mixed with fire, and those who overcame the beast, his image,[*] and the number of his name, standing on the sea of glass, having harps of God. 3 They sang the song of Moses, the servant of God, and the song of the Lamb, saying,

“Great and marvelous are your works, Lord God, the Almighty!

Righteous and true are your ways, you King of the nations.

4 Who wouldn’t fear you, Lord,

and glorify your name?

For you only are holy.

For all the nations will come and worship before you.

For your righteous acts have been revealed.”

5 After these things I looked, and the temple of the tabernacle of the testimony in heaven was opened. 6 The seven angels who had the seven plagues came out, clothed with pure, bright linen, and wearing golden sashes around their chests.

7 One of the four living creatures gave to the seven angels seven golden bowls full of the wrath of God, who lives forever and ever. 8 The temple was filled with smoke from the glory of God and from his power. No one was able to enter into the temple until the seven plagues of the seven angels would be finished.

16

1 I heard a loud voice out of the temple, saying to the seven angels, “Go and pour out the seven bowls of the wrath of God on the earth!”

2 The first went, and poured out his bowl into the earth, and it became a harmful and painful sore on the people who had the mark of the beast, and who worshiped his image.

3 The second angel poured out his bowl into the sea, and it became blood as of a dead man. Every living thing in the sea died.

4 The third poured out his bowl into the rivers and springs of water, and they became blood. 5 I heard the angel of the waters saying, “You are righteous, who are and who were, O Holy One, because you have judged these things. 6 For they poured out the blood of saints and prophets, and you have given them blood to drink. They deserve this.”

7 I heard the altar saying, “Yes, Lord God, the Almighty, true and righteous are your judgments.”

8 The fourth poured out his bowl on the sun, and it was given to him to scorch men with fire. 9 People were scorched with great heat, and people blasphemed the name of God who has the power over these plagues. They didn’t repent and give him glory.

10 The fifth poured out his bowl on the throne of the beast, and his kingdom was darkened. They gnawed their tongues because of the pain, 11 and they blasphemed the God of heaven because of their pains and their sores. They still didn’t repent of their works.

12 The sixth poured out his bowl on the great river, the Euphrates. Its water was dried up, that the way might be prepared for the kings that come from the sunrise.[*] 13 I saw coming out of the mouth of the dragon, and out of the mouth of the beast, and out of the mouth of the false prophet, three unclean spirits, something like frogs; 14 for they are spirits of demons, performing signs, which go out to the kings of the whole inhabited earth, to gather them together for the war of that great day of God the Almighty.

15  “Behold, I come like a thief. Blessed is he who watches, and keeps his clothes, so that he doesn’t walk naked, and they see his shame.” 16 He gathered them together into the place which is called in Hebrew, “Harmagedon”.

17 The seventh poured out his bowl into the air. A loud voice came out of the temple of heaven, from the throne, saying, “It is done!” 18 There were lightnings, sounds, and thunders; and there was a great earthquake such as has not happened since there were men on the earth—so great an earthquake and so mighty. 19 The great city was divided into three parts, and the cities of the nations fell. Babylon the great was remembered in the sight of God, to give to her the cup of the wine of the fierceness of his wrath. 20 Every island fled away, and the mountains were not found. 21 Great hailstones, about the weight of a talent,[†] came down out of the sky on people. People blasphemed God because of the plague of the hail, for this plague was exceedingly severe.

17

1 One of the seven angels who had the seven bowls came and spoke with me, saying, “Come here. I will show you the judgment of the great prostitute who sits on many waters, 2 with whom the kings of the earth committed sexual immorality. Those who dwell in the earth were made drunken with the wine of her sexual immorality.” 3 He carried me away in the Spirit into a wilderness. I saw a woman sitting on a scarlet-colored beast, full of blasphemous names, having seven heads and ten horns. 4 The woman was dressed in purple and scarlet, and decked with gold and precious stones and pearls, having in her hand a golden cup full of abominations and the impurities of the sexual immorality of the earth. 5 And on her forehead a name was written, “MYSTERY, BABYLON THE GREAT, THE MOTHER OF THE PROSTITUTES AND OF THE ABOMINATIONS OF THE EARTH.” 6 I saw the woman drunken with the blood of the saints and with the blood of the martyrs of Jesus. When I saw her, I wondered with great amazement.

7 The angel said to me, “Why do you wonder? I will tell you the mystery of the woman and of the beast that carries her, which has the seven heads and the ten horns. 8 The beast that you saw was, and is not; and is about to come up out of the abyss and to go into destruction. Those who dwell on the earth and whose names have not been written in the book of life from the foundation of the world will marvel when they see that the beast was, and is not, and shall be present.[*]

9 Here is the mind that has wisdom. The seven heads are seven mountains on which the woman sits. 10 They are seven kings. Five have fallen, the one is, and the other has not yet come. When he comes, he must continue a little while. 11 The beast that was, and is not, is himself also an eighth, and is of the seven; and he goes to destruction. 12 The ten horns that you saw are ten kings who have received no kingdom as yet, but they receive authority as kings with the beast for one hour. 13 These have one mind, and they give their power and authority to the beast. 14 These will war against the Lamb, and the Lamb will overcome them, for he is Lord of lords and King of kings; and those who are with him are called, chosen, and faithful.” 15 He said to me, “The waters which you saw, where the prostitute sits, are peoples, multitudes, nations, and languages. 16 The ten horns which you saw, they and the beast will hate the prostitute, will make her desolate, will strip her naked, will eat her flesh, and will burn her utterly with fire. 17 For God has put in their hearts to do what he has in mind, to be of one mind, and to give their kingdom to the beast, until the words of God should be accomplished. 18 The woman whom you saw is the great city which reigns over the kings of the earth.”

18

1 After these things, I saw another angel coming down out of the sky, having great authority. The earth was illuminated with his glory. 2 He cried with a mighty voice, saying, “Fallen, fallen is Babylon the great, and she has become a habitation of demons, a prison of every unclean spirit, and a prison of every unclean and hated bird! 3 For all the nations have drunk of the wine of the wrath of her sexual immorality, the kings of the earth committed sexual immorality with her, and the merchants of the earth grew rich from the abundance of her luxury.”

4 I heard another voice from heaven, saying, “Come out of her, my people, that you have no participation in her sins, and that you don’t receive of her plagues, 5 for her sins have reached to the sky, and God has remembered her iniquities. 6 Return to her just as she returned, and repay her double as she did, and according to her works. In the cup which she mixed, mix to her double. 7 However much she glorified herself and grew wanton, so much give her of torment and mourning. For she says in her heart, ‘I sit a queen, and am no widow, and will in no way see mourning.’ 8 Therefore in one day her plagues will come: death, mourning, and famine; and she will be utterly burned with fire, for the Lord God who has judged her is strong.

9 The kings of the earth who committed sexual immorality and lived wantonly with her will weep and wail over her, when they look at the smoke of her burning, 10 standing far away for the fear of her torment, saying, ‘Woe, woe, the great city, Babylon, the strong city! For your judgment has come in one hour.’ 11 The merchants of the earth weep and mourn over her, for no one buys their merchandise any more: 12 merchandise of gold, silver, precious stones, pearls, fine linen, purple, silk, scarlet, all expensive wood, every vessel of ivory, every vessel made of most precious wood, and of brass, and iron, and marble; 13 and cinnamon, incense, perfume, frankincense, wine, olive oil, fine flour, wheat, sheep, horses, chariots, and people’s bodies and souls. 14 The fruits which your soul lusted after have been lost to you. All things that were dainty and sumptuous have perished from you, and you will find them no more at all. 15 The merchants of these things, who were made rich by her, will stand far away for the fear of her torment, weeping and mourning, 16 saying, ‘Woe, woe, the great city, she who was dressed in fine linen, purple, and scarlet, and decked with gold and precious stones and pearls! 17 For in an hour such great riches are made desolate.’ Every ship master, and everyone who sails anywhere, and mariners, and as many as gain their living by sea, stood far away, 18 and cried out as they looked at the smoke of her burning, saying, ‘What is like the great city?’ 19 They cast dust on their heads, and cried, weeping and mourning, saying, ‘Woe, woe, the great city, in which all who had their ships in the sea were made rich by reason of her great wealth!’ For she is made desolate in one hour.

20 “Rejoice over her, O heaven, you saints, apostles, and prophets, for God has judged your judgment on her.”

21 A mighty angel took up a stone like a great millstone and cast it into the sea, saying, “Thus with violence will Babylon, the great city, be thrown down, and will be found no more at all. 22 The voice of harpists, minstrels, flute players, and trumpeters will be heard no more at all in you. No craftsman of whatever craft will be found any more at all in you. The sound of a mill will be heard no more at all in you. 23 The light of a lamp will shine no more at all in you. The voice of the bridegroom and of the bride will be heard no more at all in you, for your merchants were the princes of the earth; for with your sorcery all the nations were deceived. 24 In her was found the blood of prophets and of saints, and of all who have been slain on the earth.”

19

1 After these things I heard something like a loud voice of a great multitude in heaven, saying, “Hallelujah! Salvation, power, and glory belong to our God; 2 for his judgments are true and righteous. For he has judged the great prostitute who corrupted the earth with her sexual immorality, and he has avenged the blood of his servants at her hand.”

3 A second said, “Hallelujah! Her smoke goes up forever and ever.” 4 The twenty-four elders and the four living creatures fell down and worshiped God who sits on the throne, saying, “Amen! Hallelujah!”

5 A voice came from the throne, saying, “Give praise to our God, all you his servants, you who fear him, the small and the great!”

6 I heard something like the voice of a great multitude, and like the voice of many waters, and like the voice of mighty thunders, saying, “Hallelujah! For the Lord our God, the Almighty, reigns! 7 Let’s rejoice and be exceedingly glad, and let’s give the glory to him. For the wedding of the Lamb has come, and his wife has made herself ready.” 8 It was given to her that she would array herself in bright, pure, fine linen, for the fine linen is the righteous acts of the saints.

9 He said to me, “Write, ‘Blessed are those who are invited to the wedding supper of the Lamb.’ ” He said to me, “These are true words of God.”

10 I fell down before his feet to worship him. He said to me, “Look! Don’t do it! I am a fellow bondservant with you and with your brothers who hold the testimony of Jesus. Worship God, for the testimony of Jesus is the Spirit of Prophecy.”

11 I saw the heaven opened, and behold, a white horse, and he who sat on it is called Faithful and True. In righteousness he judges and makes war. 12 His eyes are a flame of fire, and on his head are many crowns. He has names written and a name written which no one knows but he himself. 13 He is clothed in a garment sprinkled with blood. His name is called “The Word of God.” 14 The armies which are in heaven, clothed in white, pure, fine linen, followed him on white horses. 15 Out of his mouth proceeds a sharp, double-edged sword that with it he should strike the nations. He will rule them with an iron rod.[✡] He treads the wine press of the fierceness of the wrath of God, the Almighty. 16 He has on his garment and on his thigh a name written, “KING OF KINGS AND LORD OF LORDS.”

17 I saw an angel standing in the sun. He cried with a loud voice, saying to all the birds that fly in the sky, “Come! Be gathered together to the great supper of God,[*] 18 that you may eat the flesh of kings, the flesh of captains, the flesh of mighty men, and the flesh of horses and of those who sit on them, and the flesh of all men, both free and slave, small and great.” 19 I saw the beast, the kings of the earth, and their armies, gathered together to make war against him who sat on the horse and against his army. 20 The beast was taken, and with him the false prophet who worked the signs in his sight, with which he deceived those who had received the mark of the beast and those who worshiped his image. These two were thrown alive into the lake of fire that burns with sulfur. 21 The rest were killed with the sword of him who sat on the horse, the sword which came out of his mouth. So all the birds were filled with their flesh.

20

1 I saw an angel coming down out of heaven, having the key of the abyss and a great chain in his hand. 2 He seized the dragon, the old serpent, who is the devil and Satan, who deceives the whole inhabited earth,[*] and bound him for a thousand years, 3 and cast him into the abyss, and shut it and sealed it over him, that he should deceive the nations no more until the thousand years were finished. After this, he must be freed for a short time.

4 I saw thrones, and they sat on them, and judgment was given to them. I saw the souls of those who had been beheaded for the testimony of Jesus and for the word of God, and such as didn’t worship the beast nor his image, and didn’t receive the mark on their forehead and on their hand. They lived and reigned with Christ for a thousand years. 5 The rest of the dead didn’t live until the thousand years were finished. This is the first resurrection. 6 Blessed and holy is he who has part in the first resurrection. Over these, the second death has no power, but they will be priests of God and of Christ, and will reign with him one thousand years.

7 And after the thousand years, Satan will be released from his prison 8 and he will come out to deceive the nations which are in the four corners of the earth, Gog and Magog, to gather them together to the war, whose number is as the sand of the sea. 9 They went up over the width of the earth and surrounded the camp of the saints and the beloved city. Fire came down out of heaven from God and devoured them. 10 The devil who deceived them was thrown into the lake of fire and sulfur, where the beast and the false prophet are also. They will be tormented day and night forever and ever.

11 I saw a great white throne and him who sat on it, from whose face the earth and the heaven fled away. There was found no place for them. 12 I saw the dead, the great and the small, standing before the throne, and they opened books. Another book was opened, which is the book of life. The dead were judged out of the things which were written in the books, according to their works. 13 The sea gave up the dead who were in it. Death and Hades[†] gave up the dead who were in them. They were judged, each one according to his works. 14 Death and Hades[‡] were thrown into the lake of fire. This is the second death, the lake of fire. 15 If anyone was not found written in the book of life, he was cast into the lake of fire.

21

1 I saw a new heaven and a new earth, for the first heaven and the first earth have passed away, and the sea is no more. 2 I saw the holy city, New Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, prepared like a bride adorned for her husband. 3 I heard a loud voice out of heaven saying, “Behold, God’s dwelling is with people; and he will dwell with them, and they will be his people, and God himself will be with them as their God. 4 He will wipe away every tear from their eyes. Death will be no more; neither will there be mourning, nor crying, nor pain any more. The first things have passed away.”

5 He who sits on the throne said, “Behold, I am making all things new.” He said, “Write, for these words of God are faithful and true.” 6 He said to me, “I am the Alpha and the Omega, the Beginning and the End. I will give freely to him who is thirsty from the spring of the water of life. 7  He who overcomes, I will give him these things. I will be his God, and he will be my son. 8  But for the cowardly, unbelieving, sinners,[*] abominable, murderers, sexually immoral, sorcerers,[†] idolaters, and all liars, their part is in the lake that burns with fire and sulfur, which is the second death.”

9 One of the seven angels who had the seven bowls which were loaded with the seven last plagues came, and he spoke with me, saying, “Come here. I will show you the bride, the Lamb’s wife.” 10 He carried me away in the Spirit to a great and high mountain, and showed me the holy city, Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, 11 having the glory of God. Her light was like a most precious stone, like a jasper stone, clear as crystal; 12 having a great and high wall with twelve gates, and at the gates twelve angels, and names written on them, which are the names of the twelve tribes of the children of Israel. 13 On the east were three gates, and on the north three gates, and on the south three gates, and on the west three gates. 14 The wall of the city had twelve foundations, and on them twelve names of the twelve Apostles of the Lamb.

15 He who spoke with me had for a measure a golden reed to measure the city, its gates, and its walls. 16 The city is square. Its length is as great as its width. He measured the city with the reed: twelve thousand twelve stadia.[‡] Its length, width, and height are equal. 17 Its wall is one hundred forty-four cubits,[§] by the measure of a man, that is, of an angel. 18 The construction of its wall was jasper. The city was pure gold, like pure glass. 19 The foundations of the city’s wall were adorned with all kinds of precious stones. The first foundation was jasper, the second sapphire;[*] the third chalcedony, the fourth emerald, 20 the fifth sardonyx, the sixth sardius, the seventh chrysolite, the eighth beryl, the ninth topaz, the tenth chrysoprase, the eleventh jacinth, and the twelfth amethyst. 21 The twelve gates were twelve pearls. Each one of the gates was made of one pearl. The street of the city was pure gold, like transparent glass.

22 I saw no temple in it, for the Lord God the Almighty and the Lamb are its temple. 23 The city has no need for the sun or moon to shine, for the very glory of God illuminated it and its lamp is the Lamb. 24 The nations will walk in its light. The kings of the earth bring the glory and honor of the nations into it. 25 Its gates will in no way be shut by day (for there will be no night there), 26 and they shall bring the glory and the honor of the nations into it so that they may enter. 27 There will in no way enter into it anything profane, or one who causes an abomination or a lie, but only those who are written in the Lamb’s book of life.

22

1 He showed me a[*] river of water of life, clear as crystal, proceeding out of the throne of God and of the Lamb, 2 in the middle of its street. On this side of the river and on that was the tree of life, bearing twelve kinds of fruits, yielding its fruit every month. The leaves of the tree were for the healing of the nations. 3 There will be no curse any more. The throne of God and of the Lamb will be in it, and his servants will serve him. 4 They will see his face, and his name will be on their foreheads. 5 There will be no night, and they need no lamp light or sun light; for the Lord God will illuminate them. They will reign forever and ever.

6 He said to me, “These words are faithful and true. The Lord God of the spirits of the prophets sent his angel to show to his bondservants the things which must happen soon.”

7  “Behold, I am coming soon! Blessed is he who keeps the words of the prophecy of this book.”

8 Now I, John, am the one who heard and saw these things. When I heard and saw, I fell down to worship before the feet of the angel who had shown me these things. 9 He said to me, “You must not do that! I am a fellow bondservant with you and with your brothers, the prophets, and with those who keep the words of this book. Worship God.” 10 He said to me, “Don’t seal up the words of the prophecy of this book, for the time is at hand. 11 He who acts unjustly, let him act unjustly still. He who is filthy, let him be filthy still. He who is righteous, let him do righteousness still. He who is holy, let him be holy still.”

12  “Behold, I am coming soon! My reward is with me, to repay to each man according to his work. 13  I am the Alpha and the Omega, the First and the Last, the Beginning and the End. 14  Blessed are those who do his commandments,[†] that they may have the right to the tree of life, and may enter in by the gates into the city. 15  Outside are the dogs, the sorcerers, the sexually immoral, the murderers, the idolaters, and everyone who loves and practices falsehood. 16  I, Jesus, have sent my angel to testify these things to you for the assemblies. I am the root and the offspring of David, the Bright and Morning Star.”

17 The Spirit and the bride say, “Come!” He who hears, let him say, “Come!” He who is thirsty, let him come. He who desires, let him take the water of life freely.

18 I testify to everyone who hears the words of the prophecy of this book: if anyone adds to them, God will add to him the plagues which are written in this book. 19 If anyone takes away from the words of the book of this prophecy, God will take away his part from the tree[‡] of life, and out of the holy city, which are written in this book. 20 He who testifies these things says, “Yes, I am coming soon.”

Amen! Yes, come, Lord Jesus!

21 The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with all the saints. Amen.

* 1:1 “Christ” means “Anointed One”.

† 1:1 or, messenger (here and wherever angel is mentioned)

✡ 1:6 Exodus 19:6; Isaiah 61:6

‡ 1:7 “Behold”, from “ἰδοὺ”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

§ 1:8 TR adds “the Beginning and the End”

* 1:8 TR omits “God”

† 1:11 TR adds “I am the Alpha and the Omega, the First and the Last.”

‡ 1:11 TR adds “which are in Asia”

✡ 1:13 Daniel 7:13

§ 1:18 or, Hell

* 1:20 or, messengers (here and wherever angels are mentioned)

* 2:3 TR adds “have labored and”

† 2:15 TR reads “which I hate” instead of “likewise”

‡ 2:17 Manna is supernatural food, named after the Hebrew for “What is it?”. See Exodus 11:7-9.

§ 2:20 TR, NU read “that” instead of “your”

✡ 2:27 Psalm 2:9

* 3:2 NU & TR read “which were about to die” instead of “which you were about to throw away”.

† 3:14 or, Source, or Head

* 4:8 Hodges/Farstad MT reads “holy” 9 times instead of 3.

† 4:11 TR omits “and God, the Holy One,”

* 5:13 TR omits “Amen!”

† 5:14 TR adds “twenty-four”

‡ 5:14 TR adds “the one living forever and ever”

* 6:6 A choenix is a dry volume measure that is a little more than a liter (a little more than a quart).

† 6:8 or, Hell

‡ 6:11 The word for “brothers” here and where context allows may also be correctly translated “brothers and sisters” or “siblings.”

* 7:14 or, oppression

* 8:7 TR omits “One third of the earth was burned up”

† 8:13 TR reads “angel” instead of “eagle”

* 9:2 TR adds “great”

† 9:11 “Abaddon” is a Hebrew word that means “ruin”, “destruction”, or “the place of destruction”

‡ 9:11 “Apollyon” means “Destroyer”.

§ 9:16 literally, “ten thousands of ten thousands”

* 9:21 The word for “sorceries” (pharmakeia) also implies the use of potions, poisons, and drugs

* 10:11 TR reads “He” instead of “They”

* 11:17 TR adds “and who is coming”

* 12:17 or, seed

* 13:10 TR reads “If anyone leads into captivity, into captivity he goes. If anyone will kill with the sword, he must be killed with a sword.” instead of “If anyone is to go into captivity, he will go into captivity. If anyone is to be killed with the sword, he must be killed.”

† 13:14 NU omits “my own”

* 14:5 TR adds “before the throne of God”

✡ 14:14 Daniel 7:13

† 14:20 1600 stadia = 296 kilometers or 184 miles

* 15:2 TR adds “his mark,”

* 16:12 or, east

† 16:21 A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds.

* 17:8 TR reads “yet is” instead of “shall be present”

✡ 19:15 Psalm 2:9

* 19:17 TR reads “supper of the great God” instead of “great supper of God”

* 20:2 TR and NU omit “who deceives the whole inhabited earth”.

† 20:13 or, Hell

‡ 20:14 or, Hell

* 21:8 TR and NU omit “sinners”

† 21:8 The word for “sorcerers” here also includes users of potions and drugs.

‡ 21:16 12,012 stadia = or 2,221 kilometers or 1,380 miles. TR reads 12,000 stadia instead of 12,012 stadia.

§ 21:17 144 cubits is about 65.8 meters or 216 feet

* 21:19 or, lapis lazuli

* 22:1 TR adds “pure”

† 22:14 NU reads “wash their robes” instead of “do his commandments”.

‡ 22:19 TR reads “Book” instead of “tree”

Romans

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16

Paul’s Letter to the

Romans

1

1 Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ,[*] called to be an apostle, set apart for the Good News of God, 2 which he promised before through his prophets in the holy Scriptures, 3 concerning his Son, who was born of the offspring[†] of David according to the flesh, 4 who was declared to be the Son of God with power according to the Spirit of holiness, by the resurrection from the dead, Jesus Christ our Lord, 5 through whom we received grace and apostleship for obedience of faith among all the nations for his name’s sake; 6 among whom you are also called to belong to Jesus Christ; 7 to all who are in Rome, beloved of God, called to be saints: Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

8 First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for all of you, that your faith is proclaimed throughout the whole world. 9 For God is my witness, whom I serve in my spirit in the Good News of his Son, how unceasingly I make mention of you always in my prayers, 10 requesting, if by any means now at last I may be prospered by the will of God to come to you. 11 For I long to see you, that I may impart to you some spiritual gift, to the end that you may be established; 12 that is, that I with you may be encouraged in you, each of us by the other’s faith, both yours and mine.

13 Now I don’t desire to have you unaware, brothers, that I often planned to come to you (and was hindered so far), that I might have some fruit among you also, even as among the rest of the Gentiles. 14 I am debtor both to Greeks and to foreigners, both to the wise and to the foolish. 15 So as much as is in me, I am eager to preach the Good News to you also who are in Rome.

16 For I am not ashamed of the Good News of Christ, because it is the power of God for salvation for everyone who believes, for the Jew first, and also for the Greek. 17 For in it is revealed God’s righteousness from faith to faith. As it is written, “But the righteous shall live by faith.”[✡]

18 For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men who suppress the truth in unrighteousness, 19 because that which is known of God is revealed in them, for God revealed it to them. 20 For the invisible things of him since the creation of the world are clearly seen, being perceived through the things that are made, even his everlasting power and divinity, that they may be without excuse. 21 Because knowing God, they didn’t glorify him as God, and didn’t give thanks, but became vain in their reasoning, and their senseless heart was darkened.

22 Professing themselves to be wise, they became fools, 23 and traded the glory of the incorruptible God for the likeness of an image of corruptible man, and of birds, four-footed animals, and creeping things. 24 Therefore God also gave them up in the lusts of their hearts to uncleanness, that their bodies should be dishonored among themselves; 25 who exchanged the truth of God for a lie, and worshiped and served the creature rather than the Creator, who is blessed forever. Amen.

26 For this reason, God gave them up to vile passions. For their women changed the natural function into that which is against nature. 27 Likewise also the men, leaving the natural function of the woman, burned in their lust toward one another, men doing what is inappropriate with men, and receiving in themselves the due penalty of their error. 28 Even as they refused to have God in their knowledge, God gave them up to a reprobate mind, to do those things which are not fitting; 29 being filled with all unrighteousness, sexual immorality, wickedness, covetousness, malice; full of envy, murder, strife, deceit, evil habits, secret slanderers, 30 backbiters, hateful to God, insolent, arrogant, boastful, inventors of evil things, disobedient to parents, 31 without understanding, covenant breakers, without natural affection, unforgiving, unmerciful; 32 who, knowing the ordinance of God, that those who practice such things are worthy of death, not only do the same, but also approve of those who practice them.

2

1 Therefore you are without excuse, O man, whoever you are who judge. For in that which you judge another, you condemn yourself. For you who judge practice the same things. 2 We know that the judgment of God is according to truth against those who practice such things. 3 Do you think this, O man who judges those who practice such things, and do the same, that you will escape the judgment of God? 4 Or do you despise the riches of his goodness, forbearance, and patience, not knowing that the goodness of God leads you to repentance? 5 But according to your hardness and unrepentant heart you are treasuring up for yourself wrath in the day of wrath, revelation, and of the righteous judgment of God, 6 who “will pay back to everyone according to their works:”[✡] 7 to those who by perseverance in well-doing seek for glory, honor, and incorruptibility, eternal life; 8 but to those who are self-seeking and don’t obey the truth, but obey unrighteousness, will be wrath, indignation, 9 oppression, and anguish on every soul of man who does evil, to the Jew first, and also to the Greek.

10 But glory, honor, and peace go to every man who does good, to the Jew first, and also to the Greek. 11 For there is no partiality with God. 12 For as many as have sinned without the law will also perish without the law. As many as have sinned under the law will be judged by the law. 13 For it isn’t the hearers of the law who are righteous before God, but the doers of the law will be justified 14 (for when Gentiles who don’t have the law do by nature the things of the law, these, not having the law, are a law to themselves, 15 in that they show the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience testifying with them, and their thoughts among themselves accusing or else excusing them) 16 in the day when God will judge the secrets of men, according to my Good News, by Jesus Christ.

17 Indeed you bear the name of a Jew, rest on the law, glory in God, 18 know his will, and approve the things that are excellent, being instructed out of the law, 19 and are confident that you yourself are a guide of the blind, a light to those who are in darkness, 20 a corrector of the foolish, a teacher of babies, having in the law the form of knowledge and of the truth. 21 You therefore who teach another, don’t you teach yourself? You who preach that a man shouldn’t steal, do you steal? 22 You who say a man shouldn’t commit adultery, do you commit adultery? You who abhor idols, do you rob temples? 23 You who glory in the law, do you dishonor God by disobeying the law? 24 For “the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles because of you,” [✡] just as it is written. 25 For circumcision indeed profits, if you are a doer of the law, but if you are a transgressor of the law, your circumcision has become uncircumcision. 26 If therefore the uncircumcised keep the ordinances of the law, won’t his uncircumcision be accounted as circumcision? 27 Won’t those who are physically uncircumcised, but fulfill the law, judge you, who with the letter and circumcision are a transgressor of the law? 28 For he is not a Jew who is one outwardly, neither is that circumcision which is outward in the flesh; 29 but he is a Jew who is one inwardly, and circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit, not in the letter; whose praise is not from men, but from God.

3

1 Then what advantage does the Jew have? Or what is the profit of circumcision? 2 Much in every way! Because first of all, they were entrusted with the revelations of God. 3 For what if some were without faith? Will their lack of faith nullify the faithfulness of God? 4 May it never be! Yes, let God be found true, but every man a liar. As it is written,

“that you might be justified in your words,

and might prevail when you come into judgment.”[✡]

5 But if our unrighteousness commends the righteousness of God, what will we say? Is God unrighteous who inflicts wrath? I speak like men do. 6 May it never be! For then how will God judge the world? 7 For if the truth of God through my lie abounded to his glory, why am I also still judged as a sinner? 8 Why not (as we are slanderously reported, and as some affirm that we say), “Let’s do evil, that good may come?” Those who say so are justly condemned.

9 What then? Are we better than they? No, in no way. For we previously warned both Jews and Greeks that they are all under sin. 10 As it is written,

“There is no one righteous;

no, not one.

11 There is no one who understands.

There is no one who seeks after God.

12 They have all turned away.

They have together become unprofitable.

There is no one who does good,

no, not so much as one.”[✡]

13 “Their throat is an open tomb.

With their tongues they have used deceit.”[✡]

“The poison of vipers is under their lips.”[✡]

14 “Their mouth is full of cursing and bitterness.”[✡]

15 “Their feet are swift to shed blood.

16 Destruction and misery are in their ways.

17 The way of peace, they haven’t known.”[✡]

18 “There is no fear of God before their eyes.”[✡]

19 Now we know that whatever things the law says, it speaks to those who are under the law, that every mouth may be closed, and all the world may be brought under the judgment of God. 20 Because by the works of the law, no flesh will be justified in his sight; for through the law comes the knowledge of sin.

21 But now apart from the law, a righteousness of God has been revealed, being testified by the law and the prophets; 22 even the righteousness of God through faith in Jesus Christ to all and on all those who believe. For there is no distinction, 23 for all have sinned, and fall short of the glory of God; 24 being justified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Christ Jesus, 25 whom God sent to be an atoning sacrifice[*] through faith in his blood, for a demonstration of his righteousness through the passing over of prior sins, in God’s forbearance; 26 to demonstrate his righteousness at this present time, that he might himself be just and the justifier of him who has faith in Jesus.

27 Where then is the boasting? It is excluded. By what kind of law? Of works? No, but by a law of faith. 28 We maintain therefore that a man is justified by faith apart from the works of the law. 29 Or is God the God of Jews only? Isn’t he the God of Gentiles also? Yes, of Gentiles also, 30 since indeed there is one God who will justify the circumcised by faith and the uncircumcised through faith.

31 Do we then nullify the law through faith? May it never be! No, we establish the law.

4

1 What then will we say that Abraham, our forefather, has found according to the flesh? 2 For if Abraham was justified by works, he has something to boast about, but not toward God. 3 For what does the Scripture say? “Abraham believed God, and it was accounted to him for righteousness.”[✡] 4 Now to him who works, the reward is not counted as grace, but as something owed. 5 But to him who doesn’t work, but believes in him who justifies the ungodly, his faith is accounted for righteousness. 6 Even as David also pronounces blessing on the man to whom God counts righteousness apart from works:

7 “Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven,

whose sins are covered.

8 Blessed is the man whom the Lord will by no means charge with sin.” [✡]

9 Is this blessing then pronounced only on the circumcised, or on the uncircumcised also? For we say that faith was accounted to Abraham for righteousness. 10 How then was it counted? When he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision. 11 He received the sign of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith which he had while he was in uncircumcision, that he might be the father of all those who believe, though they might be in uncircumcision, that righteousness might also be accounted to them. 12 He is the father of circumcision to those who not only are of the circumcision, but who also walk in the steps of that faith of our father Abraham, which he had in uncircumcision.

13 For the promise to Abraham and to his offspring that he would be heir of the world wasn’t through the law, but through the righteousness of faith. 14 For if those who are of the law are heirs, faith is made void, and the promise is made of no effect. 15 For the law produces wrath; for where there is no law, neither is there disobedience.

16 For this cause it is of faith, that it may be according to grace, to the end that the promise may be sure to all the offspring, not to that only which is of the law, but to that also which is of the faith of Abraham, who is the father of us all. 17 As it is written, “I have made you a father of many nations.”[✡] This is in the presence of him whom he believed: God, who gives life to the dead, and calls the things that are not, as though they were. 18 Against hope, Abraham in hope believed, to the end that he might become a father of many nations, according to that which had been spoken, “So will your offspring be.”[✡] 19 Without being weakened in faith, he didn’t consider his own body, already having been worn out, (he being about a hundred years old), and the deadness of Sarah’s womb. 20 Yet, looking to the promise of God, he didn’t waver through unbelief, but grew strong through faith, giving glory to God, 21 and being fully assured that what he had promised, he was also able to perform. 22 Therefore it also was “credited to him for righteousness.”[✡] 23 Now it was not written that it was accounted to him for his sake alone, 24 but for our sake also, to whom it will be accounted, who believe in him who raised Jesus our Lord from the dead, 25 who was delivered up for our trespasses, and was raised for our justification.

5

1 Being therefore justified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ; 2 through whom we also have our access by faith into this grace in which we stand. We rejoice in hope of the glory of God. 3 Not only this, but we also rejoice in our sufferings, knowing that suffering produces perseverance; 4 and perseverance, proven character; and proven character, hope; 5 and hope doesn’t disappoint us, because God’s love has been poured into our hearts through the Holy Spirit who was given to us.

6 For while we were yet weak, at the right time Christ died for the ungodly. 7 For one will hardly die for a righteous man. Yet perhaps for a good person someone would even dare to die. 8 But God commends his own love toward us, in that while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.

9 Much more then, being now justified by his blood, we will be saved from God’s wrath through him. 10 For if while we were enemies, we were reconciled to God through the death of his Son, much more, being reconciled, we will be saved by his life.

11 Not only so, but we also rejoice in God through our Lord Jesus Christ, through whom we have now received the reconciliation. 12 Therefore, as sin entered into the world through one man, and death through sin, so death passed to all men because all sinned. 13 For until the law, sin was in the world; but sin is not charged when there is no law. 14 Nevertheless death reigned from Adam until Moses, even over those whose sins weren’t like Adam’s disobedience, who is a foreshadowing of him who was to come.

15 But the free gift isn’t like the trespass. For if by the trespass of the one the many died, much more did the grace of God and the gift by the grace of the one man, Jesus Christ, abound to the many. 16 The gift is not as through one who sinned; for the judgment came by one to condemnation, but the free gift followed many trespasses to justification. 17 For if by the trespass of the one, death reigned through the one; so much more will those who receive the abundance of grace and of the gift of righteousness reign in life through the one, Jesus Christ.

18 So then as through one trespass, all men were condemned; even so through one act of righteousness, all men were justified to life. 19 For as through the one man’s disobedience many were made sinners, even so through the obedience of the one, many will be made righteous. 20 The law came in that the trespass might abound; but where sin abounded, grace abounded more exceedingly, 21 that as sin reigned in death, even so grace might reign through righteousness to eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord.

6

1 What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound? 2 May it never be! We who died to sin, how could we live in it any longer? 3 Or don’t you know that all of us who were baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death? 4 We were buried therefore with him through baptism into death, that just as Christ was raised from the dead through the glory of the Father, so we also might walk in newness of life.

5 For if we have become united with him in the likeness of his death, we will also be part of his resurrection; 6 knowing this, that our old man was crucified with him, that the body of sin might be done away with, so that we would no longer be in bondage to sin. 7 For he who has died has been freed from sin. 8 But if we died with Christ, we believe that we will also live with him, 9 knowing that Christ, being raised from the dead, dies no more. Death no longer has dominion over him! 10 For the death that he died, he died to sin one time; but the life that he lives, he lives to God. 11 Thus consider yourselves also to be dead to sin, but alive to God in Christ Jesus our Lord.

12 Therefore don’t let sin reign in your mortal body, that you should obey it in its lusts. 13 Also, do not present your members to sin as instruments of unrighteousness, but present yourselves to God as alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness to God. 14 For sin will not have dominion over you, for you are not under law, but under grace.

15 What then? Shall we sin because we are not under law but under grace? May it never be! 16 Don’t you know that when you present yourselves as servants and obey someone, you are the servants of whomever you obey, whether of sin to death, or of obedience to righteousness? 17 But thanks be to God that, whereas you were bondservants of sin, you became obedient from the heart to that form of teaching to which you were delivered. 18 Being made free from sin, you became bondservants of righteousness.

19 I speak in human terms because of the weakness of your flesh; for as you presented your members as servants to uncleanness and to wickedness upon wickedness, even so now present your members as servants to righteousness for sanctification. 20 For when you were servants of sin, you were free from righteousness. 21 What fruit then did you have at that time in the things of which you are now ashamed? For the end of those things is death. 22 But now, being made free from sin and having become servants of God, you have your fruit of sanctification and the result of eternal life. 23 For the wages of sin is death, but the free gift of God is eternal life in Christ Jesus our Lord.

7

1 Or don’t you know, brothers[*] (for I speak to men who know the law), that the law has dominion over a man for as long as he lives? 2 For the woman that has a husband is bound by law to the husband while he lives, but if the husband dies, she is discharged from the law of the husband. 3 So then if, while the husband lives, she is joined to another man, she would be called an adulteress. But if the husband dies, she is free from the law, so that she is no adulteress, though she is joined to another man. 4 Therefore, my brothers, you also were made dead to the law through the body of Christ, that you would be joined to another, to him who was raised from the dead, that we might produce fruit to God. 5 For when we were in the flesh, the sinful passions which were through the law worked in our members to bring out fruit to death. 6 But now we have been discharged from the law, having died to that in which we were held; so that we serve in newness of the spirit, and not in oldness of the letter.

7 What shall we say then? Is the law sin? May it never be! However, I wouldn’t have known sin except through the law. For I wouldn’t have known coveting unless the law had said, “You shall not covet.”[✡] 8 But sin, finding occasion through the commandment, produced in me all kinds of coveting. For apart from the law, sin is dead. 9 I was alive apart from the law once, but when the commandment came, sin revived and I died. 10 The commandment which was for life, this I found to be for death; 11 for sin, finding occasion through the commandment, deceived me, and through it killed me. 12 Therefore the law indeed is holy, and the commandment holy, righteous, and good.

13 Did then that which is good become death to me? May it never be! But sin, that it might be shown to be sin, was producing death in me through that which is good; that through the commandment sin might become exceedingly sinful. 14 For we know that the law is spiritual, but I am fleshly, sold under sin. 15 For I don’t understand what I am doing. For I don’t practice what I desire to do; but what I hate, that I do. 16 But if what I don’t desire, that I do, I consent to the law that it is good. 17 So now it is no more I that do it, but sin which dwells in me. 18 For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, dwells no good thing. For desire is present with me, but I don’t find it doing that which is good. 19 For the good which I desire, I don’t do; but the evil which I don’t desire, that I practice. 20 But if what I don’t desire, that I do, it is no more I that do it, but sin which dwells in me. 21 I find then the law that, while I desire to do good, evil is present. 22 For I delight in God’s law after the inward person, 23 but I see a different law in my members, warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity under the law of sin which is in my members. 24 What a wretched man I am! Who will deliver me out of the body of this death? 25 I thank God through Jesus Christ, our Lord! So then with the mind, I myself serve God’s law, but with the flesh, sin’s law.

8

1 There is therefore now no condemnation to those who are in Christ Jesus, who don’t walk according to the flesh, but according to the Spirit.[*] 2 For the law of the Spirit of life in Christ Jesus made me free from the law of sin and of death. 3 For what the law couldn’t do, in that it was weak through the flesh, God did, sending his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh and for sin, he condemned sin in the flesh, 4 that the ordinance of the law might be fulfilled in us who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit. 5 For those who live according to the flesh set their minds on the things of the flesh, but those who live according to the Spirit, the things of the Spirit. 6 For the mind of the flesh is death, but the mind of the Spirit is life and peace; 7 because the mind of the flesh is hostile toward God, for it is not subject to God’s law, neither indeed can it be. 8 Those who are in the flesh can’t please God.

9 But you are not in the flesh but in the Spirit, if it is so that the Spirit of God dwells in you. But if any man doesn’t have the Spirit of Christ, he is not his. 10 If Christ is in you, the body is dead because of sin, but the spirit is alive because of righteousness. 11 But if the Spirit of him who raised up Jesus from the dead dwells in you, he who raised up Christ Jesus from the dead will also give life to your mortal bodies through his Spirit who dwells in you.

12 So then, brothers, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live after the flesh. 13 For if you live after the flesh, you must die; but if by the Spirit you put to death the deeds of the body, you will live. 14 For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, these are children of God. 15 For you didn’t receive the spirit of bondage again to fear, but you received the Spirit of adoption, by whom we cry, “Abba![†] Father!”

16 The Spirit himself testifies with our spirit that we are children of God; 17 and if children, then heirs—heirs of God and joint heirs with Christ, if indeed we suffer with him, that we may also be glorified with him.

18 For I consider that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which will be revealed toward us. 19 For the creation waits with eager expectation for the children of God to be revealed. 20 For the creation was subjected to vanity, not of its own will, but because of him who subjected it, in hope 21 that the creation itself also will be delivered from the bondage of decay into the liberty of the glory of the children of God. 22 For we know that the whole creation groans and travails in pain together until now. 23 Not only so, but ourselves also, who have the first fruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves, waiting for adoption, the redemption of our body. 24 For we were saved in hope, but hope that is seen is not hope. For who hopes for that which he sees? 25 But if we hope for that which we don’t see, we wait for it with patience.

26 In the same way, the Spirit also helps our weaknesses, for we don’t know how to pray as we ought. But the Spirit himself makes intercession for us with groanings which can’t be uttered. 27 He who searches the hearts knows what is on the Spirit’s mind, because he makes intercession for the saints according to God.

28 We know that all things work together for good for those who love God, for those who are called according to his purpose. 29 For whom he foreknew, he also predestined to be conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be the firstborn among many brothers.[‡] 30 Whom he predestined, those he also called. Whom he called, those he also justified. Whom he justified, those he also glorified.

31 What then shall we say about these things? If God is for us, who can be against us? 32 He who didn’t spare his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how would he not also with him freely give us all things? 33 Who could bring a charge against God’s chosen ones? It is God who justifies. 34 Who is he who condemns? It is Christ who died, yes rather, who was raised from the dead, who is at the right hand of God, who also makes intercession for us.

35 Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? Could oppression, or anguish, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword? 36 Even as it is written,

“For your sake we are killed all day long.

We were accounted as sheep for the slaughter.”[✡]

37 No, in all these things we are more than conquerors through him who loved us. 38 For I am persuaded that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers, 39 nor height, nor depth, nor any other created thing will be able to separate us from God’s love which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

9

1 I tell the truth in Christ. I am not lying, my conscience testifying with me in the Holy Spirit 2 that I have great sorrow and unceasing pain in my heart. 3 For I could wish that I myself were accursed from Christ for my brothers’ sake, my relatives according to the flesh 4 who are Israelites; whose is the adoption, the glory, the covenants, the giving of the law, the service, and the promises; 5 of whom are the fathers, and from whom is Christ as concerning the flesh, who is over all, God, blessed forever. Amen.

6 But it is not as though the word of God has come to nothing. For they are not all Israel that are of Israel. 7 Neither, because they are Abraham’s offspring, are they all children. But, “your offspring will be accounted as from Isaac.”[✡] 8 That is, it is not the children of the flesh who are children of God, but the children of the promise are counted as heirs. 9 For this is a word of promise: “At the appointed time I will come, and Sarah will have a son.”[✡] 10 Not only so, but Rebekah also conceived by one, by our father Isaac. 11 For being not yet born, neither having done anything good or bad, that the purpose of God according to election might stand, not of works, but of him who calls,[*] 12 it was said to her, “The elder will serve the younger.”[✡] 13 Even as it is written, “Jacob I loved, but Esau I hated.”[✡]

14 What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? May it never be! 15 For he said to Moses, “I will have mercy on whom I have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I have compassion.”[✡] 16 So then it is not of him who wills, nor of him who runs, but of God who has mercy. 17 For the Scripture says to Pharaoh, “For this very purpose I caused you to be raised up, that I might show in you my power, and that my name might be proclaimed in all the earth.”[✡] 18 So then, he has mercy on whom he desires, and he hardens whom he desires.

19 You will say then to me, “Why does he still find fault? For who withstands his will?” 20 But indeed, O man, who are you to reply against God? Will the thing formed ask him who formed it, “Why did you make me like this?”[✡] 21 Or hasn’t the potter a right over the clay, from the same lump to make one part a vessel for honor, and another for dishonor? 22 What if God, willing to show his wrath and to make his power known, endured with much patience vessels of wrath prepared for destruction, 23 and that he might make known the riches of his glory on vessels of mercy, which he prepared beforehand for glory— 24 us, whom he also called, not from the Jews only, but also from the Gentiles? 25 As he says also in Hosea,

“I will call them ‘my people,’ which were not my people;

and her ‘beloved,’ who was not beloved.”[✡]

26 “It will be that in the place where it was said to them, ‘You are not my people,’

there they will be called ‘children of the living God.’ ”[✡]

27 Isaiah cries concerning Israel,

“If the number of the children of Israel are as the sand of the sea,

it is the remnant who will be saved;

28 for He will finish the work and cut it short in righteousness,

because the LORD will make a short work upon the earth.”[✡]

29 As Isaiah has said before,

“Unless the Lord of Armies[†] had left us a seed,

we would have become like Sodom,

and would have been made like Gomorrah.”[✡]

30 What shall we say then? That the Gentiles, who didn’t follow after righteousness, attained to righteousness, even the righteousness which is of faith; 31 but Israel, following after a law of righteousness, didn’t arrive at the law of righteousness. 32 Why? Because they didn’t seek it by faith, but as it were by works of the law. They stumbled over the stumbling stone, 33 even as it is written,

“Behold,[‡] I lay in Zion a stumbling stone and a rock of offense;

and no one who believes in him will be disappointed.”[✡]

10

1 Brothers, my heart’s desire and my prayer to God is for Israel, that they may be saved. 2 For I testify about them that they have a zeal for God, but not according to knowledge. 3 For being ignorant of God’s righteousness, and seeking to establish their own righteousness, they didn’t subject themselves to the righteousness of God. 4 For Christ is the fulfillment[*] of the law for righteousness to everyone who believes.

5 For Moses writes about the righteousness of the law, “The one who does them will live by them.”[✡] 6 But the righteousness which is of faith says this, “Don’t say in your heart, ‘Who will ascend into heaven?’[✡] (that is, to bring Christ down); 7 or, ‘Who will descend into the abyss?’[✡] (that is, to bring Christ up from the dead.)” 8 But what does it say? “The word is near you, in your mouth and in your heart;”[✡] that is, the word of faith which we preach: 9 that if you will confess with your mouth that Jesus is Lord and believe in your heart that God raised him from the dead, you will be saved. 10 For with the heart one believes resulting in righteousness; and with the mouth confession is made resulting in salvation. 11 For the Scripture says, “Whoever believes in him will not be disappointed.”[✡]

12 For there is no distinction between Jew and Greek; for the same Lord is Lord of all, and is rich to all who call on him. 13 For, “Whoever will call on the name of the Lord will be saved.”[✡] 14 How then will they call on him in whom they have not believed? How will they believe in him whom they have not heard? How will they hear without a preacher? 15 And how will they preach unless they are sent? As it is written:

“How beautiful are the feet of those who preach the Good News of peace,

who bring glad tidings of good things!”[✡]

16 But they didn’t all listen to the glad news. For Isaiah says, “Lord, who has believed our report?”[✡] 17 So faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God. 18 But I say, didn’t they hear? Yes, most certainly,

“Their sound went out into all the earth,

their words to the ends of the world.”[✡]

19 But I ask, didn’t Israel know? First Moses says,

“I will provoke you to jealousy with that which is no nation.

I will make you angry with a nation void of understanding.”[✡]

20 Isaiah is very bold and says,

“I was found by those who didn’t seek me.

I was revealed to those who didn’t ask for me.”[✡]

21 But about Israel he says, “All day long I stretched out my hands to a disobedient and contrary people.”[✡]

11

1 I ask then, did God reject his people? May it never be! For I also am an Israelite, a descendant of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin. 2 God didn’t reject his people, whom he foreknew. Or don’t you know what the Scripture says about Elijah? How he pleads with God against Israel: 3 “Lord, they have killed your prophets. They have broken down your altars. I am left alone, and they seek my life.”[✡] 4 But how does God answer him? “I have reserved for myself seven thousand men who have not bowed the knee to Baal.”[✡] 5 Even so too at this present time also there is a remnant according to the election of grace. 6 And if by grace, then it is no longer of works; otherwise grace is no longer grace. But if it is of works, it is no longer grace; otherwise work is no longer work.

7 What then? That which Israel seeks for, that he didn’t obtain, but the chosen ones obtained it, and the rest were hardened. 8 According as it is written, “God gave them a spirit of stupor, eyes that they should not see, and ears that they should not hear, to this very day.” [✡]

9 David says,

“Let their table be made a snare, a trap,

a stumbling block, and a retribution to them.

10 Let their eyes be darkened, that they may not see.

Always keep their backs bent.”[✡]

11 I ask then, did they stumble that they might fall? May it never be! But by their fall salvation has come to the Gentiles, to provoke them to jealousy. 12 Now if their fall is the riches of the world, and their loss the riches of the Gentiles, how much more their fullness!

13 For I speak to you who are Gentiles. Since then as I am an apostle to Gentiles, I glorify my ministry, 14 if by any means I may provoke to jealousy those who are my flesh, and may save some of them. 15 For if the rejection of them is the reconciling of the world, what would their acceptance be, but life from the dead?

16 If the first fruit is holy, so is the lump. If the root is holy, so are the branches. 17 But if some of the branches were broken off, and you, being a wild olive, were grafted in among them and became partaker with them of the root and of the richness of the olive tree, 18 don’t boast over the branches. But if you boast, remember that it is not you who support the root, but the root supports you. 19 You will say then, “Branches were broken off, that I might be grafted in.” 20 True; by their unbelief they were broken off, and you stand by your faith. Don’t be conceited, but fear; 21 for if God didn’t spare the natural branches, neither will he spare you. 22 See then the goodness and severity of God. Toward those who fell, severity; but toward you, goodness, if you continue in his goodness; otherwise you also will be cut off. 23 They also, if they don’t continue in their unbelief, will be grafted in, for God is able to graft them in again. 24 For if you were cut out of that which is by nature a wild olive tree, and were grafted contrary to nature into a good olive tree, how much more will these, which are the natural branches, be grafted into their own olive tree?

25 For I don’t desire you to be ignorant, brothers,[*] of this mystery, so that you won’t be wise in your own conceits, that a partial hardening has happened to Israel, until the fullness of the Gentiles has come in, 26 and so all Israel will be saved. Even as it is written,

“There will come out of Zion the Deliverer,

and he will turn away ungodliness from Jacob.

27 This is my covenant with them,

when I will take away their sins.”[✡]

28 Concerning the Good News, they are enemies for your sake. But concerning the election, they are beloved for the fathers’ sake. 29 For the gifts and the calling of God are irrevocable. 30 For as you in time past were disobedient to God, but now have obtained mercy by their disobedience, 31 even so these also have now been disobedient, that by the mercy shown to you they may also obtain mercy. 32 For God has bound all to disobedience, that he might have mercy on all.

33 Oh the depth of the riches both of the wisdom and the knowledge of God! How unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past tracing out!

34 “For who has known the mind of the Lord?

Or who has been his counselor?”[✡]

35 “Or who has first given to him,

and it will be repaid to him again?”[✡]

36 For of him and through him and to him are all things. To him be the glory for ever! Amen.

12

1 Therefore I urge you, brothers, by the mercies of God, to present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God, which is your spiritual service. 2 Don’t be conformed to this world, but be transformed by the renewing of your mind, so that you may prove what is the good, well-pleasing, and perfect will of God.

3 For I say through the grace that was given me, to everyone who is among you, not to think of yourself more highly than you ought to think; but to think reasonably, as God has apportioned to each person a measure of faith. 4 For even as we have many members in one body, and all the members don’t have the same function, 5 so we, who are many, are one body in Christ, and individually members of one another, 6 having gifts differing according to the grace that was given to us: if prophecy, let’s prophesy according to the proportion of our faith; 7 or service, let’s give ourselves to service; or he who teaches, to his teaching; 8 or he who exhorts, to his exhorting; he who gives, let him do it with generosity; he who rules, with diligence; he who shows mercy, with cheerfulness.

9 Let love be without hypocrisy. Abhor that which is evil. Cling to that which is good. 10 In love of the brothers be tenderly affectionate to one another; in honor prefer one another, 11 not lagging in diligence, fervent in spirit, serving the Lord, 12 rejoicing in hope, enduring in troubles, continuing steadfastly in prayer, 13 contributing to the needs of the saints, and given to hospitality.

14 Bless those who persecute you; bless, and don’t curse. 15 Rejoice with those who rejoice. Weep with those who weep. 16 Be of the same mind one toward another. Don’t set your mind on high things, but associate with the humble. Don’t be wise in your own conceits. 17 Repay no one evil for evil. Respect what is honorable in the sight of all men. 18 If it is possible, as much as it is up to you, be at peace with all men. 19 Don’t seek revenge yourselves, beloved, but give place to God’s wrath. For it is written, “Vengeance belongs to me; I will repay, says the Lord.” [✡] 20 Therefore

“If your enemy is hungry, feed him.

If he is thirsty, give him a drink;

for in doing so, you will heap coals of fire on his head.”[✡]

21 Don’t be overcome by evil, but overcome evil with good.

13

1 Let every soul be in subjection to the higher authorities, for there is no authority except from God, and those who exist are ordained by God. 2 Therefore he who resists the authority withstands the ordinance of God; and those who withstand will receive to themselves judgment. 3 For rulers are not a terror to the good work, but to the evil. Do you desire to have no fear of the authority? Do that which is good, and you will have praise from the authority, 4 for he is a servant of God to you for good. But if you do that which is evil, be afraid, for he doesn’t bear the sword in vain; for he is a servant of God, an avenger for wrath to him who does evil. 5 Therefore you need to be in subjection, not only because of the wrath, but also for conscience’ sake. 6 For this reason you also pay taxes, for they are servants of God’s service, continually doing this very thing. 7 Therefore give everyone what you owe: if you owe taxes, pay taxes; if customs, then customs; if respect, then respect; if honor, then honor.

8 Owe no one anything, except to love one another; for he who loves his neighbor has fulfilled the law. 9 For the commandments, “You shall not commit adultery,” “You shall not murder,” “You shall not steal,”[*] “You shall not covet,” [✡] and whatever other commandments there are, are all summed up in this saying, namely, “You shall love your neighbor as yourself.”[✡] 10 Love doesn’t harm a neighbor. Love therefore is the fulfillment of the law.

11 Do this, knowing the time, that it is already time for you to awaken out of sleep, for salvation is now nearer to us than when we first believed. 12 The night is far gone, and the day is near. Let’s therefore throw off the deeds of darkness, and let’s put on the armor of light. 13 Let’s walk properly, as in the day; not in reveling and drunkenness, not in sexual promiscuity and lustful acts, and not in strife and jealousy. 14 But put on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make no provision for the flesh, for its lusts.

14

1 Now accept one who is weak in faith, but not for disputes over opinions. 2 One man has faith to eat all things, but he who is weak eats only vegetables. 3 Don’t let him who eats despise him who doesn’t eat. Don’t let him who doesn’t eat judge him who eats, for God has accepted him. 4 Who are you who judge another’s servant? To his own lord he stands or falls. Yes, he will be made to stand, for God has power to make him stand.

5 One man esteems one day as more important. Another esteems every day alike. Let each man be fully assured in his own mind. 6 He who observes the day, observes it to the Lord; and he who does not observe the day, to the Lord he does not observe it. He who eats, eats to the Lord, for he gives God thanks. He who doesn’t eat, to the Lord he doesn’t eat, and gives God thanks. 7 For none of us lives to himself, and none dies to himself. 8 For if we live, we live to the Lord. Or if we die, we die to the Lord. If therefore we live or die, we are the Lord’s. 9 For to this end Christ died, rose, and lived again, that he might be Lord of both the dead and the living.

10 But you, why do you judge your brother? Or you again, why do you despise your brother? For we will all stand before the judgment seat of Christ. 11 For it is written,

“ ‘As I live,’ says the Lord, ‘to me every knee will bow.

Every tongue will confess to God.’ ”[✡]

12 So then each one of us will give account of himself to God.

13 Therefore let’s not judge one another any more, but judge this rather, that no man put a stumbling block in his brother’s way, or an occasion for falling. 14 I know and am persuaded in the Lord Jesus that nothing is unclean of itself; except that to him who considers anything to be unclean, to him it is unclean. 15 Yet if because of food your brother is grieved, you walk no longer in love. Don’t destroy with your food him for whom Christ died. 16 Then don’t let your good be slandered, 17 for God’s Kingdom is not eating and drinking, but righteousness, peace, and joy in the Holy Spirit. 18 For he who serves Christ in these things is acceptable to God and approved by men. 19 So then, let’s follow after things which make for peace, and things by which we may build one another up. 20 Don’t overthrow God’s work for food’s sake. All things indeed are clean, however it is evil for that man who creates a stumbling block by eating. 21 It is good to not eat meat, drink wine, nor do anything by which your brother stumbles, is offended, or is made weak.

22 Do you have faith? Have it to yourself before God. Happy is he who doesn’t judge himself in that which he approves. 23 But he who doubts is condemned if he eats, because it isn’t of faith; and whatever is not of faith is sin.

24 Now to him who is able to establish you according to my Good News and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery which has been kept secret through long ages, 25 but now is revealed, and by the Scriptures of the prophets, according to the commandment of the eternal God, is made known for obedience of faith to all the nations; 26 to the only wise God, through Jesus Christ, to whom be the glory forever! Amen.[*]

15

1 Now we who are strong ought to bear the weaknesses of the weak, and not to please ourselves. 2 Let each one of us please his neighbor for that which is good, to be building him up. 3 For even Christ didn’t please himself. But, as it is written, “The reproaches of those who reproached you fell on me.”[✡] 4 For whatever things were written before were written for our learning, that through perseverance and through encouragement of the Scriptures we might have hope. 5 Now the God of perseverance and of encouragement grant you to be of the same mind with one another according to Christ Jesus, 6 that with one accord you may with one mouth glorify the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ.

7 Therefore accept one another, even as Christ also accepted you,[*] to the glory of God. 8 Now I say that Christ has been made a servant of the circumcision for the truth of God, that he might confirm the promises given to the fathers, 9 and that the Gentiles might glorify God for his mercy. As it is written,

“Therefore I will give praise to you among the Gentiles

and sing to your name.”[✡]

10 Again he says,

“Rejoice, you Gentiles, with his people.”[✡]

11 Again,

“Praise the Lord, all you Gentiles!

Let all the peoples praise him.”[✡]

12 Again, Isaiah says,

“There will be the root of Jesse,

he who arises to rule over the Gentiles;

in him the Gentiles will hope.”[✡]

13 Now may the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that you may abound in hope in the power of the Holy Spirit.

14 I myself am also persuaded about you, my brothers,[†] that you yourselves are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish others. 15 But I write the more boldly to you in part as reminding you, because of the grace that was given to me by God, 16 that I should be a servant of Christ Jesus to the Gentiles, serving as a priest of the Good News of God, that the offering up of the Gentiles might be made acceptable, sanctified by the Holy Spirit. 17 I have therefore my boasting in Christ Jesus in things pertaining to God. 18 For I will not dare to speak of any things except those which Christ worked through me for the obedience of the Gentiles, by word and deed, 19 in the power of signs and wonders, in the power of God’s Spirit; so that from Jerusalem and around as far as to Illyricum, I have fully preached the Good News of Christ; 20 yes, making it my aim to preach the Good News, not where Christ was already named, that I might not build on another’s foundation. 21 But, as it is written,

“They will see, to whom no news of him came.

They who haven’t heard will understand.”[✡]

22 Therefore also I was hindered these many times from coming to you, 23 but now, no longer having any place in these regions, and having these many years a longing to come to you, 24 whenever I travel to Spain, I will come to you. For I hope to see you on my journey, and to be helped on my way there by you, if first I may enjoy your company for a while. 25 But now, I say, I am going to Jerusalem, serving the saints. 26 For it has been the good pleasure of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certain contribution for the poor among the saints who are at Jerusalem. 27 Yes, it has been their good pleasure, and they are their debtors. For if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, they owe it to them also to serve them in material things. 28 When therefore I have accomplished this, and have sealed to them this fruit, I will go on by way of you to Spain. 29 I know that when I come to you, I will come in the fullness of the blessing of the Good News of Christ.

30 Now I beg you, brothers, by our Lord Jesus Christ and by the love of the Spirit, that you strive together with me in your prayers to God for me, 31 that I may be delivered from those who are disobedient in Judea, and that my service which I have for Jerusalem may be acceptable to the saints, 32 that I may come to you in joy through the will of God, and together with you, find rest. 33 Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen.

16

1 I commend to you Phoebe, our sister, who is a servant[*] of the assembly that is at Cenchreae, 2 that you receive her in the Lord in a way worthy of the saints, and that you assist her in whatever matter she may need from you, for she herself also has been a helper of many, and of my own self.

3 Greet Prisca and Aquila, my fellow workers in Christ Jesus, 4 who risked their own necks for my life, to whom not only I give thanks, but also all the assemblies of the Gentiles. 5 Greet the assembly that is in their house. Greet Epaenetus, my beloved, who is the first fruits of Achaia to Christ. 6 Greet Mary, who labored much for us. 7 Greet Andronicus and Junia, my relatives and my fellow prisoners, who are notable among the apostles, who were also in Christ before me. 8 Greet Amplias, my beloved in the Lord. 9 Greet Urbanus, our fellow worker in Christ, and Stachys, my beloved. 10 Greet Apelles, the approved in Christ. Greet those who are of the household of Aristobulus. 11 Greet Herodion, my kinsman. Greet them of the household of Narcissus, who are in the Lord. 12 Greet Tryphaena and Tryphosa, who labor in the Lord. Greet Persis, the beloved, who labored much in the Lord. 13 Greet Rufus, the chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine. 14 Greet Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas, and the brothers[†] who are with them. 15 Greet Philologus and Julia, Nereus and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints who are with them. 16 Greet one another with a holy kiss. The assemblies of Christ greet you.

17 Now I beg you, brothers, look out for those who are causing the divisions and occasions of stumbling, contrary to the doctrine which you learned, and turn away from them. 18 For those who are such don’t serve our Lord Jesus Christ, but their own belly; and by their smooth and flattering speech they deceive the hearts of the innocent. 19 For your obedience has become known to all. I rejoice therefore over you. But I desire to have you wise in that which is good, but innocent in that which is evil. 20 And the God of peace will quickly crush Satan under your feet.

The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you.

21 Timothy, my fellow worker, greets you, as do Lucius, Jason, and Sosipater, my relatives. 22 I, Tertius, who write the letter, greet you in the Lord. 23 Gaius, my host and host of the whole assembly, greets you. Erastus, the treasurer of the city, greets you, as does Quartus, the brother. 24 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all! Amen. 25  [‡]

* 1:1 “Christ” means “Anointed One”.

† 1:3 or, seed

✡ 1:17 Habakkuk 2:4

✡ 2:6 Psalm 62:12; Proverbs 24:12

✡ 2:24 Isaiah 52:5; Ezekiel 36:22

✡ 3:4 Psalm 51:4

✡ 3:12 Psalm 14:1-3; 53:1-3; Ecclesiastes 7:20

✡ 3:13 Psalm 5:9

✡ 3:13 Psalm 140:3

✡ 3:14 Psalm 10:7

✡ 3:17 Isaiah 59:7-8

✡ 3:18 Psalm 36:1

* 3:25 or, a propitiation

✡ 4:3 Genesis 15:6

✡ 4:8 Psalm 32:1-2

✡ 4:17 Genesis 17:5

✡ 4:18 Genesis 15:5

✡ 4:22 Genesis 15:6

* 7:1 The word for “brothers” here and where context allows may also be correctly translated “brothers and sisters” or “siblings.”

✡ 7:7 Exodus 20:17; Deuteronomy 5:21

* 8:1 NU omits “who don’t walk according to the flesh, but according to the Spirit”

† 8:15 Abba is an Aramaic word for “Father” or “Daddy”, which can be used affectionately and respectfully in prayer to our Father in heaven.

‡ 8:29 The word for “brothers” here and where context allows may also be correctly translated “brothers and sisters” or “siblings.”

✡ 8:36 Psalm 44:22

✡ 9:7 Genesis 21:12

✡ 9:9 Genesis 18:10,14

* 9:11 NU puts the phrase “not of works, but of him who calls” at the beginning of verse 12 instead of the end of verse 11.

✡ 9:12 Genesis 25:23

✡ 9:13 Malachi 1:2-3

✡ 9:15 Exodus 33:19

✡ 9:17 Exodus 9:16

✡ 9:20 Isaiah 29:16; 45:9

✡ 9:25 Hosea 2:23

✡ 9:26 Hosea 1:10

✡ 9:28 Isaiah 10:22-23

† 9:29 Greek: Sabaoth (for Hebrew: Tze’va’ot)

✡ 9:29 Isaiah 1:9

‡ 9:33 “Behold”, from “ἰδοὺ”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

✡ 9:33 Isaiah 8:14; 28:16

* 10:4 or, completion, or end

✡ 10:5 Leviticus 18:5

✡ 10:6 Deuteronomy 30:12

✡ 10:7 Deuteronomy 30:13

✡ 10:8 Deuteronomy 30:14

✡ 10:11 Isaiah 28:16

✡ 10:13 Joel 2:32

✡ 10:15 Isaiah 52:7

✡ 10:16 Isaiah 53:1

✡ 10:18 Psalm 19:4

✡ 10:19 Deuteronomy 32:21

✡ 10:20 Isaiah 65:1

✡ 10:21 Isaiah 65:2

✡ 11:3 1 Kings 19:10,14

✡ 11:4 1 Kings 19:18

✡ 11:8 Deuteronomy 29:4; Isaiah 29:10

✡ 11:10 Psalm 69:22,23

* 11:25 The word for “brothers” here and where context allows may also be correctly translated “brothers and sisters” or “siblings.”

✡ 11:27 Isaiah 59:20-21; 27:9; Jeremiah 31:33-34

✡ 11:34 Isaiah 40:13

✡ 11:35 Job 41:11

✡ 12:19 Deuteronomy 32:35

✡ 12:20 Proverbs 25:21-22

* 13:9 TR adds “You shall not give false testimony,”

✡ 13:9 Exodus 20:13-15,17; Deuteronomy 5:17-19,21

✡ 13:9 Leviticus 19:18

✡ 14:11 Isaiah 45:23

* 14:26 TR places verses 24-26 after Romans 16:24 as verses 25-27.

✡ 15:3 Psalm 69:9

* 15:7 TR reads “us” instead of “you”

✡ 15:9 2 Samuel 22:50; Psalm 18:49

✡ 15:10 Deuteronomy 32:43

✡ 15:11 Psalm 117:1

✡ 15:12 Isaiah 11:10

† 15:14 The word for “brothers” here and where context allows may also be correctly translated “brothers and sisters” or “siblings.”

✡ 15:21 Isaiah 52:15

* 16:1 or, deacon

† 16:14 The word for “brothers” here and where context allows may also be correctly translated “brothers and sisters” or “siblings.”

‡ 16:25 TR places Romans 14:24-26 at the end of Romans instead of at the end of chapter 14, and numbers these verses 16:25-27.

Sirach

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31
32
33
34
35
36
37
38
39
40

41
42
43
44
45
46
47
48
49
50

51

THE WISDOM OF JESUS THE SON OF SIRACH,

OR

ECCLESIASTICUS

The Wisdom of Jesus the Son of Sirach, also called Ecclesiasticus, is recognized as Deuterocanonical Scripture by the Roman Catholic, Greek Orthodox, and Russian Orthodox Churches.

The Prologue of the Wisdom of Jesus the Son of Sirach.

WHEREAS many and great things have been delivered to us by the law and the prophets, and by the others that have followed in their steps, for which we must give Israel the praise for instruction and wisdom; and since not only the readers need to become skillful themselves, but also those who love learning must be able to profit those who are outside, both by speaking and writing; my grandfather Jesus, having much given himself to the reading of the law, and the prophets, and the other books of our fathers, and having gained great familiarity with them, was also drawn on himself to write somewhat pertaining to instruction and wisdom, in order that those who love learning, and are devoted to these things, might make progress much more by living according to the law. You are entreated therefore to read with favor and attention, and to pardon us, if in any parts of what we have labored to interpret, we may seem to fail in some of the phrases. For things originally spoken in Hebrew don’t have the same force in them when they are translated into another language. Not only these, but the law itself, and the prophecies, and the rest of the books, have no small difference, when they are spoken in their original language. For having come into Egypt in the thirty-eighth year of Energetes the king, and having continued there some time, I found a copy giving no small instruction. I thought it therefore most necessary for me to apply some diligence and travail to translate this book, applying indeed much watchfulness and skill in that space of time to bring the book to an end and publish for them also, who in the land of their travels are desiring to learn, preparing their character in advance, so as to live according to the law.

1

1 All wisdom comes from the Lord,

and is with him forever.

2 Who can count the sand of the seas,

the drops of rain,

and the days of eternity?

3 Who will search out the height of the sky,

the breadth of the earth, the deep,

and wisdom?

4 Wisdom has been created before all things,

and the understanding of prudence from everlasting. 5  [*]

6 To whom has the root of wisdom been revealed?

Who has known her shrewd counsels? 7  [†]

8 There is one wise, greatly to be feared,

sitting upon his throne: the Lord.

9 He created her.

He saw and measured her.

He poured her out upon all his works.

10 She is with all flesh according to his gift.

He gave her freely to those who love him.

11 The fear of the Lord is glory, exultation,

gladness, and a crown of rejoicing.

12 The fear of the Lord will delight the heart,

and will give gladness, joy, and length of days.

13 Whoever fears the Lord, it will go well with him at the last.

He will be blessed in the day of his death.

14 To fear the Lord is the beginning of wisdom.

It was created together with the faithful in the womb.

15 She[‡] laid an eternal foundation with men.

She will be trusted among their offspring.

16 To fear the Lord is the fullness of wisdom.

She inebriates men with her fruits.

17 She will fill all her house with desirable things,

and her storehouses with her produce.

18 The fear of the Lord is the crown of wisdom,

making peace and[§] perfect health to flourish.[*]

19 He both saw and measured her.

He rained down skill and knowledge of understanding,

and exalted the honor of those who hold her fast.

20 To fear the Lord is the root of wisdom.

Her branches are length of days. 21  [†]

22 Unjust wrath can never be justified,

for his wrath tips the scale to his downfall.

23 A man that is patient will resist for a season,

and afterward gladness will spring up to him.

24 He will hide his words until the right moment,

and the lips of many will tell of his understanding.

25 A wise saying is in the treasures of wisdom;

but godliness is an abomination to a sinner.

26 If you desire wisdom, keep the commandments

and the Lord will give her to you freely;

27 for the fear of the Lord is wisdom and instruction.

Faith and humility are his good pleasure.

28 Don’t disobey the fear of the Lord.

Don’t come to him with a double heart.

29 Don’t be a hypocrite in men’s sight.

Keep watch over your lips.

30 Don’t exalt yourself,

lest you fall and bring dishonor upon your soul.

The Lord will reveal your secrets

and will cast you down in the midst of the congregation,

because you didn’t come to the fear of the Lord

and your heart was full of deceit.

2

1 My son, if you come to serve the Lord,

prepare your soul for temptation.

2 Set your heart aright, constantly endure,

and don’t make haste in time of calamity.

3 Cling to him, and don’t depart,

that you may be increased at your latter end.

4 Accept whatever is brought upon you,

and be patient when you suffer humiliation.

5 For gold is tried in the fire,

and acceptable men in the furnace of humiliation.

6 Put your trust in him, and he will help you.

Make your ways straight, and set your hope on him.

7 All you who fear the Lord, wait for his mercy.

Don’t turn aside, lest you fall.

8 All you who fear the Lord, put your trust in him,

and your reward will not fail.

9 All you who fear the Lord, hope for good things,

and for eternal gladness and mercy.

10 Look at the generations of old, and see:

Who ever put his trust in the Lord, and was ashamed?

Or who remained in his fear, and was forsaken?

Or who called upon him, and he neglected him?

11 For the Lord is full of compassion and mercy.

He forgives sins and saves in time of affliction.

12 Woe to fearful hearts, to faint hands,

and to the sinner who goes two ways!

13 Woe to the faint heart! For it doesn’t believe.

Therefore it won’t be defended.

14 Woe to you who have lost your patience!

And what will you all do when the Lord visits you?

15 Those who fear the Lord will not disobey his words.

Those who love him will keep his ways.

16 Those who fear the Lord will seek his good pleasure.

Those who love him will be filled with the law.

17 Those who fear the Lord will prepare their hearts,

and will humble their souls in his sight.

18 We will fall into the hands of the Lord,

and not into the hands of men;

for as his majesty is,

so also is his mercy.

3

1 Hear me, your father, O my children,

and do what you hear, that you all may be safe.

2 For the Lord honors the father over the children,

and has confirmed the judgment of the mother over her sons.

3 He who honors his father will make atonement for sins.

4 He who gives glory to his mother is as one who lays up treasure.

5 Whoever honors his father will have joy in his own children.

He will be heard in the day of his prayer.

6 He who gives glory to his father will have length of days.

He who listens to the Lord will bring rest to his mother,

7  [*] and will serve under his parents, as to masters.

8 Honor your father in deed and word,

that a blessing may come upon you from him.

9 For the blessing of the father establishes the houses of children,

but the curse of the mother roots out the foundations.

10 Don’t glorify yourself in the dishonor of your father,

for your father’s dishonor is no glory to you.

11 For the glory of a man is from the honor of his father,

and a mother in dishonor is a reproach to her children.

12 My son, help your father in his old age,

and don’t grieve him as long as he lives.

13 If he fails in understanding, have patience with him.

Don’t dishonor him in your full strength.

14 For the kindness to your father will not be forgotten.

Instead of sins it will be added to build you up.

15 In the day of your affliction it will be remembered for you,

as fair weather upon ice,

so your sins will also melt away.

16 He who forsakes his father is as a blasphemer.

He who provokes his mother is cursed by the Lord.

17 My son, go on with your business in humility;

so you will be loved by an acceptable man.

18 The greater you are, humble yourself the more,

and you will find favor before the Lord. 19  [†]

20 For the power of the Lord is great,

and he is glorified by those who are lowly.

21 Don’t seek things that are too hard for you,

and don’t search out things that are above your strength.

22 Think about the things that have been commanded you,

for you have no need of the things that are secret.

23 Don’t be overly busy in tasks that are beyond you,

for more things are shown to you than men can understand.

24 For the conceit of many has led them astray.

Evil opinion has caused their judgment to slip.

25  [‡]There is no light without eyes.

There is no wisdom without knowledge.

26 A stubborn heart will do badly at the end.

He who loves danger will perish in it.

27 A stubborn heart will be burdened with troubles.

The sinner will heap sin upon sins.

28 The calamity of the proud has no healing,

for a weed of wickedness has taken root in him.

29 The heart of the prudent will understand a proverb.

A wise man desires the ear of a listener.

30 Water will quench a flaming fire;

almsgiving will make atonement for sins.

31 He who repays good turns is mindful of that which comes afterward.

In the time of his falling he will find a support.

4

1 My son, don’t deprive the poor of his living.

Don’t make the needy eyes wait long.

2 Don’t make a hungry soul sorrowful,

or provoke a man in his distress.

3 Don’t add more trouble to a heart that is provoked.

Don’t put off giving to him who is in need.

4 Don’t reject a suppliant in his affliction.

Don’t turn your face away from a poor man.

5 Don’t turn your eye away from one who asks.

Give no occasion to a man to curse you.

6 For if he curses you in the bitterness of his soul,

he who made him will hear his supplication.

7 Endear yourself to the assembly.

Bow your head to a great man.

8 Incline your ear to a poor man.

Answer him with peaceful words in humility.

9 Deliver him who is wronged from the hand of him who wrongs him;

Don’t be hesitant in giving judgment.

10 Be as a father to the fatherless,

and like a husband to their mother.

So you will be as a son of the Most High,

and he will love you more than your mother does.

11 Wisdom exalts her sons,

and takes hold of those who seek her.

12 He who loves her loves life.

Those who seek her early will be filled with gladness.

13 He who holds her fast will inherit glory.

Where[*] he enters, the Lord will bless.

14 Those who serve her minister to the Holy One.

The Lord loves those who love her.

15 He who listens to her will judge the nations.

He who heeds her will dwell securely.

16 If he trusts her, he will inherit her,

and his generations will possess her.

17 For at the first she will walk with him in crooked ways,

and will bring fear and dread upon him,

and torment him with her discipline,

until she may trust his soul, and try him by her judgments.

18 Then she will return him again to the straight way,

and will gladden him, and reveal to him her secrets.

19 If he goes astray, she will forsake him,

and hand him over to his fall.

20 Watch for the opportunity, and beware of evil.

Don’t be ashamed of your soul.

21 For there is a shame that brings sin,

and there is a shame that is glory and grace.

22 Don’t show partiality, discrediting your soul.

Don’t revere any man to your falling.

23 Don’t refrain from speaking when it is for safety.

[†]Don’t hide your wisdom for the sake of seeming fair.

24 For wisdom will be known by speech,

and instruction by the word of the tongue.

25 Don’t speak against the truth

and be shamed for your ignorance.

26 Don’t be ashamed to confess your sins.

Don’t fight the river’s current.

27 Don’t lay yourself down for a fool to tread upon.

Don’t be partial to one who is mighty.

28 Strive for the truth to death,

and the Lord God will fight for you.

29 Don’t be hasty with your tongue,

or slack and negligent in your deeds.

30 Don’t be like a lion in your house,

or suspicious of your servants.

31 Don’t let your hand be stretched out to receive,

and closed when you should repay.

5

1 Don’t set your heart upon your goods.

Don’t say, “They are sufficient for me.”

2 Don’t follow your own mind and your strength

to walk in the desires of your heart.

3 Don’t say, “Who will have dominion over me?”

for the Lord will surely take vengeance on you.

4 Don’t say, “I sinned, and what happened to me?”

for the Lord is patient.

5 Don’t be so confident of atonement

that you add sin upon sins.

6 Don’t say, “His compassion is great.

He will be pacified for the multitude of my sins,”

for mercy and wrath are with him,

and his indignation will rest on sinners.

7 Don’t wait to turn to the Lord.

Don’t put off from day to day;

for suddenly the wrath of the Lord will come on you,

and you will perish in the time of vengeance.

8 Don’t set your heart upon unrighteous gains,

for you will profit nothing in the day of calamity.

9 Don’t winnow with every wind.

Don’t walk in every path.

This is what the sinner who has a double tongue does.

10 Be steadfast in your understanding.

Let your speech be consistent.

11 Be swift to hear

and answer with patience.

12 If you have understanding, answer your neighbor;

but if not, put your hand over your mouth.

13 Glory and dishonor is in talk.

A man’s tongue may be his downfall.

14 Don’t be called a whisperer.

Don’t lie in wait with your tongue;

for shame is on the thief,

and an evil condemnation is on him who has a double tongue.

15 Don’t be ignorant in a great or small matter.

6

1 Don’t become an enemy instead of a friend;

for an evil name will inherit shame and reproach.

So it is with the sinner who has a double tongue.

2 Don’t exalt yourself in the counsel of your soul,

that your soul not be torn in pieces like a bull.

3 You will eat up your leaves, destroy your fruit,

and leave yourself like a dry tree.

4 A wicked soul will destroy him who has it,

and will make him a laughing stock to his enemies.

5 Sweet words will multiply a man’s friends.

A gracious tongue will multiply courtesies.

6 Let those that are at peace with you be many,

but your advisers one of a thousand.

7 If you want to gain a friend, get him in a time of testing,

and don’t be in a hurry to trust him.

8 For there is a friend just for an occasion.

He won’t continue in the day of your affliction.

9 And there is a friend who turns into an enemy.

He will discover strife to your reproach.

10 And there is a friend who is a companion at the table,

but he won’t continue in the day of your affliction.

11 In your prosperity he will be as yourself,

and will be bold over your servants.

12 If you are brought low, he will be against you,

and will hide himself from your face.

13 Separate yourself from your enemies,

and beware of your friends.

14 A faithful friend is a strong defense.

He who has found him has found a treasure.

15 There is nothing that can be taken in exchange for a faithful friend.

His excellency is beyond price.

16 A faithful friend is a life-saving medicine.

Those who fear the Lord will find him.

17 He who fears the Lord directs his friendship properly;

for as he is, so is his neighbor also.

18 My son, gather instruction from your youth up.

Even when you have gray hair you will find wisdom.

19 Come to her as one who plows and sows

and wait for her good fruit;

for your toil will be little in her cultivation,

and you will soon eat of her fruit.

20 How exceedingly harsh she is to the unlearned!

He who is without understanding will not remain in her.

21 She will rest upon him as a mighty stone of trial.

He won’t hesitate to cast her from him.

22 For wisdom is according to her name.

She isn’t manifest to many.

23 Give ear, my son, and accept my judgment.

Don’t refuse my counsel.

24 Bring your feet into her fetters,

and your neck into her chain.

25 Put your shoulder under her and bear her.

Don’t be grieved with her bonds.

26 Come to her with all your soul.

Keep her ways with your whole power.

27 Search and seek, and she will be made known to you.

When you get hold of her, don’t let her go.

28 For at the last you will find her rest;

and she will be turned for you into gladness.

29 Her fetters will be to you for a covering of strength,

and her chains for a robe of glory.

30 For there is a golden ornament upon her,

and her bands are [✡] a purple cord.

31 You shall put her on as a robe of glory,

and shall put her on as a crown of rejoicing.

32 My son, if you are willing, you will be instructed.

If you will yield your soul, you will be prudent.

33 If you love to hear, you will receive.

If you incline your ear, you will be wise.

34 Stand in the multitude of the elders.

Attach yourself to whomever is wise.

35 Be willing to listen to every godly discourse.

Don’t let the proverbs of understanding escape you.

36 If you see a man of understanding, get to him early.

Let your foot wear out the steps of his doors.

37 Let your mind dwell on the ordinances of the Lord

and meditate continually on his commandments.

He will establish your heart

and your desire for wisdom will be given to you.

7

1 Do no evil,

so no evil will overtake you.

2 Depart from wrong,

and it will turn away from you.

3 My son, don’t sow upon the furrows of unrighteousness,

and you won’t reap them sevenfold.

4 Don’t seek preeminence from the Lord,

nor the seat of honor from the king.

5 Don’t justify yourself in the presence of the Lord,

and don’t display your wisdom before the king.

6 Don’t seek to be a judge,

lest you not be able to take away iniquities,

lest perhaps you fear the person of a mighty man,

and lay a stumbling block in the way of your uprightness.

7 Don’t sin against the multitude of the city.

Don’t disgrace yourself in the crowd.

8 Don’t commit a sin twice,

for even in one you will not be unpunished.

9 Don’t say, “He will look upon the multitude of my gifts.

When I make an offering to the Most High God, he will accept it.”

10 Don’t be faint-hearted in your prayer.

Don’t neglect to give alms.

11 Don’t laugh a man to scorn when he is in the bitterness of his soul,

for there is one who humbles and exalts.

12  [*] Don’t devise a lie against your brother,

or do the same to a friend.

13 Refuse to utter a lie,

for that habit results in no good.

14 Don’t babble in the assembly of elders.

Don’t repeat your words in your prayer.

15 Don’t hate hard labor

or farm work, which the Most High has created.

16 Don’t number yourself among the multitude of sinners.

Remember that wrath will not wait.

17 Humble your soul greatly,

for the punishment of the ungodly man is fire and the worm.

18 Don’t exchange a friend for something,

neither a true brother for the gold of Ophir.

19 Don’t deprive yourself of a wise and good wife,

for her grace is worth more than gold.

20 Don’t abuse a servant who works faithfully,

or a hireling who gives you his life.

21 Let your soul love a wise servant.

Don’t defraud him of liberty.

22 Do you have cattle? Look after them.

If they are profitable to you, let them stay by you.

23 Do you have children? Correct them,

and make them obedient from their youth.

24 Do you have daughters? Take care of their bodies,

and don’t be overly indulgent toward them.

25 Give your daughter in marriage, and you will have accomplished a great matter.

Give her to a man of understanding.

26 Do you have a wife who pleases you? Don’t cast her out.

[†] But don’t trust yourself to one who is hateful.

27 Honor your father with your whole heart,

and don’t forget the birth pangs of your mother.

28 Remember that you were born of them.

What will you repay them for the things that they have done for you?

29 Fear the Lord with all your soul;

and revere his priests.

30 With all your strength love him who made you.

Don’t forsake his ministers.

31 Fear the Lord and honor the priest.

Give him his portion, even as it is commanded you:

the first fruits, the trespass offering, the gift of the shoulders,

the sacrifice of sanctification, and the first fruits of holy things.

32 Also stretch out your hand to the poor man,

that your blessing may be complete.

33 A gift has grace in the sight of every living man.

Don’t withhold grace for a dead man.

34 Don’t avoid those who weep,

and mourn with those who mourn.

35 Don’t be slow to visit a sick man,

for by such things you will gain love.

36 In all your words, remember eternity,

and you will never sin.

8

1 Don’t contend with a mighty man,

lest perhaps you fall into his hands.

2 Don’t strive with a rich man, lest perhaps he overpower you;

for gold has destroyed many,

and turned away the hearts of kings.

3 Don’t argue with a loudmouthed man.

Don’t heap wood upon his fire.

4 Don’t make fun of a rude man,

lest your ancestors be dishonored.

5 Don’t reproach a man when he turns from sin.

Remember that we are all worthy of punishment.

6 Don’t dishonor a man in his old age,

for some of us are also growing old.

7 Don’t rejoice over anyone’s death.

Remember that we all die.

8 Don’t neglect the discourse of the wise.

Be conversant with their proverbs;

for from them you will learn discipline

and how to serve great men.

9 Don’t miss the discourse of the aged,

for they also learned from their parents,

because from them you will learn understanding,

and to give an answer in time of need.

10 Don’t kindle the coals of a sinner,

lest you be burned with the flame of his fire.

11 Don’t rise up from the presence of an insolent man,

lest he lie in wait as an ambush for your mouth.

12 Don’t lend to a man who is stronger than you;

and if you lend, count it as a loss.

13 Don’t be surety beyond your means.

If you give surety, think as one who will have to pay.

14 Don’t go to law with a judge;

for according to his honor they will give judgment for him.

15 Don’t travel with a reckless man,

lest he be burdensome to you;

for he will do as he pleases,

and you will perish with his folly.

16 Don’t fight with a wrathful man.

Don’t travel with him through the desert,

for blood is as nothing in his sight.

Where there is no help, he will overthrow you.

17 Don’t consult with a fool,

for he will not be able to keep a secret.

18 Do no secret thing before a stranger,

for you don’t know what it will cause.

19 Don’t open your heart to every man.

Don’t let him return you a favor.

9

1 Don’t be jealous over the wife of your bosom,

and don’t teach her an evil lesson against yourself.

2 Don’t give your soul to a woman

and let her trample down your strength.

3 Don’t go to meet a woman who plays the prostitute,

lest perhaps you fall into her snares.

4 Don’t with a woman who is a singer,

lest perhaps you be caught by her tricks.

5 Don’t gaze at a virgin,

lest perhaps you stumble and incur penalties for her.

6 Don’t give your soul to prostitutes,

that you not lose your inheritance.

7 Don’t look around in the streets of the city.

Don’t wander in its deserted places.

8 Turn your eye away from a beautiful woman,

and don’t gaze at another’s beauty.

Many have been led astray by the beauty of a woman;

and with this, passion is kindled like a fire.

9 Don’t dine at all with a woman who has a husband,

or revel with her at wine,[*]

lest perhaps your soul turn away to her,

and with your spirit you slide into destruction.

10 Don’t forsake an old friend;

for a new one is not comparable to him.

A new friend is like new wine:

if it becomes old, you will drink it with gladness.

11 Don’t envy the success of a sinner;

for you don’t know what his end will be.

12 Don’t delight in the delights of the ungodly.

Remember they will not go unpunished to[†] the grave.

13 Keep yourself far from the man who has[‡] power to kill,

and you will not be troubled by the fear of death.

If you come to him, commit no fault,

lest he take away your life.

Know surely that you go about in the midst of snares,

and walk upon the battlements of a city.

14 As well as you can, aim to know your neighbors,

and take counsel with the wise.

15 Let your conversation be with men of understanding.

Let all your discourse be in the law of the Most High.

16 Let righteous people be companions at your table.

Let your glorying be in the fear of the Lord.

17 A work is commended because of the skill of the artisan;

so he who rules the people will be considered wise for his speech.

18 A loudmouthed man is dangerous in his city.

He who is reckless in his speech will be hated.

10

1 A wise judge will instruct his people.

The government of a man of understanding will be well ordered.

2 As is the judge of his people, so are his officials.

As the city’s ruler is, so are all those who dwell in it.

3 An undisciplined king will destroy his people.

A city will be established through the understanding of the powerful.

4 The government of the earth is in the Lord’s hand.

In due time, he will raise up over it the right person at the right time.

5 A man’s prosperity is in the Lord’s hand.

He will lay his honor upon the person of the scribe.

6 Don’t be angry with your neighbor for every wrong.

Do nothing by works of violence.

7 Pride is hateful before the Lord and men.

Arrogance is abhorrent in the judgment of both.

8 Sovereignty is transferred from nation to nation

because of injustice, violence, and greed for money.

9  Why are dirt and ashes proud?[*]

Because in life, my body decays.

10  A long disease mocks the physician.

The king of today will die tomorrow.

11 For when a man is dead,

he will inherit maggots, vermin, and worms.

12  It is the beginning of pride when a man departs from the Lord.

His heart has departed from him who made him.

13 For the beginning of pride is sin.

He who keeps it will pour out abomination.

For this cause the Lord brought upon them strange calamities

and utterly overthrew them.

14 The Lord cast down the thrones of rulers

and set the lowly in their place.

15 The Lord plucked up the roots of nations

and planted the lowly in their place.

16 The Lord overthrew the lands of nations

and destroyed them to the foundations of the earth.

17 He took some of them away and destroyed them,

and made their memory to cease from the earth.

18 Pride has not been created for men,

nor wrathful anger for the offspring of women.

19  Whose offspring has honor?

Human offspring who fear the Lord.

Whose offspring has no honor?

Human offspring who break the commandments.

20 In the midst of kindred he who rules them has honor.

Those who fear the Lord have honor in his eyes. 21  [†]

22 The rich man, the honorable, and the poor

all glory in the fear of the Lord.

23 It is not right to dishonor a poor man who has understanding.

It is not fitting to glorify a man who is a sinner.

24 The prince, the judge, and the mighty man will be honored.

There is not one of them greater than he who fears the Lord.

25 Free men will minister to a wise servant.

A man who has knowledge will not complain.

26 Don’t flaunt your wisdom in doing your work.

Don’t boast in the time of your distress.

27  [‡] Better is he who labors and abounds in all things,

Than he who boasts and lacks bread.

28 My son, glorify your soul in humility,

and ascribe to yourself honor according to your worthiness.

29 Who will justify him who sins against his own soul?

Who will honor him who dishonors his own life?

30 A poor man is honored for his knowledge.

A rich man is honored for his riches.

31 But he who is honored in poverty, how much more in riches?

He who is dishonored in riches, how much more in poverty?

11

1 The wisdom of the lowly will lift up his head,

and make him sit in the midst of great men.

2 Don’t commend a man for his good looks.

Don’t abhor a man for his outward appearance.

3 The bee is little among flying creatures,

but what it produces is the best of confections.

4 Don’t boast about the clothes you wear,

and don’t exalt yourself in the day of honor;

for the Lord’s works are wonderful,

and his works are hidden among men.

5 Many[*] kings have sat down upon the ground,

but one who was never thought of has worn a crown.

6 Many mighty men have been greatly disgraced.

Men of renown have been delivered into other men’s hands.

7 Don’t blame before you investigate.

Understand first, and then rebuke.

8 Don’t answer before you have heard.

Don’t interrupt while someone else is speaking.

9 Don’t argue about a matter that doesn’t concern you.

Don’t sit with sinners when they judge.

10 My son, don’t be busy about many matters;

for if you meddle much, you will not be unpunished.

If you pursue, you will not overtake,

and you will not escape by fleeing.

11 There is one who toils, labors, and hurries,

and is even more behind.

12 There is one who is sluggish, and needs help,

lacking in strength, and who abounds in poverty,

but the Lord’s eyes looked upon him for good,

and he raised him up from his low condition,

13 and lifted up his head

so that many marveled at him.

14 Good things and bad, life and death,

poverty and riches, are from the Lord. 15-16  [†]

17 The Lord’s gift remains with the godly.

His good pleasure will prosper forever.

18 One grows rich by his diligence and self-denial,

and this is the portion of his reward:

19 when he says, “I have found rest,

and now I will eat of my goods!”

he doesn’t know how much time will pass

until he leaves them to others and dies.

20 Be steadfast in your covenant and be doing it,

and grow old in your work.

21 Don’t marvel at the works of a sinner,

but trust the Lord and stay in your labor;

for it is an easy thing in the sight of the Lord

to swiftly and suddenly make a poor man rich.

22 The Lord’s blessing is in the reward of the godly.

He makes his blessing flourish in an hour that comes swiftly.

23 Don’t say, “What use is there of me?

What further good things can be mine?”

24 Don’t say, “I have enough.

What harm could happen to me now?”

25 In the day of good things, bad things are forgotten.

In the day of bad things, a man will not remember things that are good.

26 For it is an easy thing in the sight of the Lord

to reward a man in the day of death according to his ways.

27 The affliction of an hour causes delights to be forgotten.

In the end, a man’s deeds are revealed.

28 Call no man happy before his death.

A man will be known in his children.

29 Don’t bring every man into your house,

for many are the tricks of a deceitful man.

30 Like a decoy partridge in a cage, so is the heart of a proud man.

Like a spy, he looks for your weakness.

31 For he lies in wait to turn things that are good into evil,

and assigns blame in things that are praiseworthy.

32 From a spark of fire, a heap of many coals is kindled,

and a sinful man lies in wait to shed blood.

33 Take heed of an evil-doer, for he plans wicked things,

lest perhaps he ruin your reputation forever.

34 Receive a stranger into your house, and he will distract you with arguments

and estrange you from your own family.

12

1 If you do good, know to whom you do it,

and your good deeds will have thanks.

2 Do good to a godly man, and you will find a reward—

if not from him, then from the Most High.

3 No good will come to him who continues to do evil,

nor to him who gives no alms.

4 Give to the godly man,

and don’t help the sinner.

5 Do good to one who is lowly.

Don’t give to an ungodly man.

Keep back his bread, and don’t give it to him,

lest he subdue you with it;

for you would receive twice as much evil

for all the good you would have done to him.

6 For the Most High also hates sinners,

and will repay vengeance to the ungodly.[*]

7 Give to the good man,

and don’t help the sinner.

8 A man’s friend won’t be[†] fully tried in prosperity.

His enemy won’t be hidden in adversity.

9 In a man’s prosperity, his enemies are grieved.

In his adversity, even his friend leaves.

10 Never trust your enemy,

for his wickedness is like corrosion in copper.

11 Though he humbles himself and walks bowed down,

still be careful and beware of him.

You will be to him as one who has wiped a mirror,

to be sure it doesn’t completely tarnish.

12 Don’t set him next to you,

lest he overthrow you and stand in your place.

Don’t let him sit on your right hand,

lest he seek to take your seat,

and at the last you acknowledge my words,

and be pricked with my sayings.

13 Who will pity a charmer that is bitten by a snake,

or any who come near wild beasts?

14 Even so, who will pity him who goes to a sinner,

and is associated with him in his sins?

15 For a while he will stay with you,

and if you falter, he will not stay.

16 The enemy will speak sweetly with his lips,

and in his heart plan to throw you into a pit.

The enemy may weep with his eyes,

but if he finds opportunity, he will want more blood.

17 If adversity meets you, you will find him there before you.

Pretending to help you, he will trip you.

18 He will shake his head, clap his hands,

whisper much, and change his countenance.

13

1 He who touches pitch will be defiled.

He who has fellowship with a proud man will become like him.

2 Don’t take up a burden above your strength.

Have no fellowship with one who is mightier and richer than yourself.

What fellowship would the earthen pot have with the kettle?

The kettle will strike, and the pot will be dashed in pieces.

3 The rich man does a wrong and threatens.

The poor is wronged and apologizes.

4 If you are profitable, he will exploit you.

If you are in need, he will forsake you.

5 If you own something, he will live with you.

He will drain your resources and will not be sorry.

6 Does he need you? Then he will deceive you,

smile at you, and give you hope.

He will speak kindly to you and say, “What do you need?”

7 He will shame you by his delicacies

until he has made you bare twice or thrice,

and in the end he will laugh you to scorn.

Afterward he will see you, will forsake you,

and shake his head at you.

8 Beware that you are not deceived

and brought low in your enjoyment.

9 If a mighty man invites you, be reserved,

and he will invite you more.

10 Don’t press him, lest you be thrust back.

Don’t stand far off, lest you be forgotten.

11 Don’t try to speak with him as an equal,

and don’t believe his many words;

for he will test you with much talk,

and will examine you in a smiling manner.

12 He who doesn’t keep secrets to himself is unmerciful.

He won’t hesitate to harm and to bind.

13 Keep them to yourself and be careful,

for you walk[*] in danger of falling. 14  [†]

15 Every living creature loves its own kind,

and every man loves his neighbor.

16 All flesh associates with their own kind.

A man will stick to people like himself.

17 What fellowship would the wolf have with the lamb?

So is the sinner to the godly.

18 What peace is there between a hyena and a dog?

What peace is there between a rich man and the poor?

19 Wild donkeys are the prey of lions in the wilderness;

likewise poor men are feeding grounds for the rich.

20 Lowliness is an abomination to a proud man;

likewise a poor man is an abomination to the rich.

21 When a rich man is shaken, he is supported by his friends,

but when the humble is down, he is pushed away even by his friends.

22 When a rich man falls, there are many helpers.

He speaks things not to be spoken, and men justify him.

A humble man falls, and men rebuke him.

He utters wisdom, and is not listened to.

23 A rich man speaks, and all keep silence.

They extol what he says to the clouds.

A poor man speaks, and they say, “Who is this?”

If he stumbles, they will help to overthrow him.

24 Riches are good if they have no sin.

Poverty is evil only in the opinion of the ungodly.

25 The heart of a man changes his countenance,

whether it is for good or for evil.[‡]

26 A cheerful countenance is a sign of a prosperous heart.

Devising proverbs takes strenuous thinking.

14

1 Blessed is the man who has not slipped with his mouth,

and doesn’t suffer from sorrow for sins.

2 Blessed is he whose soul does not condemn him,

and who has not given up hope.

3 Riches are not appropriate for a stingy person.

What would a miser do with money?

4 He who gathers by denying himself gathers for others.

Others will revel in his goods.

5 If one is mean to himself, to whom will he be good?

He won’t enjoy his possessions.

6 There is none more evil than he who is grudging to himself.

This is a punishment for his wickedness.

7 Even if he does good, he does it in forgetfulness.

In the end, he reveals his wickedness.

8 A miser is evil.

He turns away and disregards souls.

9 A covetous man’s eye is not satisfied with his portion.

Wicked injustice dries up his soul.

10 A miser begrudges bread,

and it is lacking at his table.

11 My son, according to what you have, treat yourself well,

and bring worthy offerings to the Lord.

12 Remember that death will not wait,

and that the covenant of Hades hasn’t been shown to you.

13 Do good to your friends before you die.

According to your ability, reach out and give to them.

14 Don’t deprive yourself of a good day.

Don’t let your share of a desired good pass you by.

15 Won’t you leave your labors to another,

and your toils be divided by lot?

16 Give, take, and treat yourself well,

because there is no seeking of luxury in Hades.

17 All flesh grows old like a garment,

for the covenant from the beginning is, “You must die!”

18 Like the leaves flourishing on a thick tree,

some it sheds, and some grow,

so also are the generations of flesh and blood:

one comes to an end and another is born.

19 Every work rots and falls away,

and its builder will depart with it.

20 Blessed is the man who meditates on wisdom,

and who reasons by his understanding.

21 He who considers her ways in his heart

will also have knowledge of her secrets.

22 Go after her like a hunter,

and lie in wait in her paths.

23 He who peers in at her windows

will also listen at her doors.

24 He who lodges close to her house

will also fasten a nail in her walls.

25 He will pitch his tent near at hand to her,

and will lodge in a lodging where good things are.

26 He will set his children under her shelter,

and will rest under her branches.

27 By her he will be covered from heat,

and will lodge in her glory.

15

1 He who fears the Lord will do this.

He who has possession of the law will obtain her.

2 She will meet him like a mother,

and receive him like a wife married in her virginity.

3 She will feed him with bread of understanding

and give him water of wisdom to drink.

4 He will be stayed upon her, and will not be moved.

He will rely upon her, and will not be confounded.

5 She will exalt him above his neighbors.

She will open his mouth in the midst of the congregation.

6 He will inherit joy, a crown of gladness,

and an everlasting name.

7 Foolish men will not obtain her.

Sinners will not see her.

8 She is far from pride.

Liars will not remember her.

9 Praise is not attractive in the mouth of a sinner;

for it was not sent to him from the Lord.

10 For praise will be spoken in wisdom;

The Lord will prosper it.

11 Don’t say, “It is through the Lord that I fell away;”

for you shall not do the things that he hates.

12 Don’t say, “It is he that caused me to err;”

for he has no need of a sinful man.

13 The Lord hates every abomination;

and those who fear him don’t love them.

14 He himself made man from the beginning

and left him in the hand of his own counsel.

15 If you choose, you can keep the commandments.

To be faithful is a matter of your choice.

16 He has set fire and water before you.

You will stretch forth your hand to whichever you desire.

17 Before man is life and death.

Whichever he likes, it will be given to him.

18 For the wisdom of the Lord is great.

He is mighty in power, and sees all things.

19 His eyes are upon those who fear him.

He knows every act of man.

20 He has not commanded any man to be ungodly.

He has not given any man license to sin.

16

1 Don’t desire a multitude of unprofitable children,

neither delight in ungodly sons.

2 If they multiply, don’t delight in them

unless the fear of the Lord is in them.

3 Don’t trust in their life.

Don’t rely on their numbers;

for one can be better than a thousand,

and to die childless than to have ungodly children.

4 For from one who has understanding, a city will be populated,

but a race of wicked men will be made desolate.

5 I have seen many such things with my eyes.

My ear has heard mightier things than these.

6 In a congregation of sinners, a fire will be kindled.

In a disobedient nation, wrath is kindled.

7 He was not pacified toward the giants of old time,

who revolted in their strength.

8 He didn’t spare Lot’s neighbors,

whom he abhorred for their pride.

9 He didn’t pity the people of perdition

who were taken away in their sins,

10 or in like manner, the six hundred thousand footmen

who were gathered together in the hardness of their hearts.

11 Even if there is one stiff-necked person,

it is a marvel if he will be unpunished;

for mercy and wrath are both with him who is mighty to forgive,

and he pours out wrath.

12 As his mercy is great, so is his correction also.

He judges a man according to his works.

13 The sinner will not escape with plunder.

The perseverance of the godly will not be frustrated.

14 He will make room for every work of mercy.

Each man will receive according to his works. 15-16  [*]

17 Don’t say, “I will be hidden from the Lord,”

and “Who will remember me from on high?”

I will not be known among so many people,

for what is my soul in a boundless creation?

18 Behold, the heaven, the heaven of heavens,

the deep, and the earth, will be moved when he visits.

19 The mountains and the foundations of the earth together

are shaken with trembling when he looks at them.

20 No heart will think about these things.

Who could comprehend his ways?

21 Like a tempest which no man can see,

so, the majority of his works are[†] hidden.

22 Who will declare his works of righteousness?

Who will wait for them?

For his covenant is afar off.[‡]

23 He who is lacking in[§] understanding thinks about these things.

An unwise and erring man thinks foolishly.

24 My son, listen to me, learn knowledge,

and heed my words with your heart.

25 I will impart instruction with precision,

and declare knowledge exactly.

26 In the judgment of the Lord are his works from the beginning.

From the making of them he determined their boundaries.

27 He arranged his works for all time,

and their beginnings to their generations.

They aren’t hungry or weary,

and they don’t cease from their works.

28 No one pushes aside his neighbor.

They will never disobey his word.

29 After this also the Lord looked at the earth

and filled it with his blessings.

30  [*] [†] All manner of living things covered its surface,

and they return into it.

17

1 The Lord created mankind out of earth,

and turned them back to it again.

2 He gave them days by number, and a set time,

and gave them authority over the things that are on it.

3 He endowed them with strength proper to them,

and made them according to his own image.

4 He put the fear of man upon all flesh,

and gave him dominion over beasts and birds. 5  [*]

6 He gave them counsel, tongue, eyes,

ears, and heart to have understanding.

7 He filled them with the knowledge of wisdom,

and showed them good and evil.

8 He set his eye upon their hearts,

to show them the majesty of his works. 9  [†]

10 And they will praise his holy name,

[‡] that they may declare the majesty of his works.

11 He added to them knowledge,

and gave them a law of life for a heritage.

12 He made an everlasting covenant with them,

and showed them his decrees.

13 Their eyes saw the majesty of his glory.

Their ears heard the glory of his voice.

14 He said to them, “Beware of all unrighteousness.”

So he gave them commandment, each man concerning his neighbor.

15 Their ways are ever before him.

They will not be hidden from his eyes. 16  [§]

17  [*] For every nation he appointed a ruler,

but Israel is the Lord’s portion. 18  [†]

19 All their works are as clear as the sun before him.

His eyes are continually upon their ways.

20 Their iniquities are not hidden from him.

All their sins are before the Lord. 21  [‡]

22 With him the alms of a man is as a signet.

He will keep a man’s kindness as the pupil of the eye. [§]

23 Afterwards he will rise up and repay them,

and render their repayment upon their head.

24 However to those who repent he grants a return.

He comforts those who are losing hope.

25 Return to the Lord, and forsake sins.

Make your prayer before his face offend less.

26 Turn again to the Most High, and turn away from iniquity.[*]

Greatly hate the abominable thing.

27 Who will give praise to the Most High in Hades,

in place of the living who return thanks?

28 Thanksgiving perishes from the dead, as from one who doesn’t exist.

He who is in life and health will praise the Lord.

29 How great is the mercy of the Lord,

and his forgiveness to those who turn to him!

30 For humans are not capable of everything,

because the son of man is not immortal.

31 What is brighter than the sun? Yet even this can be eclipsed.

So flesh and blood devise evil.

32 He looks upon the power of the height of heaven,

while all men are earth and ashes.

18

1 He who lives forever created the whole universe.

2 The Lord alone is just. 3  [*]

4 He has given power to declare his works to no one.

Who could trace out his mighty deeds?

5 Who could measure the strength of his majesty?

Who could also proclaim his mercies?

6 As for the wondrous works of the Lord, it is not possible to take from them nor add to them,

neither is it possible to explore them.

7 When a man has finished, then he is just at the beginning.

When he stops, then he will be perplexed.

8 What is mankind, and what purpose do they serve?

What is their good, and what is their evil?

9 The number of man’s days at the most are a hundred years.

10 As a drop of water from the sea, and a pebble from the sand,

so are a few years in the day of eternity.

11 For this cause the Lord was patient over them,

and poured out his mercy upon them.

12 He saw and perceived their end, that it is evil.

Therefore he multiplied his forgiveness.

13 The mercy of a man is on his neighbor;

but the mercy of the Lord is on all flesh:

reproving, chastening, teaching,

and bringing back, as a shepherd does his flock.

14 He has mercy on those who accept chastening,

and that diligently seek after his judgments.

15 My son, don’t add reproach to your good deeds,

and no harsh words in any of your giving.

16 Doesn’t the dew relieve the scorching heat?

So a word is better than a gift.

17 Behold, isn’t a word better than a gift?

Both are with a gracious person.

18 A fool is ungracious and abusive.

The gift of an grudging person consumes the eyes.

19 Learn before you speak.

Take care of your health before you get sick.

20 Before judgment, examine yourself,

and in the hour of scrutiny you will find forgiveness.

21 Humble yourself before you get sick.

In the time of sins, repent.

22 Let nothing hinder you to pay your vow in due time.

Don’t wait until death to be released.

23 Before you make a vow, prepare yourself.

Don’t be like a man who tests the Lord.

24 Think about the wrath coming in the days of the end,

and the time of vengeance, when he turns away his face.

25 In the days of fullness remember the time of hunger.

Remember poverty and lack in the days of wealth.

26 From morning until evening, the time changes.

All things are speedy before the Lord.

27 A wise man is cautious in everything.

In days of sinning, he will beware of offense.[†]

28 Every man of understanding knows wisdom.

He will give thanks to him who found her.

29 They who were of understanding in sayings also became wise themselves,

and poured out apt proverbs.

30 Don’t go after your lusts.

Restrain your appetites.

31 If you give fully to your soul the delight of her desire,

she will make you[‡] the laughing stock of your enemies.

32 Don’t make merry in much luxury,

and don’t be tied to its expense.

33 Don’t be made a beggar by banqueting with borrowed money

when you have nothing in your purse.[§]

19

1 A worker who is a drunkard will not become rich.

He who despises small things will fall little by little.

2 Wine and women will make men of understanding go astray.

He who joins with prostitutes is reckless.

3 Decay and worms will have him as their heritage.

A reckless soul will be taken away.

4 He who is hasty to trust is shallow-hearted.

He who sins offends against his own soul.

5 He who rejoices in wickedness will be condemned.[*]

6  [†] He who hates gossip has less wickedness.

7 Never repeat what is told you,

and you won’t lose anything.

8 Whether it is of friend or foe, don’t tell it.

Unless it is a sin to you, don’t reveal it.

9 For if he has heard you and observed you,

when the time comes, he will hate you.

10 Have you heard something? Let it die with you.

Be brave: it will not make you burst!

11 A fool will travail in pain with a word,

as a woman in labor with a child.

12 As an arrow that sticks in the flesh of the thigh,

so is gossip in a fool.

13 Question a friend; it may be he didn’t do it.

If he did something, it may be that he may do it no more.

14 Question your neighbor; it may be he didn’t say it.

If he has said it, it may be that he may not say it again.

15 Question a friend; for many times there is slander.

Don’t trust every word.

16 There is one who slips, and not from the heart.

Who is he who hasn’t sinned with his tongue?

17 Reprove your neighbor before you threaten him;

and give place to the law of the Most High. 18-19  [‡]

20 All wisdom is the fear of the Lord.

In all wisdom is the doing of the law. 21  [§]

22 The knowledge of wickedness is not wisdom.

The prudence of sinners is not counsel.

23 There is a wickedness, and it is an abomination.

There is a fool lacking in wisdom.

24 Better is one who has little understanding, and fears God,

than one who has much intelligence and transgresses the law.

25 There is an exquisite subtlety, and it is unjust.

And there is one who perverts favor to gain a judgment.[*]

26 There is one who does wickedly, who hangs down his head with mourning;

but inwardly he is full of deceit,

27 bowing down his face, and pretending to be deaf in one ear.

Where he isn’t known, he will take advantage of you.

28 And if for lack of power he is hindered from sinning,

if he finds opportunity, he will do mischief.

29 A man will be known by his appearance.

One who has understanding will be known by his face when you meet him.

30 A man’s attire, grinning laughter,

and the way he walks show what he is.

20

1 There is a reproof that is not timely;

and there is a person who is wise enough to keep silent.

2 How good is it to reprove, rather than to be angry.

He who confesses will be kept back from harm. 3  [*]

4 As is the lust of a eunuch to deflower a virgin,

so is he who executes judgments with violence.

5 There is one who keeps silent and is found wise;

and there is one who is hated for his much talk.

6 There is one who keeps silent, for he has no answer to make;

And there is one who keeps silent, knowing when to speak.

7 A wise man will be silent until his time has come,

but the braggart and fool will miss his time.

8 He who uses many words will be abhorred.

He who takes authority for himself will be hated in it.

9 There is a prosperity that a man finds in misfortunes;

and there is a gain that turns to loss.

10 There is a gift that will not profit you;

and there is a gift that pays back double.

11 There are losses because of glory;

and there is one who has lifted up his head from a low estate.

12 There is one who buys much for a little,

and pays for it again sevenfold.

13 He who is wise in words will make himself beloved;

but the pleasantries of fools will be wasted.

14 The gift of a fool will not profit you,[†]

for looks for repayment many times instead of one.

15 He will give little and insult much.

He will open his mouth like a crier.

Today he will lend, and tomorrow he will ask for it back.

Such a one is a hateful man.

16 The fool will say, “I have no friend,

and I have no thanks for my good deeds.

Those who eat my bread have an evil tongue.”

17 How often, and of how many, will he be laughed to scorn! [‡]

18 A slip on a pavement is better than a slip with the tongue.

So the fall of the wicked will come speedily.

19 A man without grace is a tale out of season.

It will be continually in the mouth of the ignorant.

20 A parable from a fool’s mouth will be rejected;

for he won’t tell it in at the proper time.

21 There is one who is hindered from sinning through lack.

When he rests, he will not be troubled.

22 There is one who destroys his soul through bashfulness.

By a foolish countenance, he will destroy it.

23 There is one who for bashfulness makes promises to his friend;

and he makes him his enemy for nothing.

24 A lie is an ugly blot on a person.

It will be continually in the mouth of the ignorant.

25 A thief is better than a man who is continually lying,

but they both will inherit destruction.

26 The destination of a liar is dishonor.

His shame is with him continually.

27 He who is wise in words will advance himself.

And one who is prudent will please great men.

28 He who tills his land will raise his harvest high.

He who pleases great men will get pardon for iniquity.

29 Favors and gifts blind the eyes of the wise,

and as a muzzle on the mouth, turn away reproofs.

30 Wisdom that is hidden, and treasure that is out of sight—

what profit is in either of them?

31 Better is a man who hides his folly

than a man who hides his wisdom. 32  [§]

21

1 My son, have you sinned?

Do it no more;

and ask forgiveness for your past sins.

2 Flee from sin as from the face of a snake;

for if you go near, it will bite you.

Its teeth are like lion’s teeth,

slaying people’s souls.

3 All iniquity is as a two-edged sword.

Its stroke has no healing.

4 Terror and violence will waste away riches.

So the house of an arrogant man will be laid waste.

5 Supplication from a poor man’s mouth reaches to the ears of[*] God,

and his judgment comes speedily.

6 One who hates reproof is in the path of the sinner.

He who fears the Lord will repent in his heart.

7 He who is mighty in tongue is known far away;

but the man of understanding knows when he slips.

8 He who builds his house with other men’s money

is like one who gathers stones for his own tomb.

9 The congregation of wicked men is as a bundle of tow

with a flame of fire at the end of them.

10 The way of sinners is paved with stones;

and at the end of it is the pit of Hades.

11 He who keeps the law becomes master of its intent.

The fulfilment of the fear of the Lord is wisdom.

12 He who is not clever will not be instructed.

There is a cleverness which makes bitterness abound.

13 The knowledge of a wise man will be made to abound as a flood,

and his counsel as a fountain of life.

14 The inward parts of a fool are like a broken vessel.

He will hold no knowledge.

15 If a man of knowledge hears a wise word,

he will commend it and add to it.

The wanton man hears it, and it displeases him,

so he throws it away behind his back.

16 The chatter of a fool is like a burden in the way,

but grace will be found on the lips of the wise.

17 The utterance of the prudent man will be sought for in the congregation.

They will ponder his words in their heart.

18 As a house that is destroyed, so is wisdom to a fool.

The knowledge of an unwise man is [†] talk without sense.

19 Instruction is as fetters on the feet of an unwise man,

and as manacles on the right hand.

20 A fool lifts up his voice with laughter,

but a clever man smiles quietly.

21 Instruction is to a prudent man as an ornament of gold,

and as a bracelet upon his right arm.

22 The foot of a fool rushes into a house,

but a man of experience will be ashamed of entering.

23 A foolish man peers into the door of a house,

but a man who is instructed will stand outside.

24 It is rude for someone to listen at a door,

but a prudent person will be grieved with the disgrace.

25  [‡] The lips of strangers will be grieved at these things,

but the words of prudent men will be weighed in the balance.

26 The heart of fools is in their mouth,

but the mouth of wise men is their heart.

27 When the ungodly curses an adversary,

he curses his own soul.

28 A whisperer defiles his own soul,

and will be hated wherever he travels.

22

1 A slothful man is compared to a stone that is defiled.

Everyone will at hiss at him in his disgrace.

2 A slothful man is compared to the filth of a dunghill.

Anyone who picks it up will shake it out of his hand.

3 An undisciplined child is a disgrace to his father,

and a foolish daughter is born to his loss.

4 A prudent daughter will inherit a husband of her own.

She who brings shame is the grief of her father.

5 She who is arrogant brings shame on father and husband.

She will be despised by both of them.

6 Ill-timed conversation is like music in mourning,

but stripes and correction are wisdom in every season.

7 He who teaches a fool is like one who glues potsherds together,

even like one who wakes a sleeper out of a deep sleep.

8 He who teaches a fool is as one who teaches a man who slumbers.

In the end he will say, “What is it?” 9-10  [*]

11 Weep for the dead, for he lacks light.

Weep for a fool, for he lacks understanding.

Weep more sweetly for the dead, because he has found rest,

but the life of the fool is worse than death.

12 Mourning for the dead lasts seven days,

but for a fool and an ungodly man, it lasts all the days of his life.

13 Don’t talk much with a foolish man,

and don’t go to one who has no understanding.

Beware of him, lest you have trouble and be defiled in his onslaught.

Turn away from him, and you will find rest,

and you won’t be wearied in his madness.

14 What would be heavier than lead?

What is its name, but “Fool”?

15 Sand, salt, and a mass of iron is easier to bear

than a man without understanding.

16 Timber girded and bound into a building will not be released with shaking.

So a heart established in due season on well advised counsel will not be afraid.

17 A heart settled upon a thoughtful understanding

is as an ornament of plaster on a polished wall.

18 Fences set on a high place will not stand against the wind;

so a fearful heart in the imagination of a fool will not stand against any fear.

19 He who pricks the eye will make tears fall.

He who pricks the heart makes it show feeling.

20 Whoever casts a stone at birds scares them away.

He who insults a friend will dissolve friendship.

21 If you have drawn a sword against a friend, don’t despair,

for there may be a way back.

22 If you have opened your mouth against a friend, don’t be afraid,

for there may be reconciliation,

unless it is for insulting, arrogance, disclosing of a secret, or a treacherous blow—

for these things any friend will flee.

23 Gain trust with your neighbor in his poverty,

that in his prosperity you may have gladness.

Stay steadfast to him in the time of his affliction,

that you may be heir with him in his inheritance.[†]

24 Before fire is the vapor and smoke of a furnace,

so insults precede bloodshed.

25 I won’t be ashamed to shelter a friend.

I won’t hide myself from his face.

26 If any evil happens to me because of him,

everyone who hears it will beware of him.

27 Who will set a watch over my mouth,

and a seal of shrewdness upon my lips,

that I may not fall from it, and that my tongue may not destroy me?

23

1 O Lord, Father and Master of my life,

don’t abandon me to their counsel.

Don’t let me fall because of them.

2 Who will set scourges over my thought,

and a discipline of wisdom over my heart,

that they spare me not for my errors,

and not overlook their sins?

3 Otherwise my errors might be multiplied,

and my sins abound,

I fall before my adversaries,

and my enemy rejoice over me.[*]

4 O Lord, Father and God of my life,

don’t give me a haughty eyes,[†]

5 and turn away evil desire from me.[‡]

6 Let neither gluttony nor lust overtake me.

Don’t give me over to a shameless mind.

7 Listen, my children, to the discipline of the mouth.

He who keeps it will not be caught.

8 The sinner will be overpowered through his lips.

By them, the insulter and the arrogant will stumble.

9 Don’t accustom your mouth to an oath,

and don’t be accustomed to naming the Holy One,

10 for as a servant who is continually scourged will not lack bruises,

so he also who swears and continually utters the Name will not be cleansed from sin.

11 A man of many oaths will be filled with iniquity.

The scourge will not depart from his house.

If he offends, his sin will be upon him.

If he disregards it, he has sinned doubly.

If he has sworn falsely, he will not be justified,

for his house will be filled with calamities.

12 There is a manner of speech that is clothed with death.

Let it not be found in the heritage of Jacob,

for all these things will be far from the godly,

and they will not wallow in sins.

13 Don’t accustom your mouth to gross rudeness,

for it involves sinful speech.

14 Remember your father and your mother,

for you sit in the midst of great men,

that you be not forgetful before them,

and become a fool by your bad habit;

so you may wish that you had not been born,

and curse the day of your birth.

15 A man who is accustomed to abusive language

won’t be corrected all the days of his life.

16 Two sorts of people multiply sins,

and the third will bring wrath:

a hot passion, like a burning fire, will not be quenched until it is consumed;

a fornicator in the body of his flesh will never cease until he has burned out the fire.

17 All bread is sweet to a fornicator.

He will not cease until he dies.

18 A man who goes astray from his own marriage bed

says in his heart, “Who sees me?

Darkness is around me, and the walls hide me.

No one sees me. Of whom am I afraid?

The Most High will not remember my sins.”

19 The eyes of men are his terror.

He doesn’t know that the eyes of the Lord are ten thousand times brighter than the sun,

seeing all the ways of men,

and looking into secret places.

20 All things were known to him before they were created,

and also after they were completed.

21 This man will be punished in the streets of the city.

He will be seized where he least expects it.

22 So also is a wife who leaves her husband,

and produces an heir by another man.

23 For first, she was disobedient in the law of the Most High.

Second, she trespassed against her own husband.

Third, she played the adulteress in whoredom,

and had children by another man.

24 She shall be brought out into the congregation.

Her punishment will extend to her children.

25 Her children will not take root.

Her branches will bear no fruit.

26 She will leave her memory for a curse.

Her reproach won’t be blotted out.

27 And those who are left behind will know that there is nothing better than the fear of the Lord,

and nothing sweeter than to heed the commandments of the Lord. 28  [§]

24

1 Wisdom will praise her own soul,

and will proclaim her glory in the midst of her people.

2 She will open her mouth in the congregation of the Most High,

and proclaim her glory in the presence of his power.

3 “I came out of the mouth of the Most High,

and covered the earth as a mist.

4 I lived in high places,

and my throne is in the pillar of the cloud.

5 Alone I surrounded the circuit of heaven,

and walked in the depth of the abyss.

6 In the waves of the sea, and in all the earth,

and in every people and nation, I obtained a possession.

7 With all these I sought rest.

In whose inheritance shall I lodge?

8 Then the Creator of all things gave me a command.

He who created me made my tent to rest,

and said, ‘Let your dwelling be in Jacob,

and your inheritance in Israel.’

9 He created me from the beginning, before the ages.

For all ages, I will not cease to exist.

10 In the holy tabernacle, I ministered before him.

So I was established in Zion.

11 In the beloved city, likewise he gave me rest.

In Jerusalem was my domain.

12 I took root in a people that was honored,

even in the portion of the Lord’s own inheritance.

13 I was exalted like a cedar in Lebanon,

And like a cypress tree on the mountains of Hermon.

14 I was exalted like a palm tree on the sea shore,

like rose bushes in Jericho,

and like a fair olive tree in the plain.

I was exalted like a plane tree.

15 Like cinnamon and aspalathus, I have given a scent to perfumes.

Like choice myrrh, I spread abroad a pleasant fragrance,

like[*] galbanum, onycha, stacte,

and as the smell of frankincense in the tabernacle.

16 Like the terebinth, I stretched out my branches.

My branches are glorious and graceful.

17 Like the vine, I put forth grace.

My flowers are the fruit of glory and riches. 18  [†]

19 “Come to me, all you who desire me,

and be filled with my fruits.

20 For my memory is sweeter than honey,

and my inheritance than the honeycomb.

21 Those who eat me will be hungry for more.

Those who drink me will be thirsty for more.

22 He who obeys me will not be ashamed.

Those who work with me will not sin.”

23 All these things are the book of the covenant of the Most High God,

the law which Moses commanded us for an inheritance for the assemblies of Jacob. 24  [‡]

25 It is he who makes wisdom abundant, as Pishon,

and as Tigris in the days of first fruits.

26 He makes understanding full as the Euphrates,

and as the Jordan in the days of harvest,

27 who makes instruction shine forth as the light,

as Gihon in the days of vintage.

28 The first man didn’t know her perfectly.

In like manner, the last has not explored her.

29 For her thoughts are filled from the sea,

and her counsels from the great deep.

30 I came out as a canal stream from a river,

and as an irrigation ditch into a garden.

31 I said, “I will water my garden,

and will drench my garden bed.”

Behold, my stream became a river,

and my river became a sea.

32 I will yet bring instruction to light as the morning,

and will make these things clear from far away.

33 I will continue to pour out teaching like prophecy,

and leave it to all generations.

34 See that I have not labored for myself only,

but for all those who diligently seek wisdom.

25

1 I enjoy three things,

and they are beautiful before the Lord and men:

the agreement of kindred,

the friendship of neighbors,

and a woman and her husband who walk together in agreement.

2 But my soul hates three sorts of people,

and I am greatly offended at their life:

a poor man who is arrogant,

a rich man who is a liar,

and an old fool who is an adulterer.

3 If you gathered nothing in your youth,

how could you find anything in your old age?

4 How beautiful a thing is judgment in the gray-haired,

and for elders to know good counsel!

5 How beautiful is the wisdom of old men,

and understanding and counsel to men who are in honor!

6 Much experience is the crown of the aged.

Their glory is the fear of the Lord.

7 There are nine things that I have thought of, and in my heart counted happy,

and the tenth I will utter with my tongue:

a man who has joy with his children,

and a man who lives and sees the fall of his enemies.

8 Happy is he who dwells with a wife of understanding,

he who has not slipped with his tongue,

Aad he who has not served a man who is unworthy of him.

9 Happy is he who has found prudence,

and he who speaks in the ears of those who listen.

10 How great is he who has found wisdom!

Yet is there none above him who fears the Lord.

11 The fear of the Lord surpasses all things.

To whom shall he who holds it be likened? 12  [*]

13  Any wound but a wound of the heart!

Any wickedness but the wickedness of a woman!

14 Any calamity but a calamity from those who hate me!

Any vengeance but the vengeance of enemies!

15 There is no venom worse than a snake’s venom.

There is no wrath worse than an enemy’s wrath.

16 I would rather dwell with a lion and a dragon

than keep house with a wicked woman.

17 The wickedness of a woman changes her appearance,

and darkens her countenance like that of a bear.

18 Her husband will sit among his neighbors,

and when he hears it, he sighs bitterly.

19 All malice is small compared to the malice of a woman.

Let the portion of a sinner fall on her.

20  As walking up a sandy hill is to the feet of the aged,

so is a wife full of words to a quiet man.

21 Don’t be ensnared by a woman’s beauty.

Don’t desire a woman for her beauty.

22 There is anger, impudence, and great reproach

if a woman supports her husband.

23 A wicked woman is abasement of heart,

sadness of countenance, and a wounded heart.

A woman who won’t make her husband happy

is like hands that hang down, and weak knees.

24 The beginning of sin came from a woman.

Because of her, we all die.

25 Don’t give water an outlet,

and don’t give a wicked woman freedom of speech.

26 If she doesn’t go as you direct,

cut her away from your flesh.[†]

26

1 Happy is the husband of a good wife.

The number of his days will be doubled.

2 A faithful wife gives joy to her husband.

He will fulfill his years in peace.

3 A good wife is a great gift.

She will be given to those who fear the Lord.

4 Whether a man is rich or poor,

a good heart makes a cheerful face at all times.

5 Of three things my heart was afraid,

and concerning the fourth[*] kind I made supplication:

The slander of a city, the assembly of a mob, and a false accusation.

All these are more grievous than death.

6 A grief of heart and sorrow is a woman who is jealous of another woman.

Her tongue-lashing makes it known to all.

7 A wicked woman is like a chafing yoke.

He who takes hold of her is like one who grasps a scorpion.

8 A drunken woman causes great wrath.

She will not cover her own shame.

9 The whoredom of a woman is in the lifting up of her eyes;

it will be known by her eyelids.

10 Keep strict watch on a headstrong daughter,

lest she find liberty for herself, and use it.

11 Watch out for an impudent eye,

and don’t be surprised if it sins against you.

12 She will open her mouth like a thirsty traveller,

and drink from every water that is near.

She will sit down at every post,

and open her quiver to any arrow.

13 The grace of a wife will delight her husband.

Her knowledge will strengthen [†] his bones.

14 A silent woman is a gift of the Lord.

There is nothing worth so much as a well-instructed soul.

15 A modest woman is grace upon grace.

There are no scales that can weigh the value of a self-controlled soul.

16 As the sun when it arises in the highest places of the Lord,

so is the beauty of a good wife in her well-organized home.

17 As the lamp that shines upon the holy lampstand,

so is the beauty of the face on a well-proportioned body.

18 As the golden pillars are upon a base of silver,

so are beautiful feet with the breasts of one who is steadfast. 19-27  [‡]

28 For two things my heart is grieved,

and for the third anger comes upon me:

a warrior who suffers for poverty,

men of understanding who are counted as garbage,

and one who turns back from righteousness to sin—

the Lord will prepare him for the sword!

29 It is difficult for a merchant to keep himself from wrong doing,

and for a retailer to be acquitted of sin.

27

1 Many have sinned for profit.

He who seeks to multiply wealth will turn his eye away.

2 As a nail will stick fast between the joinings of stones,

so sin will thrust itself in between buying and selling.

3 Unless a person holds on diligently to the fear of the Lord,

his house will be overthrown quickly.

4 In the shaking of a sieve, the refuse remains,

so does the filth of man in his thoughts.

5 The furnace tests the potter’s vessels;

so the test of a person is in his thoughts.

6 The fruit of a tree discloses its cultivation,

so is the utterance of the thought of a person’s heart.

7 Praise no man before you hear his thoughts,

for this is how people are tested.

8 If you follow righteousness, you will obtain it,

and put it on like a long robe of glory.

9 Birds will return to their own kind,

so truth will return to those who practice it.

10 The lion lies in wait for prey.

So does sin for those who do evil.

11 The discourse of a godly man is always wise,

but the fool changes like the moon.

12 Limit your time among people void of understanding,

but persevere among the thoughtful.

13 The talk of fools is offensive.

Their laughter is wantonly sinful.

14 Their talk with much swearing makes hair stand upright.

Their strife makes others plug their ears.

15 The strife of the proud leads to bloodshed.

Their abuse of each other is a grievous thing to hear.

16 He who reveals secrets destroys trust,

and will not find a close friend.

17 Love a friend, and keep faith with him;

but if you reveal his secrets,

you shall not follow him;

18 for as a man has destroyed his enemy,

so you have destroyed the friendship of your neighbor.

19 As a bird which you have released out of your hand,

so you have let your neighbor go, and you will not catch him again.

20 Don’t pursue him, for he has gone far away,

and has escaped like a gazelle out of the snare.

21 For a wound may be bound up, and after abuse there may be reconciliation;

but he who reveals secrets is without hope.

22 One who winks the eye contrives evil things;

and those who know him will keep their distance.

23 When you are present, he will speak sweetly,

and will admire your words;

but afterward he will twist his speech

and set a trap in your words.

24 I have hated many things, but nothing like him.

The Lord will hate him.

25 One who casts a stone straight up casts it on his own head.

A deceitful blow opens wounds.

26 He who digs a pit will fall into it.

He who sets a snare will be caught in it.

27 He who does evil things, they will roll back upon him,

and he will not know where they came from.

28 Mockery and reproach are from the arrogant.

Vengeance lies in wait for them like a lion.

29 Those who rejoice at the fall of the godly will be caught in a snare.

Anguish will consume them before they die.

30 Wrath and anger, these also are abominations.

A sinner will possess them.

28

1 He who takes vengeance will find vengeance from the Lord,

and he will surely make his sins firm.

2 Forgive your neighbor the hurt that he has done,

and then your sins will be pardoned when you pray.

3 Does anyone harbor anger against another

and expect healing from the Lord?

4 Upon a man like himself he has no mercy,

and does he make supplication for his own sins?

5 He being himself flesh nourishes wrath.

Who will make atonement for his sins?

6 Remember your last end, and stop enmity.

Remember corruption and death, and be true to the commandments.

7 Remember the commandments, and don’t be angry with your neighbor.

Remember the covenant of the Highest, and overlook ignorance.

8 Abstain from strife, and you will diminish your sins,

for a passionate man will kindle strife.

9 A man who is a sinner will trouble friends

and sow discord among those who are at peace.

10 As is the fuel of the fire, so will it burn;

and as the stoutness of the strife is, so will it burn.

As is the strength of the man, so will be his wrath;

and as is his wealth, so he will exalt his anger.

11 A contention begun in haste kindles a fire;

and hasty fighting sheds blood.

12 If you blow on a spark, it will burn;

and if you spit upon it, it will be quenched.

Both of these come out of your mouth.

13 Curse the whisperer and double-tongued,

for he has destroyed many who were at peace.

14 A slanderer has shaken many,

and dispersed them from nation to nation.

It has pulled down strong cities

and overthrown the houses of great men.

15 A slanderer has cast out brave women

and deprived them of their labors.

16 He who listens to it will not find rest,

nor will he live quietly.

17 The stroke of a whip makes a mark in the flesh,

but the stroke of a tongue will break bones.

18 Many have fallen by the edge of the sword,

yet not so many as those who have fallen because of the tongue.

19 Happy is he who is sheltered from it,

who has not passed through its wrath,

who has not drawn its yoke,

and has not been bound with its bands.

20 For its yoke is a yoke of iron,

and its bands are bands of brass.

21 Its death is an evil death,

and Hades is better than it.

22 It will not have rule over godly men.

They will not be burned in its flame.

23 Those who forsake the Lord will fall into it.

It will burn among them, and won’t be quenched.

It will be sent against them like a lion.

It will destroy them like a leopard.

24 As you hedge your possession about with thorns,

and secure your silver and your gold,

25 so make a balance and a weight for your words,

and make a door and a bar for your mouth.

26 Take heed lest you slip with it,

lest you fall before one who lies in wait.

29

1 He who shows mercy will lend to his neighbor.

He who strengthens him with his hand keeps the commandments.

2 Lend to your neighbor in time of his need.

Repay your neighbor on time.

3 Confirm your word, and keep faith with him;

and at all seasons you will find what you need.

4 Many have considered a loan to be a windfall,

and have given trouble to those who helped them.

5 Until he has received, he will kiss a man’s hands.

For his neighbor’s money he will speak submissly.

Then when payment is due, he will prolong the time,

return excuses, and complain about the season.

6 If he prevails, the creditor will hardly receive half;

And he will count it as a windfall.

If not, he has deprived him of his money,

and he has gotten him for an enemy without cause.

He will pay him with cursing and railing.

Instead of honor, he will pay him disgrace.

7  [*] Many on account of fraud have turned away.

They are afraid of being defrauded for nothing.

8 However be patient with a man in poor estate.

Don’t keep him waiting for your alms.

9 Help a poor man for the commandment’s sake.

According to his need don’t send him empty away.

10 Lose your money for a brother and a friend.

Don’t let it rust under a stone and be lost.

11 Allocate your treasure according to the commandments of the Most High

and it will profit you more than gold.

12 Store up almsgiving in your store-chambers

and it will deliver you out of all affliction.

13 It will fight for you against your enemy

better than a mighty shield and a ponderous spear.

14 A good man will be surety for his neighbor.

He who has lost shame will fail him.

15 Don’t forget the kindness of your guarantor,

for he has given his life for you.

16 A sinner will waste the property of his guarantor.

17 He who is thankless will fail him who delivered him.

18 Being surety has undone many who were prospering

and shaken them as a wave of the sea.

It has driven mighty men from their homes.

They wandered among foreign nations.

19 A sinner who falls into suretiship and undertakes contracts for work

will fall into lawsuits.

20 Help your neighbor according to your power,

and be careful not to fall yourself.

21 The essentials of life are water, bread,

a garment, and a house for privacy.

22 Better is the life of a poor man under a shelter of logs

than sumptuous fare in another man’s house.

23 With little or with much, be well satisfied.[†]

24 It is a miserable life to go from house to house.

Where you are a guest, you dare not open your mouth.

25 You will entertain, serve drinks, and have no thanks.

In addition to this, you will hear bitter words.

26 “Come here, you sojourner, set a table,

and if you have anything in your hand, feed me with it.”

27 “Leave, you sojourner, for an honored guest is here.

My brother has come to be my guest. I need my house.”

28 These things are grievous to a man of understanding:

The scolding about lodging and the insults of creditors.

30

1 He who loves his son will continue to lay stripes upon him,

that he may have joy from him in the end.

2 He who chastises his son will have profit from him,

and will brag about him among his acquaintances.

3 He who teaches his son will provoke his enemy to jealousy.

Before friends, he will rejoice in him.

4 His father dies, and is as though he had not died;

for he has left one behind him like himself.

5 In his life, he saw his son and rejoiced.

When he died, it was without regret.

6 He left behind him an avenger against his enemies,

and one to repay kindness to his friends.

7 He who makes too much of his son will bind up his wounds.

His heart will be troubled at every cry.

8 An unbroken horse becomes stubborn.

An unrestrained son becomes headstrong.

9 Pamper your child, and he will make you afraid.

Play with him, and he will grieve you.

10 Don’t laugh with him, lest you have sorrow with him,

and you gnash your teeth in the end.

11 Give him no liberty in his youth,

and don’t ignore his follies.[*]

12  [†] Bow down his neck in his youth,

and beat him on the sides while he is a child,

lest he become stubborn, and be disobedient to you,

and there be sorrow to your soul.[‡]

13 Chastise your son, and give him work,

lest his shameless behavior be an offense to you.

14 Better is a poor man who is healthy and fit,

than a rich man who is afflicted in his body.

15 Health and fitness are better than all gold,

and a strong body better than wealth without measure.

16 There is no wealth better than health of body.

There is no gladness above the joy of the heart.

17 Death is better than a bitter life,

[§] and[*] eternal rest than a continual sickness.

18 Good things poured out upon a mouth that is closed

are like food offerings laid upon a grave.

19 What does an offering profit an idol?

For it can’t eat or smell.

So is he who is punished by the Lord,

20 seeing with his eyes and groaning,

like a eunuch embracing a virgin and groaning.

21 Don’t give your soul to sorrow.

Don’t afflict yourself deliberately.

22 Gladness of heart is the life of a man.

Cheerfulness of a man lengthens his days.

23 Love your own soul, and comfort your heart.

Remove sorrow far from you,

for sorrow has destroyed many,

and there is no profit in it.

24 Envy and wrath shorten life.

Anxiety brings old age before its time.

25 Those who are cheerful and merry

will benefit from their food.

31

1 Wakefulness that comes from riches consumes the flesh,

and anxiety about it takes away sleep.

2 Wakeful anxiety will crave slumber.

[*] In a severe disease, sleep will be broken.

3 A rich man toils in gathering money together.

When he rests, he is filled with his good things.

4 A poor man toils in lack of substance.

When he rests, he becomes needy.

5 He who loves gold won’t be justified.

He who follows destruction will himself have his fill of it.

6 Many have been given over to ruin for the sake of gold.

Their destruction meets them face to face.

7 It is a stumbling block to those who sacrifice to it.

Every fool will be taken by it.

8 Blessed is the rich person who is found blameless,

and who doesn’t go after gold.

9 Who is he, that we may call him blessed?

For he has done wonderful things among his people.

10 Who has been tried by it, and found perfect?

Then let him boast.

Who has had the power to transgress, and has not transgressed?

And to do evil, and has not done it?

11 His prosperity will be made sure.

The congregation will proclaim his alms.

12 Do you sit at a great table? Don’t be greedy there.

Don’t say, “There is a lot of food on it!”

13 Remember that a greedy eye is a wicked thing.

What has been created more greedy than an eye?

Therefore it sheds tears from every face.

14 Don’t stretch your hand wherever it looks.

Don’t thrust yourself with it into the dish.

15 Consider your neighbor’s feelings by your own.

Be discreet in every point.

16 Eat like a human being those things which are set before you.

Don’t eat greedily, lest you be hated.

17 Be first to stop for manners’ sake.

Don’t be insatiable, lest you offend.

18 And if you sit among many,

Don’t reach out your hand before them.

19 How sufficient to a well-mannered man is a very little.

He doesn’t breathe heavily in his bed.

20 Healthy sleep comes from moderate eating.

He rises early, and his wits are with him.

The pain of wakefulness, colic,

and griping are with an insatiable man.

21 And if you have been forced to eat,

rise up in the middle of it, and you shall have rest.

22 Hear me, my son, and don’t despise me,

and in the end you will appreciate my words.

In all your works be skillful,

and no disease will come to you.

23 People bless him who is liberal with his food.

The testimony of his excellence will be believed.

24 The city will murmer at him who is a stingy with his food.

The testimony of his stinginess will be accurate.

25 Don’t show not yourself valiant in wine,

for wine has destroyed many.

26 The furnace tests the temper of steel by dipping;

so does wine test hearts in the quarreling of the proud.

27 Wine is as good as life to men,

if you drink it in moderation.

What life is there to a man who is without wine?

It has been created to make men glad.

28 Wine drunk in season and in moderation

is joy of heart and gladness of soul:

29 Wine drunk excessively is bitterness of soul,

with provocation and conflict.

30 Drunkenness increases the rage of a fool to his hurt.

It diminishes strength and adds wounds.

31 Don’t rebuke your neighbor at a banquet of wine.

Don’t despise him in his mirth.

Don’t speak a word of reproach to him.

Don’t distress him by making demands of him.

32

1 Have they made you ruler of a feast?

Don’t be lifted up.

Be among them as one of them.

Take care of them first, and then sit down.

2 And when you have done all your duties, take your place,

that you may be gladdened on their account,

and receive a wreath for your good service.

3 Speak, you who are older, for it’s your right, but with sound knowledge;

and don’t interrupt the music.

4 Don’t pour out talk where there is a performance of music.

Don’t display your wisdom at the wrong time.

5  As a ruby signet in a setting of gold,

so is a music concert at a wine banquet.

6 As an emerald signet in a work of gold,

so is musical melody with pleasant wine.

7 Speak, young man, if you are obliged to,

but no more than twice, and only if asked.

8 Sum up your speech, many things in few words.

Be as one who knows and yet holds his tongue.

9  When among great men, don’t behave as their equal.

When another is speaking, don’t babble.

10 Lightning speeds before thunder.

Approval goes before a modesty.

11 Rise up in good time, and don’t be last.

Go home quickly and don’t loiter

12 Amuse yourself there and do what is in your heart.

Don’t sin by proud speech.

13 For these things bless your Maker,

who gives you to drink freely of his good things.

14 He who fears the Lord will receive discipline.

Those who seek him early will find favor.

15 He who seeks the law shall be filled with it,

but the hypocrite will stumble at it.

16 Those who fear the Lord will find true judgment,

and will kindle righteous acts like a light.

17 A sinful man shuns reproof,

and will find a judgment according to his will.

18 A sensible person won’t neglect a thought.

An insolent and proud man won’t crouch in fear,

even after he has done a thing by himself without counsel.

19 Do nothing without counsel,

but when you have acted, don’t regret it.

20 Don’t go in a way of conflict.

Don’t stumble in stony places.

21 Don’t be overconfident on a smooth road.

22 Beware of your own children.

23 In every work guard your own soul,

for this is the keeping of the commandments.

24 He who believes the law gives heed to the commandment.

He who trusts in the Lord will suffer no loss.

33

1 No evil will happen to him who fears the Lord,

but in trials once and again he will deliver him.

2 A wise man will not hate the law,

but he who is a hypocrite about it is like a boat in a storm.

3 A man of understanding will put his trust in the law.

And the law is faithful to him, as when one asks a divine oracle.

4 Prepare your speech, and so you will be heard.

Bind up instruction, and make your answer.

5 The heart of a fool is like a cartwheel.

His thoughts are like a rolling axle.

6 A stallion horse is like a mocking friend.

He neighs under every one who sits upon him.

7 Why does one day excel another,

when all the light of every day in the year is from the sun?

8 They were distinguished by the Lord’s knowledge,

and he varied seasons and feasts.

9 Some of them he exalted and hallowed,

and some of them he has made ordinary days.

10 And all men are from the ground.

Adam was created from dust.

11 In the abundance of his knowledge the Lord distinguished them,

and made their ways different.

12 Some of them he blessed and exalted,

and some of them he made holy and brought near to himself.

Some of them he cursed and brought low,

and overthrew them from their place.

13 As the clay of the potter in his hand,

all his ways are according to his good pleasure,

so men are in the hand of him who made them,

to render to them according to his judgment.

14 Good is the opposite of evil,

and life is the opposite of death;

so[*] the sinner is the opposite of the godly.

15 Look upon all the works of the Most High like this,

they come in pairs, one against another.

16 I was the last on watch,

like one who gleans after the grape gatherers.

17 By the Lord’s blessing I arrived before them,

and filled my winepress like one who gathers grapes.

18 Consider that I labored not for myself alone,

but for all those who seek instruction.

19 Hear me, you great men of the people,

and listen with your ears, you rulers of the congregation.

20 To son and wife, to brother and friend,

don’t give power over yourself while you live,

and don’t give your goods to another,

lest you regret it and must ask for them.

21 While you still live and breath is in you,

don’t give yourself over to anybody.

22 For it is better that your children should ask from you

than that you should look to the hand of your children.

23 Excel in all your works.

Don’t bring a stain on your honor.

24 In the day that you end the days of your life,

in the time of death, distribute your inheritance.

25 Fodder, a stick, and burdens are for a donkey.

Bread, discipline, and work are for a servant.

26 Set your slave to work, and you will find rest.

Leave his hands idle, and he will seek liberty.

27 Yoke and thong will bow the neck.

For an evil slave there are racks and tortures.

28 Send him to labor, that he not be idle,

for idleness teaches much mischief.

29 Set him to work, as is fit for him.

If he doesn’t obey, make his fetters heavy.

30 Don’t be excessive toward any.

Do nothing unjust.

31 If you have a slave, treat him like yourself,

because you have bought him with blood.

32 If you have a slave, treat him like yourself.

[†] For like your own soul, you will need him.

If you treat him ill, and he departs and runs away,

33 which way will you go to seek him?

34

1 Vain and false hopes are for a man void of understanding.

Dreams give wings to fools.

2 As one who grasps at a shadow and follows after the wind,

so is he who sets his mind on dreams.

3 The vision of dreams is a reflection,

the likeness of a face near a face.

4 From an unclean thing what can be cleansed?

From that which is false what can be true?

5 Divinations, and soothsayings, and dreams, are vain.

The heart has fantasies like a woman in labor.

6 If they are not sent in a visitation from the Most High,

don’t give your heart to them.

7 For dreams have led many astray.

They have failed by putting their hope in them.

8 Without lying the law will be fulfilled.

Wisdom is complete in a faithful mouth.

9 A well-instructed man knows many things.

He who has much experience will declare understanding.

10 He who has no experience knows few things.

But he who has traveled increases cleverness.

11 I have seen many things in my travels.

My understanding is more than my words.

12 I was often in danger even to death.

I was preserved because of these experiences.

13 The spirit of those who fear the Lord will live,

for their hope is in him who saves them.

14 Whoever fears the Lord won’t be afraid, and won’t be a coward,

for he is his hope.

15 Blessed is the soul of him who fears the Lord.

To whom does he give heed? Who is his support?

16 The eyes of the Lord are on those who love him,

a mighty protection and strong support,

a cover from the hot blast, a shade from the noonday sun,

a guard from stumbling, and a help from falling.

17 He raises up the soul, and enlightens the eyes.

He gives health, life, and blessing.

18 He who sacrifices a thing wrongfully gotten, his offering is made in mockery.

The mockeries of wicked men are not acceptable.

19 The Most High has no pleasure in the offerings of the ungodly,

Neither is he pacified for sins by the multitude of sacrifices.

20 Like one who kills a son before his father’s eyes

is he who brings a sacrifice from the goods of the poor.

21 The bread of the needy is the life of the poor.

He who deprives him of it is a man of blood.

22 Like one who murders his neighbor is he who takes away his living.

Like a shedder of blood is he who deprives a hireling of his hire.

23 When one builds, and another pulls down,

what profit do they have but toil?

24 When one prays, and another curses,

whose voice will the Lord listen to?

25 He who washes himself after touching a dead body, and touches it again,

what does he gain by his washing?

26 Even so a man fasting for his sins,

and going again, and doing the same,

who will listen to his prayer?

What profit does he have in his humiliation?

35

1 He who keeps the law multiplies offerings.

He who heeds the commandments sacrifices a peace offering.

2 He who returns a kindness offers fine flour.

He who gives alms sacrifices a thank offering.

3 To depart from wickedness pleases the Lord.

To depart from unrighteousness is an atoning sacrifice.

4 See that you don’t appear in the presence of the Lord empty.

5 For all these things are done because of the commandment.

6 The offering of the righteous enriches the altar.

The sweet fragrance of it is before the Most High.

7 The sacrifice of a righteous man is acceptable.

It won’t be forgotten.

8 Glorify the Lord with generosity.

Don’t reduce the first fruits of your hands.

9 In every gift show a cheerful countenance,

And dedicate your tithe with gladness.

10 Give to the Most High according as he has given.

As your hand has found, give generously.

11 For the Lord repays,

and he will repay you sevenfold.

12 Don’t plan to bribe him with gifts, for he will not receive them.

Don’t set your mind on an unrighteous sacrifice,

For the Lord is the judge,

and with him is no respect of persons.

13 He won’t accept any person against a poor man.

He will listen to the prayer of him who is wronged.

14 He will in no way despise the supplication of the fatherless

or the widow, when she pours out her tale.

15 Don’t the tears of the widow run down her cheek?

Isn’t her cry against him who has caused them to fall?

16 He who serves God according to his good pleasure will be accepted.

His supplication will reach to the clouds.

17 The prayer of the humble pierces the clouds.

until it comes near, he will not be comforted.

He won’t depart until the Most High visits

and he judges righteously and executes judgment.

18 And the Lord will not be slack, neither will he be patient toward them,

until he has crushed the loins of the unmerciful.

He will repay vengeance to the heathen

until he has taken away the multitude of the arrogant

and broken in pieces the sceptres of the unrighteous,

19 until he has rendered to every man according to his deeds,

and repaid the works of men according to their plans,

until he has judged the cause of his people,

and he will make them rejoice in his mercy.

20 Mercy is as welcome in the time of his affliction,

like clouds of rain in the time of drought.

36

1 Have mercy upon us, O Lord the God of all, and look at us with favor;

2 and send your fear upon all the nations.[*]

3 Lift up your hand against the foreign nations

and let them see your mighty power.

4 As you showed your holiness in us before them,

so be magnified in them before us.

5 Let them know you, as we also have known you,

that there is no God but only you, O God.

6 Show new signs, and work various wonders.

Glorify your hand and your right arm.[†]

7 Raise up indignation and pour out wrath.

Take away the adversary and destroy the enemy.

8 Hasten the time and remember your oath.

Let them declare your mighty works.

9 Let him who escapes be devoured by raging fire.

May those who harm your people find destruction.

10 Crush the heads of the rulers of the enemies

who say, “There is no one but ourselves.”

11 Gather all the tribes of Jacob together,

and[‡] take them for your inheritance, as from the beginning.

12 O Lord, have mercy upon the people that is called by your name,

and upon Israel, whom you likened to a firstborn.

13 Have compassion upon the city of your sanctuary,

Jerusalem, the place of your rest.

14 Fill Zion. Exalt your oracles

and fill your people with your glory.

15 Give testimony to those who were your creatures in the beginning,

and fulfill the prophecies that have been spoken in your name.

16 Reward those who wait for you,

and men will put their trust in your prophets.

17 Listen, O Lord, to the prayer of your servants,

according to the blessing of Aaron concerning your people;

and all those who are on the earth will know

that you are the Lord, the[§] eternal God.

18 The belly will eat any food,

but one food is better than another.

19 The mouth tastes meats taken in hunting,

so does an understanding heart detect false speech.

20 A contrary heart will cause heaviness.

A man of experience will pay him back.

21 A woman will receive any man,

but one daughter is better than another.

22 The beauty of a woman cheers the countenance.

A man desires nothing more.

23 If kindness and humility are on her tongue,

her husband is not like other sons of men.

24 He who gets a wife gets his richest treasure,

a help meet for him and a pillar of support.

25 Where no hedge is, the property will be plundered.

He who has no wife will mourn as he wanders.

26 For who would trust a nimble robber who skips from city to city?

Even so, who would trust a man who has no nest, and lodges wherever he finds himself at nightfall?

37

1 Every friend will say, “I also am his friend”;

but there is a friend which is only a friend in name.

2 Isn’t there a grief in it even to death

when a companion and friend is turned into an enemy?

3 O wicked imagination, why were you formed

to cover the dry land with deceit?

4 There is a companion who rejoices in the gladness of a friend,

but in time of affliction will be against him.

5 There is a companion who for the belly’s sake labors with his friend,

yet in the face of battle will carry his buckler.

6 Don’t forget a friend in your soul.

Don’t be unmindful of him in your riches.

7 Every counselor extols counsel,

but some give counsel in their own interest.

8 Let your soul beware of a counselor,

and know in advance what is his interest

(for he will take counsel for himself),

lest he cast the lot against you,

9 and say to you, “Your way is good.”

Then he will stand near you, to see what will happen to you.

10 Don’t take counsel with one who looks askance at you.

Hide your counsel from those who are jealous of you.

11 Don’t consult with a woman about her rival,

with a coward about war,

with a merchant about business,

with a buyer about selling,

with an envious man about thankfulness,

with an unmerciful man about kindliness,

with a sluggard about any kind of work,

with a hireling in your house about finishing his work,

or with an idle servant about much business.

Pay no attention to these in any matter of counsel.

12 But rather be continually with a godly man,

whom you know to be a keeper of the commandments,

who in his soul is as your own soul,

and who will grieve with you, if you fail.

13 Make the counsel of your heart stand,

for there is no one more faithful to you than it.

14 For a man’s soul is sometimes inclined to inform him

better than seven watchmen who sit on high on a watch-tower.

15 Above all this ask the Most High

that he may direct your way in truth.

16 Let reason be the beginning of every work.

Let counsel go before every action.

17 As a token of the changing of the heart,

18 four kinds of things rise up:

good and evil, life and death.

That which rules over them continually is the tongue.

19 There is one who is clever and the instructor of many,

and yet is unprofitable to his own soul.

20 There is one who is subtle in words, and is hated.

He will be destitute of all food.

21 For grace was not given to him from the Lord,

because he is deprived of all wisdom.

22 There is one who is wise to his own soul;

and the fruits of his understanding are trustworthy in the mouth.

23 A wise man will instruct his own people.

The fruits of his understanding are trustworthy.

24 A wise man will be filled with blessing.

All those who see him will call him happy.

25 The life of a man is counted by days.

The days of Israel are innumerable.

26 The wise man will inherit confidence among his people.

His name will live forever.

27 My son, test your soul in your life.

See what is evil for it, and don’t give in to it.

28 For not all things are profitable for all men.

Not every soul has pleasure in everything.

29 Don’t be insatiable in any luxury.

Don’t be greedy in the things that you eat.

30 For overeating brings disease,

and gluttony causes nausea.

31 Because of gluttony, many have perished,

but he who takes heed shall prolong his life.

38

1 Honor a physician according to your need with the honors due to him,

for truly the Lord has created him.

2 For healing comes from the Most High,

and he shall receive a gift from the king.

3 The skill of the physician will lift up his head.

He will be admired in the sight of great men.

4 The Lord created medicines out of the earth.

A prudent man will not despise them.

5 Wasn’t water made sweet with wood,

that its power might be known?

6 He gave men skill

that he might be glorified in his marvelous works.

7 With them he heals

and takes away pain.

8 With these, the pharmacist makes a mixture.

God’s works won’t be brought to an end.

From him, peace is upon the face of the earth.

9 My son, in your sickness don’t be negligent,

but pray to the Lord, and he will heal you.

10 Put away wrong doing, and direct your hands in righteousness.

Cleanse your heart from all sin.

11 Give a sweet savor and a memorial of fine flour,

and pour oil on your offering, according to your means.

12 Then give place to the physician, for truly the Lord has created him.

Don’t let him leave you, for you need him.

13 There is a time when in recovery is in their hands.

14 For they also shall ask the Lord

to prosper them in diagnosis and in healing for the maintenance of life.

15 He who sins before his Maker,

let him fall into the hands of the physician.

16 My son, let your tears fall over the dead,

and as one who suffers grievously, begin lamentation.

Wind up his body with due honor.

Don’t neglect his burial.

17 Make bitter weeping and make passionate wailing.

Let your mourning be according to his merit,

for one day or two, lest you be spoken evil of;

and so be comforted for your sorrow.

18 For from sorrow comes death.

Sorrow of heart saps one’s strength.

19 In calamity, sorrow also remains.

A poor man’s life is grievous to the heart.

20 Don’t give your heart to sorrow.

Put it away, remembering the end.

21 Don’t forget it, for there is no returning again.

You do him no good, and you would harm yourself.

22 Remember his end, for so also will yours be:

yesterday for me, and today for you.

23 When the dead is at rest, let his remembrance rest.

Be comforted for him when his spirit departs from him.

24 The wisdom of the scribe comes by the opportunity of leisure.

He who has little business can become wise.

25 How could he become wise who holds the plow,

who glories in the shaft of the goad,

who drives oxen and is occupied in their labors,

and who mostly talks about bulls?

26 He will set his heart upon turning his furrows.

His lack of sleep is to give his heifers their fodder.

27 So is every craftsman and master artisan

who passes his time by night as by day,

those who cut engravings of signets.

His diligence is to make great variety.

He sets his heart to preserve likeness in his portraiture,

and is careful to finish his work.

28 So too is the smith sitting by the anvil

and considering the unwrought iron.

The smoke of the fire will waste his flesh.

He toils in the heat of the furnace.

The noise of the hammer deafens his ear.

His eyes are upon the pattern of the object.

He will set his heart upon perfecting his works.

He will be careful to adorn them perfectly.

29 So is the potter sitting at his work

and turning the wheel around with his feet,

who is always anxiously set at his work.

He produces his handiwork in quantity.

30 He will fashion the clay with his arm

and will bend its strength in front of his feet.

He will apply his heart to finish the glazing.

He will be careful to clean the kiln.

31 All these put their trust in their hands.

Each becomes skillful in his own work.

32 Without these no city would be inhabited.

Men wouldn’t reside as foreigners or walk up and down there.

33  [*] They won’t be sought for in the council of the people.

They won’t mount on high in the assembly.

They won’t sit on the seat of the judge.

They won’t understand the covenant of judgment.

Neither will they declare instruction and judgment.

They won’t be found where parables are.

34 But they will maintain the fabric of the age.

Their prayer is in the handiwork of their craft.

39

1 Not so he that has applied his soul

and meditates in the law of the Most High.

He will seek out the wisdom of all the ancients

and will be occupied with prophecies.

2 He will keep the sayings of the men of renown

and will enter in amidst the subtleties of parables.

3 He will seek out the hidden meaning of proverbs

and be conversant in the dark sayings of parables.

4 He will serve among great men

and appear before him who rules.

He will travel through the land of foreign nations,

for he has learned what is good and evil among men.

5 He will apply his heart to return early to the Lord who made him,

and will make supplication before the Most High,

and will open his mouth in prayer,

and will ask for pardon for his sins.

6 If the great Lord wills,

he will be filled with the spirit of understanding;

he will pour forth the words of his wisdom

and in prayer give thanks to the Lord.

7 He will direct his counsel and knowledge,

and he will meditate in his secrets.

8 He will show the instruction which he has been taught

and will glory in the law of the covenant of the Lord.

9 Many will commend his understanding.

So long as the world endures, it won’t be blotted out.

His memory won’t depart.

His name will live from generation to generation.

10 Nations will declare his wisdom.

The congregation will proclaim his praise.

11 If he continues, he will leave a greater name than a thousand.

If he finally rests, it is enough for him.

12 Yet more I will utter, which I have thought about.

I am filled like the full moon.

13 Listen to me, you holy children,

and bud forth like a rose growing by a brook of water.

14 Give a sweet fragrance like frankincense.

Put forth flowers like a lily.

Scatter a sweet smell and sing a song of praise.

Bless the Lord for all his works!

15 Magnify his name

and give utterance to his praise

with the songs on your lips and with harps!

Say this when you utter his praise:

16 All the works of the Lord are exceedingly good,

and every command will be done in its time.

17 No one can say, “What is this?” “Why is that?”

for at the proper time they will all be sought out.

At his word, the waters stood as a heap,

as did the reservoirs of water at the word of his mouth.

18 At his command all his good pleasure is fulfilled.

There is no one that can hinder his salvation.

19 The works of all flesh are before him.

It’s impossible to be hidden from his eyes.

20 He sees from everlasting to everlasting.

There is nothing too wonderful for him.

21 No one can say, “What is this?” “Why is that?”

for all things are created for their own uses.

22 His blessing covered the dry land as a river

and saturated it as a flood.

23 As he has made the waters salty,

so the heathen will inherit his wrath.

24 His ways are plain to the holy.

They are stumbling blocks to the wicked.

25 Good things are created from the beginning for the good.

So are evil things for sinners.

26 The main things necessary for the life of man

are water, fire, iron, salt,

wheat flour, and honey, milk,

the blood of the grape, oil, and clothing.

27 All these things are for good to the godly,

but for sinners, they will be turned into evils.

28 There are winds that are created for vengeance,

and in their fury they lay on their scourges heavily.

In the time of reckoning, they pour out their strength,

and will appease the wrath of him who made them.

29 Fire, hail, famine, and death—

all these are created for vengeance—

30 wild beasts’ teeth, scorpions, adders,

and a sword punishing the ungodly to destruction.

31 They will rejoice in his commandment,

and will be made ready upon earth when needed.

In their seasons, they won’t disobey his command.

32 Therefore from the beginning I was convinced,

and I thought it through and left it in writing:

33 All the works of the Lord are good.

He will supply every need in its time.

34 No one can say, “This is worse than that,”

for they will all be well approved in their time.

35 Now with all your hearts and voices, sing praises

and bless the Lord’s name!

40

1 Great travail is created for every man.

A heavy yoke is upon the sons of Adam,

from the day of their coming forth from their mother’s womb,

until the day for their burial in the mother of all things.

2 The expectation of things to come, and the day of death,

trouble their thoughts, and cause fear in their hearts.

3 From him who sits on a throne of glory,

even to him who is humbled in earth and ashes,

4 from him who wears purple and a crown,

even to him who is clothed in burlap,

5  there is wrath, jealousy, trouble, unrest,

fear of death, anger, and strife.

In the time of rest upon his bed,

his night sleep changes his knowledge.

6 He gets little or no rest,

and afterward in his sleep, as in a day of keeping watch,

he is troubled in the vision of his heart,

as one who has escaped from the front of battle.

7 In the very time of his deliverance, he awakens,

and marvels that the fear is nothing.

8  To all creatures, human and animal,

and upon sinners sevenfold more,

9 come death, bloodshed, strife, sword,

calamities, famine, suffering, and plague.

10 All these things were created for the wicked,

and because of them the flood came.

11 All things that are of the earth turn to the earth again.

All things that are of the waters return into the sea.

12 All bribery and injustice will be blotted out.

Good faith will stand forever.

13 The goods of the unjust will be dried up like a river,

and like a great thunder in rain will go off in noise.

14 In opening his hands, a man will be made glad;

so lawbreakers will utterly fail.

15 The children of the ungodly won’t grow many branches,

and are as unhealthy roots on a sheer rock.

16 The reeds by every water or river bank

will be plucked up before all grass.

17 Kindness is like a garden of blessings.

Almsgiving endures forever.

18 The life of one who labors and is content will be made sweet.

He who finds a treasure is better than both.

19 Children and the building of a city establish a name.

A blameless wife is better than both.

20 Wine and music rejoice the heart.

The love of wisdom is better than both.

21 The pipe and the lute make pleasant melody.

A pleasant tongue is better than both.

22 Your eye desires grace and beauty,

but the green shoots of grain more than both.

23 A friend and a companion is always welcome,

and a wife with her husband is better than both.

24 Relatives and helpers are for a time of affliction,

but almsgiving rescues better than both.

25 Gold and silver will make the foot stand sure,

and counsel is esteemed better than both.

26 Riches and strength will lift up the heart.

The fear of the Lord is better than both.

There is nothing lacking in the fear of the Lord.

In it, there is no need to seek help.

27 The fear of the Lord is like a garden of blessing

and covers a man more than any glory.

28 My son, don’t lead a beggar’s life.

It is better to die than to beg.

29 A man who looks to the table of another,

his life is not to be considered a life.

He will pollute his soul with another person’s food,

but a wise and well-instructed person will beware of that.

30 Begging will be sweet in the mouth of the shameless,

but it kindles a fire in his belly.

41

1 O death, how bitter is the memory of you to a man who is at peace in his possessions,

to the man who has nothing to distract him and has prosperity in all things,

and who still has strength to enjoy food!

2 O death, your sentence is acceptable to a man who is needy and who fails in strength,

who is in extreme old age, is distracted about all things,

is perverse, and has lost patience!

3 Don’t be afraid of the sentence of death.

Remember those who have been before you and who come after.

This is the sentence from the Lord over all flesh.

4 And why do you refuse when it is the good pleasure of the Most High?

Whether life lasts ten, or a hundred, or a thousand years,

there is no inquiry about life in Hades.[*]

5 The children of sinners are abominable children

and they frequent the dwellings of the ungodly.

6 The inheritance of sinners’ children will perish

and with their posterity will be a perpetual disgrace.

7 Children will complain of an ungodly father,

because they suffer disgrace because of him.

8 Woe to you, ungodly men,

who have forsaken the law of the Most High God![†]

9 If you are born, you will be born to a curse.

If you die, a curse will be your portion.

10 All things that are of the earth will go back to the earth;

so the ungodly will go from a curse to perdition.

11 The mourning of men is about their bodies;

but the evil name of sinners will be blotted out.

12 Have regard for your name,

for it continues with you longer than a thousand great treasures of gold.

13 A good life has its number of days,

but a good name continues forever.

14 My children, follow instruction in peace.

But wisdom that is hidden and a treasure that is not seen,

what benefit is in them both?

15 Better is a man who hides his foolishness

than a man who hides his wisdom.

16 Therefore show respect for my words;

for it is not good to retain every kind of shame.

Not everything is approved by all in good faith.

17 Be ashamed of sexual immorality before father and mother,

and of a lie before a prince and a mighty man,

18 of an offense before a judge and ruler,

of iniquity before the congregation and the people,

of unjust dealing before a partner and friend,

19 and of theft in the place where you sojourn.

Be ashamed in regard of the truth of God and his covenant,

of leaning on your elbow at dinner,

of contemptuous behavior in the matter of giving and taking,

20 of silence before those who greet you,

of looking at a woman who is a prostitute,

21 of turning away your face from a kinsman,

of taking away a portion or a gift,

of gazing at a woman who has a husband,

22 of meddling with his maid—and don’t come near her bed,

of abusive speech to friends—and after you have given, don’t insult,

23 of repeating and speaking what you have heard,

and of revealing of secrets.

24 So you will be ashamed of the right things

and find favor in the sight of every man.

42

1 Don’t be ashamed of these things,

and don’t sin to save face:

2 of the law of the Most High and his covenant,

of judgment to do justice to the ungodly,

3 of reckoning with a partner and with travellers,

and of a gift from the inheritance of friends,

4 of exactness of scales and weights,

of getting much or little,

5 of bargaining dealing with merchants,

of frequent correction of children,

and of making the back of an evil slave to bleed.

6  A seal is good where an evil wife is.

Where there are many hands, lock things up.

7 Whatever you hand over, let it be by number and weight.

In giving and receiving, let all be in writing.

8  Don’t be ashamed to instruct the unwise and foolish,

and one of extreme old age who contends with those who are young.

So you will be well instructed indeed

and approved in the sight of every man living.

9 A daughter is a secret cause of wakefulness to a father.

Care for her takes away sleep—

in her youth, lest she pass the flower of her age;

when she is married, lest she should be hated;

10 in her virginity, lest she should be defiled and be with child in her father’s house;

when she has a husband, lest she should transgress;

and when she is married, lest she should be barren.

11 Keep a strict watch over a headstrong daughter,

lest she make you a laughingstock to your enemies,

a byword in the city and notorious among the people,

and shame you in public.

12 Don’t gaze at every beautiful body.

Don’t sit in the midst of women.

13 For from garments comes a moth,

and from a woman comes a woman’s wickedness.

14 Better is the wickedness of a man than a pleasant woman,

a woman who puts you to shame and disgrace.

15 I will make mention now of the works of the Lord,

and will declare the things that I have seen.

The Lord’s works are in his words.

16 The sun that gives light looks at all things.

The Lord’s work is full of his glory.

17 The Lord has not given power to the saints to declare all his marvelous works,

which the Almighty Lord firmly settled,

that the universe might be established in his glory.

18 He searches out the deep and the heart.

He has understanding of their secrets.

For the Most High knows all knowledge.

He sees the signs of the world.

19 He declares the things that are past and the things that shall be,

and reveals the traces of hidden things.

20 No thought escapes him.

There is not a word hidden from him.

21 He has ordered the mighty works of his wisdom.

He is from everlasting to everlasting.

Nothing has been added to them, nor diminished from them.

He had no need of any counselor.

22 How desirable are all his works!

One may see this even in a spark.

23 All these things live and remain forever in all manner of uses.

They are all obedient.

24 All things are in pairs, one opposite the other.

He has made nothing imperfect.

25 One thing establishes the good things of another.

Who could ever see enough of his glory?

43

1 The pride of the heavenly heights is the clear sky,

the appearance of heaven, in the spectacle of its glory.

2 The sun, when it appears, bringing tidings as it rises,

is a marvelous instrument, the work of the Most High.

3 At noon, it dries up the land.

Who can stand against its burning heat?

4 A man tending a furnace is in burning heat,

but the sun three times more, burning up the mountains,

breathing out fiery vapors,

and sending out bright beams, it blinds the eyes.

5 Great is the Lord who made it.

At his word, he hastens on its course.

6 The moon marks the changing seasons,

declares times, and is a sign for the world.

7 From the moon is the sign of feast days,

a light that wanes when it completes its course.

8 The month is called after its name,

increasing wonderfully in its changing—

an instrument of the army on high,

shining in the structure of heaven,

9 the beauty of heaven, the glory of the stars,

an ornament giving light in the highest places of the Lord.

10 At the word of the Holy One, they will stand in due order.

They won’t faint in their watches.

11 Look at the rainbow, and praise him who made it.

It is exceedingly beautiful in its brightness.

12 It encircles the sky with its glorious circle.

The hands of the Most High have stretched it out.

13 By his commandment, he makes the snow fall

and swiftly sends the lightnings of his judgment.

14 Therefore the storehouses are opened,

and clouds fly out like birds.

15 By his mighty power, he makes the clouds strong

and the hailstones are broken in pieces.

16 At his appearing, the mountains will be shaken.

At his will, the south wind will blow.

17 The voice of his thunder rebukes the earth.

So does the northern storm and the whirlwind.

Like birds flying down, he sprinkles the snow.

It falls down like the lighting of locusts.

18 The eye is dazzled at the beauty of its whiteness.

The heart is amazed as it falls.

19 He also pours out frost on the earth like salt.

When it is freezes, it has points like thorns.

20 The cold north wind blows

and ice freezes on the water.

It settles on every pool of water.

The water puts it on like it was a breastplate.

21 It will devour the mountains, burn up the wilderness,

and consume the green grass like fire.

22 A mist coming speedily heals all things.

A dew coming after heat brings cheerfulness.

23 By his counsel, he has calmed the deep

and planted islands in it.

24 Those who sail on the sea tell of its dangers.

We marvel when we hear it with our ears.

25 There are also those strange and wondrous works in it—

variety of all that has life and the huge creatures of the sea.

26 Because of him, his messengers succeed.

By his word, all things hold together.

27 We may say many things, but couldn’t say enough.

The summary of our words is, “He is everything!”

28 How could we have strength to glorify him?

For he is himself the greater than all his works.

29 The Lord is awesome and exceedingly great!

His power is marvelous!

30 Glorify the Lord and exalt him as much as you can!

For even yet, he will surpass that.

When you exalt him, summon your full strength.

Don’t be weary, because you can’t praise him enough.

31 Who has seen him, that he may describe him?

Who can magnify him as he is?

32 Many things greater than these are hidden,

for we have seen just a few of his works.

33 For the Lord made all things.

He gave wisdom to the godly.

44

1 Let us now praise famous men,

our ancestors in their generations.

2 The Lord created great glory in them—

his mighty power from the beginning.

3 Some ruled in their kingdoms

and were men renowned for their power,

giving counsel by their understanding.

Some have spoken in prophecies,

4 leaders of the people by their counsels,

and by their understanding, giving instruction for the people.

Their words in their instruction were wise.

5 Some composed musical tunes,

and set forth verses in writing,

6 rich men endowed with ability,

living peaceably in their homes.

7 All these were honored in their generations,

and were outstanding in their days.

8 Some of them have left a name behind them,

so that others declare their praises.

9 But of others, there is no memory.

They perished as though they had not been.

They become as though they had not been born,

they and their children after them.

10 But these were men of mercy,

whose righteous deeds have not been forgotten.

11 A good inheritance remains with their offspring.

Their children are within the covenant.

12 Their offspring stand fast,

with their children, for their sakes.

13 Their offspring will remain forever.

Their glory won’t be blotted out.

14 Their bodies were buried in peace.

Their name lives to all generations.

15 People will declare their wisdom.

The congregation proclaims their praise.

16 Enoch pleased the Lord, and was taken up,

an example of repentance to all generations.

17 Noah was found perfect and righteous.

In the season of wrath, he kept the race alive.

Therefore a remnant was left on the earth

when the flood came.

18 Everlasting covenants were made with him,

that all flesh should no more be blotted out by a flood.

19 Abraham was a great father of a multitude of nations.

There was none found like him in glory,

20 who kept the law of the Most High,

and was taken into covenant with him.

In his flesh he established the covenant.

When he was tested, he was found faithful.

21 Therefore he assured him by an oath

that the nations would be blessed through his offspring,

that he would multiply him like the dust of the earth,

exalt his offspring the stars,

and cause them to inherit from sea to sea,

and from the Euphrates River to the utmost parts of the earth.

22 In Isaac also, he established the same assurance for Abraham his father’s sake,

the blessing of all men, and the covenant.

23 He made it rest upon the head of Jacob.

He acknowledged him in his blessings,

gave to him by inheritance,

and divided his portions.

He distributed them among twelve tribes.

45

1 And he brought out of him a man of mercy,

who found favor in the sight of all people,

a man loved by God and men, even Moses,

whose memory is blessed.

2 He made him equal to the glory of the saints,

and magnified him in the fears of his enemies.

3 By his words he caused the wonders to cease.

God glorified him in the sight of kings.

He gave him commandments for his people

and showed him part of his glory.

4 He sanctified him in his faithfulness and meekness.

He chose him out of all people.

5 He made him to hear his voice,

led him into the thick darkness,

and gave him commandments face to face,

even the law of life and knowledge,

that he might teach Jacob the covenant,

and Israel his judgments.

6 He exalted Aaron, a holy man like Moses,

even his brother, of the tribe of Levi.

7 He established an everlasting covenant with him,

and gave him the priesthood of the people.

He blessed him with stateliness,

and dressed him in a glorious robe.

8 He clothed him in perfect splendor,

and strengthened him with symbols of authority:

the linen trousers, the long robe, and the ephod.

9 And he encircled him with pomegranates;

with many golden bells around him,

to make a sound as he went,

to make a sound that might be heard in the temple,

for a reminder for the children of his people;

10 with a holy garment, with gold, blue, and purple, the work of the embroiderer;

with an oracle of judgment—Urim and Thummim;

11 with twisted scarlet, the work of the craftsman;

with precious stones engraved like a signet, in a setting of gold, the work of the jeweller,

for a reminder engraved in writing, after the number of the tribes of Israel;

12 with a crown of gold upon the mitre, having engraved on it, as on a signet, “HOLINESS”,

an ornament of honor, the work of an expert,

the desires of the eyes, goodly and beautiful.

13 Before him there never have been anything like it.

No stranger put them on, but only his sons and his offspring perpertually.

14 His sacrifices shall be wholly burned,

twice every day continually.

15 Moses consecrated him,

and anointed him with holy oil.

It was an everlasting covenant with him

and to his offspring, all the days of heaven,

to minister to the Lord, to serve as a priest,

and to bless his people in his name.

16 He chose him out of all living

to offer sacrifice to the Lord—

incense, and a sweet fragrance, for a memorial,

to make atonement for your people.

17 He gave to him in his commandments,

authority in the covenants of judgments,

to teach Jacob the testimonies,

and to enlighten Israel in his law.

18 Strangers conspired against him

and envied him in the wilderness:

Dathan and Abiram with their company,

and the congregation of Korah, with wrath and anger.

19 The Lord saw it, and it displeased him.

In the wrath of his anger, they were destroyed.

He did wonders upon them,

to consume them with flaming fire.

20 He added glory to Aaron,

and gave him a heritage.

He divided to him the first fruits of the increase,

and prepared bread of first fruits in abundance.

21 For they eat the sacrifices of the Lord,

which he gave to him and to his offspring.

22 However, in the land of the people, he has no inheritance,

and he has no portion among the people,

for the Lord himself is your portion and inheritance.

23 Phinehas the son of Eleazar is the third in glory,

in that he was zealous in the fear of the Lord,

and stood fast when the people turned away,

and he made atonement for Israel.

24 Therefore, a covenant of peace was established for him,

that he should be leader of the sanctuary and of his people,

that he and his offspring should have the dignity of the priesthood forever.

25 Also he made a covenant with David the son of Jesse, of the tribe of Judah.

The inheritance of the king is his alone from son to son.

So the inheritance of Aaron is also to his seed.

26  May God give you wisdom in your heart

to judge his people in righteousness,

that their good things may not be abolished,

and that their glory may endure for all their generations.

46

1 Joshua the son of Nun was valiant in war,

and was the successor of Moses in prophecies.

He was made great according to his name

for the saving of[*] God’s elect,

to take vengeance on the enemies that rose up against them,

that he might give Israel their inheritance.

2 How was he glorified in the lifting up his hands,

and in stretching out his sword against the cities!

3 Who before him stood so firm?

For the Lord himself brought his enemies to him.

4 Didn’t the sun go back by his hand?

Didn’t one day become as two?

5 He called upon the Most High, the Mighty One,

when his foes pressed in all around him,

and the great Lord heard him.

6 With hailstones of mighty power,

he caused war to break violently upon the nation,

and[†] on the slope he destroyed those who resisted,

so that the nations might know his armor,

how he fought in the sight of the Lord;

for he followed the Mighty One.

7 Also in the time of Moses, he did a work of mercy—

he and Caleb the son of Jephunneh—

in that they withstood the adversary,

hindered the people from sin,

and stilled their wicked complaining.

8 And of six hundred thousand people on foot, they two alone were preserved

to bring them into their inheritance,

into a land flowing with milk and honey.

9 The Lord gave strength to Caleb,

and it remained with him to his old age,

so that he entered the hill country,

and his offspring obtained it for an inheritance,

10 that all the children of Israel might see that it is good to follow the Lord.

11 Also the judges, every one by his name,

all whose hearts didn’t engage in immorality,

and who didn’t turn away from the Lord—

may their memory be blessed!

12 May their bones flourish again out of their place.

May the name of those who have been honored be renewed in their children.

13 Samuel, the prophet of the Lord, loved by his Lord,

established a kingdom and anointed princes over his people.

14 By the law of the Lord he judged the congregation,

and the Lord watched over Jacob.

15 By his faithfulness he was proved to be a prophet.

By his words he was known to be faithful in vision.

16 When his enemies pressed on him on every side,

he called upon the Lord, the Mighty One,

with the offering of the suckling lamb.

17 Then the Lord thundered from heaven.

He made his voice heard with a mighty sound.

18 He utterly destroyed the rulers of the Tyrians

and all the princes of the Philistines.

19 Before the time of his age-long sleep,

he testified in the sight of the lord and his anointed,

“I have not taken any man’s goods, so much as a sandal;”

and no one accused him.

20 Even after he fell asleep, he prophesied,

and showed the king his end,

and lifted up his voice from the earth in prophecy,

to blot out the wickedness of the people.

47

1 And after him, Nathan rose up

to prophesy in the days of David.

2 As is the fat when it is separated from the peace offering,

so was David separated from the children of Israel.

3 He played with lions as with kids,

and with bears as with lambs of the flock.

4 In his youth didn’t he kill a giant,

and take away reproach from the people

when he lifted up his hand with a sling stone,

and beat down the boasting Goliath?

5 For he called upon the Most High Lord,

and he gave him strength in his right hand

to kill a man mighty in war,

to exalt the horn of his people.

6 So they glorified him for his tens of thousand,

and praised him for the blessings of the Lord,

in that there a glorious diadem was given to him.

7 For he destroyed the enemies on every side,

and defeated the Philistines his adversaries.

He broke their horn in pieces to this day.

8 In every work of his he gave thanks to the Holy One Most High with words of glory.

He sang praise with his whole heart,

and loved him who made him.

9 He set singers before the altar,

to make sweet melody by their music.[*]

10 He gave beauty to the feasts,

and set in order the seasons to completion

while they praised his holy name,

and the sanctuary resounded from early morning.

11 The Lord took away his sins,

and exalted his horn forever.

He gave him a covenant of kings,

and a glorious throne in Israel.

12 After him a wise son rose up,

who because of him lived in security.

13 Solomon reigned in days of peace.

God gave him rest all around,

that he might set up a house for his name,

and prepare a sanctuary forever.

14 How wise you were made in your youth,

and filled as a river with understanding!

15 Your influence covered the earth,

and you filled it with parables and riddles.

16 Your name reached to the far away islands,

and you were loved for your peace.

17 For your songs, proverbs, parables,

and interpretations, the countries marveled at you.

18 By the name of the Lord God,

who is called the God of Israel,

you gathered gold like tin,

and multiplied silver like lead.

19 You bowed your loins to women,

and in your body you were brought into subjection.

20 You blemished your honor,

and defiled your offspring,

to bring wrath upon your children.

I was grieved for your folly,

21 because the sovereignty was divided,

and a disobedient kingdom ruled out of Ephraim.

22 But the Lord will never forsake his mercy.

He won’t destroy any of his works,

nor blot out the posterity of his elect.

He won’t take away the offspring him who loved him.

He gave a remnant to Jacob,

and to David a root from his own family.

23 So Solomon rested with his fathers.

Of his offspring, he left behind him Rehoboam,

the foolishness of the people, and one who lacked understanding,

who made the people revolt by his counsel.

Also Jeroboam the son of Nebat,

who made Israel to sin,

and gave a way of sin to Ephraim.

24 Their sins were multiplied exceedingly,

until they were removed from their land.

25 For they sought out all manner of wickedness,

until vengeance came upon them.

48

1 Then Elijah arose, the prophet like fire.

His word burned like a torch:

2 He brought a famine upon them,

and by his zeal made them few in number.

3 By the word of the Lord he shut up the heavens.

He brought down fire three times.

4 How you were glorified, O Elijah, in your wondrous deeds!

Whose glory is like yours?

5 You raised up a dead man from death,

from Hades, by the word of the Most High.

6 You brought down kings to destruction,

and honorable men from their sickbeds.

7 You heard rebuke in Sinai,

and judgments of vengeance in Horeb.

8 You anointed kings for retribution,

and prophets to succeed after you.

9 You were taken up in a tempest of fire,

in a chariot of fiery horses.

10 You were recorded for reproofs in their seasons,

to pacify anger, before it broke out into wrath,

to turn the heart of the father to the son,

and to restore the tribes of Jacob.

11 Blessed are those who saw you,

and those who have been beautified with love;

for we also shall surely live.

12 Elijah was wrapped in a whirlwind.

Elisha was filled with his spirit.

In his days he was not moved by the fear of any ruler,

and no one brought him into subjection.

13 Nothing was too hard for him.

When he was buried, his body prophesied.

14 As in his life he did wonders,

so his works were also marvelous in death.

15 For all this the people didn’t repent.

They didn’t depart from their sins,

until they were carried away as a plunder from their land,

and were scattered through all the earth.

The people were left very few in number,

but with a ruler from the house of David.

16 Some of them did that which was right,

but some multiplied sins.

17 Hezekiah fortified his city,

and brought water into its midst.

He tunneled through rock with iron,

and built cisterns for water.

18 In his days Sennacherib invaded,

and sent Rabshakeh, and departed.

He lifted up his hand against Zion,

and boasted great things in his arrogance.

19 Then their hearts and their hands were shaken,

and they were in pain, as women in labor.

20 But they called upon the Lord who is merciful,

spreading out their hands to him.

The Holy One quickly heard them out of Heaven,

and delivered them by the hand of Isaiah.

21 He struck the camp of the Assyrians,

and his angel utterly destroyed them.

22 For Hezekiah did that which was pleasing to the Lord,

and was strong in the ways of his ancestor David,

which Isaiah the prophet commanded,

who was great and faithful in his vision.

23 In his days the sun went backward.

He prolonged the life of the king.

24 He saw by an excellent spirit what would come to pass in the future;

and he comforted those who mourned in Zion.

25 He showed the things that would happen through the end of time,

and the hidden things before they came.

49

1 The memory of Josiah is like the composition of incense

prepared by the work of the perfumer.

It will be sweet as honey in every mouth,

and like music at a banquet of wine.

2 He did what was right in the reforming of the people,

and took away the abominations of iniquity.

3 He set his heart right toward the Lord.

In lawless days, he made godliness prevail.

4 Except David, Hezekiah, and Josiah,

all were wicked,

because they abandoned the law of the Most High.

The kings of Judah came to an end.

5 They gave their power to others,

and their glory to a foreign nation.

6 They set the chosen city of the sanctuary on fire

and made her streets desolate, as it was written by the hand of Jeremiah.

7 For they mistreated him;

yet he was sanctified in the womb to be a prophet,

to root out, to afflict, to destroy

and likewise to build and to plant.

8 Ezekiel saw the vision of glory,

which God showed him on the chariot of the cherubim.

9 For truly he remembered the enemies in rainstorm,

and to do good to those who directed their ways aright.

10 Also of the twelve prophets,[*]

may their bones flourish again out of their place.

He comforted the people of Jacob,

and delivered them by confident hope.

11 How shall we magnify Zerubbabel?

He was like a signet ring on the right hand.

12 So was Jesus the son of Josedek,

who in their days built the house,

and exalted a[†] people holy to the Lord,

prepared for everlasting glory.

13 Also of Nehemiah the memory is great.

He raised up for us fallen walls,

set up the gates and bars,

and rebuilt our houses.

14 No man was created upon the earth like Enoch,

for he was taken up from the earth.

15 Nor was there a man born like Joseph,

a leader of his kindred, a supporter of the people.

Even his bones were cared for.

16 Shem and Seth were honored among men,

but above every living thing in the creation was Adam.

50

1  It was Simon, the son of Onias, the high priest,

who in his life repaired the house,

and in his days strengthened the temple.

2 The foundation was built by him to the height of the double walls,

the lofty retaining walls of the temple enclosure.

3 In his days, a water cistern was dug,

the brazen vessel like the sea in circumference.

4  He planned to save his people from ruin,

and fortified the city against siege.

5 How glorious he was when the people gathered around him

as he came out of the house of the veil!

6 He was like the morning star among clouds,

like the full moon,

7 like the sun shining on the temple of the Most High,

like the rainbow shining in clouds of glory,

8 like roses in the days of first fruits,

like lilies by a water spring,

like the shoot of the frankincense tree in summer time,

9 like fire and incense in the censer,

like a vessel of beaten gold adorned with all kinds of precious stones,

10 like an olive tree loaded with fruit,

and like a cypress growing high among the clouds.

11 When he put on his glorious robe,

and clothed himself in perfect splendor,

ascending to the holy altar,

he made the court of the sanctuary glorious.

12 When he received the portions out of the priests’ hands,

as he stood by the hearth of the altar,

with his kindred like a garland around him,

he was like a young cedar in Lebanon

surrounded by the trunks palm trees.

13 All the sons of Aaron in their glory,

held the Lord’s offering in their hands before all the congregation of Israel.

14 Finishing the service at the altars,

that he might arrange the offering of the Most High, the Almighty,

15 he stretched out his hand to the cup of libation,

and poured out the cup of the grape.

He poured it out at the foot of the altar,

a sweet smelling fragrance to the Most High, the King of all.

16 Then the sons of Aaron shouted.

They sounded the trumpets of beaten work.

They made a great fanfare to be heard,

for a reminder before the Most High.

17 Then all the people together hurried,

and fell down to the ground on their faces

to worship their Lord, the Almighty, God Most High.

18 The singers also praised him with their voices.

There was a sweet melody in the whole house.

19 And the people implored the Lord Most High,

in prayer before him who is merciful,

until the worship of the Lord was finished,

and so they accomplished his service.

20 Then he went down, and lifted up his hands

over the whole congregation of the children of Israel,

to give blessing to the Lord with his lips,

and to glory in his name.

21 He bowed himself down in worship the second time,

to declare the blessing from the Most High.

22 Now bless the God of all,

who everywhere does great things,

who exalts our days from the womb,

and deals with us according to his mercy.

23 May he grant us joyfulness of heart,

and that peace may be in our days in Israel for the days of eternity,

24 to entrust his mercy with us,

and let him deliver us in his time!

25 With two nations is my soul vexed,

and the third is no nation:

26 Those who sit on the mountain of[*] Samaria, the Philistines,

and the foolish people who live in Shechem.

27 I have written in this book the instruction of understanding and knowledge,

I Jesus, the son of Sirach Eleazar, of Jerusalem,

who out of his heart poured forth wisdom.

28 Blessed is he who will exercise these things.

He who lays them up in his heart will become wise.

29 For if he does them, he will be strong in all things,

for the light of the Lord is his guide.[†]

51

A Prayer of Jesus the son of Sirach.

1 I will give thanks to you, O Lord, O King,

and will praise you, O God my Savior.

I give thanks to your name,

2 for you have been my protector and helper,

and delivered my body out of destruction,

and out of the snare of a slanderous tongue,

from lips that fabricate lies.

You were my helper before those who stood by,

3 and delivered me, according to the abundance of your mercy and of your name,

from the gnashings of teeth ready to devour,

out of the hand of those seeking my life,

out of the many afflictions I endured,

4 from the choking of a fire on every side,

and out of the midst of fire that I hadn’t kindled,

5 out of the depth of the belly of Hades,

from an unclean tongue,

and from lying words—

6 the slander of an unrighteous tongue to the king.

My soul drew near to death.

My life was near to Hades.

7 They surrounded me on every side.

There was no one to help me.

I was looking for human help,

and there was none.

8 Then I remembered your mercy, O Lord,

and your working which has been from everlasting,

how you deliver those who wait for you,

and save them out of the hand of their enemies.

9 I lifted up my prayer from the earth,

and prayed for deliverance from death.

10 I called upon the Lord, the Father of my Lord,

that he would not forsake me in the days of affliction,

in the time when there was no help against the proud.

11 I will praise your name continually.

I will sing praise with thanksgiving.

My prayer was heard.

12 You saved me from destruction

and delivered me from the evil time.

Therefore I will give thanks and praise to you,

and bless the name of the Lord.

13 When I was yet young,

before I went abroad,

I sought wisdom openly in my prayer.

14 Before the temple I asked for her.

I will seek her out even to the end.

15 From the first flower to the ripening grape my heart delighted in her.

My foot walked in uprightness.

From my youth I followed her steps.

16 I inclined my ear a little, and received her,

and found for myself much instruction.

17 I profited in her.

I will give glory to him who gives me wisdom.

18 For I determined to practice her.

I was zealous for that which is good.

I will never be put to shame.

19 My soul has wrestled with her.

In my conduct I was exact.

I spread out my hands to the heaven above,

and bewailed my ignorances of her.

20 I directed my soul to her.

In purity I found her.

I got myself a heart joined with her from the beginning.

Therefore I won’t be forsaken.

21 My belly also was troubled to seek her.

Therefore I have gained a good possession.

22 The Lord gave me a tongue for my reward.

I will praise him with it.

23 Draw near to me, all you who are uneducated,

and live in the house of instruction.

24 Why therefore are you all lacking in these things,

and your souls are very thirsty?

25 I opened my mouth and spoke,

“Get her for yourselves without money.”

26 Put your neck under the yoke,

and let your soul receive instruction.

She is near to find.

27 See with your eyes

how that I labored just a little

and found for myself much rest.

28 Get instruction with a great sum of silver,

and gain much gold by her.

29 May your soul rejoice in his mercy,

and may you all not be put to shame in praising him.

30 Work your work before the time comes,

and in his time he will give you your reward.

* 1:5 Verse 5 is omitted by the best authorities: The source of wisdom is God’s word in the highest heaven, and her ways are the eternal commandments.

† 1:7 Verse 7 is omitted by the best authorities: To whom was the knowledge of wisdom manifested? Who has understood her abundant experience?

‡ 1:15 Gr. nested.

§ 1:18 Gr. health of cure.

* 1:18 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities: Both are gifts of God for peace; glory opens out for those who love him. He saw her and took her measure.

† 1:21 Verse 21 is omitted by the best authorities: The fear of the Lord drives away sins. Where it resides, it will turn away all anger.

* 3:7 Some manuscripts add those who fear the Lord honor their father,

† 3:19 Some manuscripts add Many are lofty and renowned, but he reveals his secrets to the humble.

‡ 3:25 Some manuscripts omit verse 25.

* 4:13 Or, she

† 4:23 Some manuscripts omit this line.

✡ 6:30 Numbers 15:38

* 7:12 Gr. Don’t plow

† 7:26 Many authorities omit this line

* 9:9 The preceding line of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

† 9:12 Gr. Hades.

‡ 9:13 Or, authority

* 10:9 Two lines of this verse are here omitted by the best authorities.

† 10:21 Verse 21 is omitted by the best authorities: Fear of the Lord is the beginning of acceptance, but obstinance and pride are the beginning of rejection.

‡ 10:27 The Greek text of this verse is uncertain.

* 11:5 Gr. tyrants

† 11:15-16 Verses 15 and 16 are omitted by the best authorities.

* 12:6 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

† 12:8 Or, punished

* 13:13 Gr. along with.

† 13:14 The remainder of verse 13, and verse 14, are omitted by the best authorities.

‡ 13:25 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

* 16:15-16 Verses 15 and 16 are omitted by the best authorities.

† 16:21 Gr. among hidden things.

‡ 16:22 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

§ 16:23 Gr. heart.

* 16:30 The Greek text of this line is uncertain.

† 16:30 Gr. The soul of every living thing.

* 17:5 Verse 5 is omitted by the best authorities.

† 17:9 Verse 9 is omitted by the best authorities.

‡ 17:10 This line is added by the best authorities.

§ 17:16 Verses 16, 18, and 21 are omitted by the best authorities.

* 17:17 The preceding part of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

† 17:18 Verses 16, 18, and 21 are omitted by the best authorities.

‡ 17:21 Verses 16, 18, and 21 are omitted by the best authorities.

§ 17:22 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

* 17:26 A line is here omitted by the best authorities.

* 18:3 The remainder of verse 2, and verse 3, are omitted by the best authorities.

† 18:27 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

‡ 18:31 Or, a rejoicing to

§ 18:33 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

* 19:5 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

† 19:6 The preceding part of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

‡ 19:18-19 Verses 18 and 19 are omitted by the best authorities.

§ 19:21 The remainder of verse 20, and verse 21, are omitted by the best authorities.

* 19:25 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

* 20:3 Verse 3 is omitted by the best authorities.

† 20:14 A line of this verse is here omitted by the best authorities.

‡ 20:17 The latter part of verse 17 is omitted by the best authorities.

§ 20:32 Verse 32 is omitted by the best authorities.

* 21:5 Gr. him.

† 21:18 Gr. unexamined words.

‡ 21:25 The text seems to be uncertain.

* 22:9-10 Verses 9 and 10 are omitted by the best authorities.

† 22:23 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

* 23:3 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

† 23:4 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

‡ 23:5 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

§ 23:28 Verse 28 is omitted by the best authorities.

* 24:15 See Exodus 30:34.

† 24:18 Verse 18 is omitted by the best authorities.

‡ 24:24 Verse 24 is omitted by the best authorities.

* 25:12 Verse 12 is omitted by the best authorities.

† 25:26 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

* 26:5 Gr. countenance.

† 26:13 or, fatten

‡ 26:19-27 Verses 19-27 are omitted by the best authorities.

* 29:7 Some ancient authorities read Many therefore.

† 29:23 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

* 30:11 This line and the previous two lines are absent from some older MSS.

† 30:12 These three lines are absent from the oldest MSS.

‡ 30:12 These three lines are absent from the oldest MSS.

§ 30:17 The oldest MSS. omit and eternal rest.

* 30:17 Gr. age-long rest.

* 31:2 This appears to be the meaning; but the Greek text here is probably corrupt.

* 33:14 A line of this verse is here omitted by the best authorities.

† 33:32 The Greek text of this line is probably corrupt.

* 36:2 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

† 36:6 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

‡ 36:11 The ancient authorities read I took them for my inheritance: but the Greek text is here very confused.

§ 36:17 Gr. God of the ages.

* 38:33 This line is absent from the oldest MSS.

* 41:4 or, the place of the dead or, Sheol

† 41:8 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

* 46:1 Gr. his.

† 46:6 See Joshua 10:11

* 47:9 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

* 49:10 The remainder of this line is omitted by the best authorities.

† 49:12 Some ancient authorities read temple.

* 50:26 According to some ancient versions, Seir.

† 50:29 The remainder of this verse is omitted by the best authorities.

Song of Solomon

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8

The Song of Solomon

1

1 The Song of songs, which is Solomon’s.

Beloved

2 Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth;

for your love is better than wine.

3 Your oils have a pleasing fragrance.

Your name is oil poured out,

therefore the virgins love you.

4 Take me away with you.

Let’s hurry.

The king has brought me into his rooms.

Friends

We will be glad and rejoice in you.

We will praise your love more than wine!

Beloved

They are right to love you.

5 I am dark, but lovely,

you daughters of Jerusalem,

like Kedar’s tents,

like Solomon’s curtains.

6 Don’t stare at me because I am dark,

because the sun has scorched me.

My mother’s sons were angry with me.

They made me keeper of the vineyards.

I haven’t kept my own vineyard.

7 Tell me, you whom my soul loves,

where you graze your flock,

where you rest them at noon;

for why should I be as one who is veiled

beside the flocks of your companions?

Lover

8 If you don’t know, most beautiful among women,

follow the tracks of the sheep.

Graze your young goats beside the shepherds’ tents.

9 I have compared you, my love,

to a steed in Pharaoh’s chariots.

10 Your cheeks are beautiful with earrings,

your neck with strings of jewels.

Friends

11 We will make you earrings of gold,

with studs of silver.

Beloved

12 While the king sat at his table,

my perfume spread its fragrance.

13 My beloved is to me a sachet of myrrh,

that lies between my breasts.

14 My beloved is to me a cluster of henna blossoms

from the vineyards of En Gedi.

Lover

15 Behold,[*] you are beautiful, my love.

Behold, you are beautiful.

Your eyes are like doves.

Beloved

16 Behold, you are beautiful, my beloved, yes, pleasant;

and our couch is verdant.

Lover

17 The beams of our house are cedars.

Our rafters are firs.

2

Beloved

1 I am a rose of Sharon,

a lily of the valleys.

Lover

2 As a lily among thorns,

so is my love among the daughters.

Beloved

3 As the apple tree among the trees of the wood,

so is my beloved among the sons.

I sat down under his shadow with great delight,

his fruit was sweet to my taste.

4 He brought me to the banquet hall.

His banner over me is love.

5 Strengthen me with raisins,

refresh me with apples;

for I am faint with love.

6 His left hand is under my head.

His right hand embraces me.

7 I adjure you, daughters of Jerusalem,

by the roes, or by the hinds of the field,

that you not stir up, nor awaken love,

until it so desires.

8 The voice of my beloved!

Behold, he comes,

leaping on the mountains,

skipping on the hills.

9 My beloved is like a roe or a young deer.

Behold, he stands behind our wall!

He looks in at the windows.

He glances through the lattice.

10 My beloved spoke, and said to me,

“Rise up, my love, my beautiful one, and come away.

11 For behold, the winter is past.

The rain is over and gone.

12 The flowers appear on the earth.

The time of the singing has come,

and the voice of the turtledove is heard in our land.

13 The fig tree ripens her green figs.

The vines are in blossom.

They give out their fragrance.

Arise, my love, my beautiful one,

and come away.”

Lover

14 My dove in the clefts of the rock,

in the hiding places of the mountainside,

let me see your face.

Let me hear your voice;

for your voice is sweet and your face is lovely.

15 Catch for us the foxes,

the little foxes that plunder the vineyards;

for our vineyards are in blossom.

Beloved

16 My beloved is mine, and I am his.

He browses among the lilies.

17 Until the day is cool, and the shadows flee away,

turn, my beloved,

and be like a roe or a young deer on the mountains of Bether.

3

1 By night on my bed,

I sought him whom my soul loves.

I sought him, but I didn’t find him.

2 I will get up now, and go about the city;

in the streets and in the squares I will seek him whom my soul loves.

I sought him, but I didn’t find him.

3 The watchmen who go about the city found me;

“Have you seen him whom my soul loves?”

4 I had scarcely passed from them,

when I found him whom my soul loves.

I held him, and would not let him go,

until I had brought him into my mother’s house,

into the room of her who conceived me.

5 I adjure you, daughters of Jerusalem,

by the roes, or by the hinds of the field,

that you not stir up nor awaken love,

until it so desires.

6 Who is this who comes up from the wilderness like pillars of smoke,

perfumed with myrrh and frankincense,

with all spices of the merchant?

7 Behold, it is Solomon’s carriage!

Sixty mighty men are around it,

of the mighty men of Israel.

8 They all handle the sword, and are expert in war.

Every man has his sword on his thigh,

because of fear in the night.

9 King Solomon made himself a carriage

of the wood of Lebanon.

10 He made its pillars of silver,

its bottom of gold, its seat of purple,

the middle of it being paved with love,

from the daughters of Jerusalem.

11 Go out, you daughters of Zion, and see king Solomon,

with the crown with which his mother has crowned him,

in the day of his weddings,

in the day of the gladness of his heart.

4

Lover

1 Behold, you are beautiful, my love.

Behold, you are beautiful.

Your eyes are like doves behind your veil.

Your hair is as a flock of goats,

that descend from Mount Gilead.

2 Your teeth are like a newly shorn flock,

which have come up from the washing,

where every one of them has twins.

None is bereaved among them.

3 Your lips are like scarlet thread.

Your mouth is lovely.

Your temples are like a piece of a pomegranate behind your veil.

4 Your neck is like David’s tower built for an armory,

on which a thousand shields hang,

all the shields of the mighty men.

5 Your two breasts are like two fawns

that are twins of a roe,

which feed among the lilies.

6 Until the day is cool, and the shadows flee away,

I will go to the mountain of myrrh,

to the hill of frankincense.

7 You are all beautiful, my love.

There is no spot in you.

8 Come with me from Lebanon, my bride,

with me from Lebanon.

Look from the top of Amana,

from the top of Senir and Hermon,

from the lions’ dens,

from the mountains of the leopards.

9 You have ravished my heart, my sister, my bride.

You have ravished my heart with one of your eyes,

with one chain of your neck.

10 How beautiful is your love, my sister, my bride!

How much better is your love than wine,

the fragrance of your perfumes than all kinds of spices!

11 Your lips, my bride, drip like the honeycomb.

Honey and milk are under your tongue.

The smell of your garments is like the smell of Lebanon.

12 My sister, my bride, is a locked up garden;

a locked up spring,

a sealed fountain.

13 Your shoots are an orchard of pomegranates, with precious fruits,

henna with spikenard plants,

14 spikenard and saffron,

calamus and cinnamon, with every kind of incense tree;

myrrh and aloes, with all the best spices,

15 a fountain of gardens,

a well of living waters,

flowing streams from Lebanon.

Beloved

16 Awake, north wind, and come, you south!

Blow on my garden, that its spices may flow out.

Let my beloved come into his garden,

and taste his precious fruits.

5

Lover

1 I have come into my garden, my sister, my bride.

I have gathered my myrrh with my spice;

I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey;

I have drunk my wine with my milk.

Friends

Eat, friends!

Drink, yes, drink abundantly, beloved.

Beloved

2 I was asleep, but my heart was awake.

It is the voice of my beloved who knocks:

“Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, my undefiled;

for my head is filled with dew,

and my hair with the dampness of the night.”

3 I have taken off my robe. Indeed, must I put it on?

I have washed my feet. Indeed, must I soil them?

4 My beloved thrust his hand in through the latch opening.

My heart pounded for him.

5 I rose up to open for my beloved.

My hands dripped with myrrh,

my fingers with liquid myrrh,

on the handles of the lock.

6 I opened to my beloved;

but my beloved left, and had gone away.

My heart went out when he spoke.

I looked for him, but I didn’t find him.

I called him, but he didn’t answer.

7 The watchmen who go about the city found me.

They beat me.

They bruised me.

The keepers of the walls took my cloak away from me.

8 I adjure you, daughters of Jerusalem,

If you find my beloved,

that you tell him that I am faint with love.

Friends

9 How is your beloved better than another beloved,

you fairest among women?

How is your beloved better than another beloved,

that you do so adjure us?

Beloved

10 My beloved is white and ruddy.

The best among ten thousand.

11 His head is like the purest gold.

His hair is bushy, black as a raven.

12 His eyes are like doves beside the water brooks,

washed with milk, mounted like jewels.

13 His cheeks are like a bed of spices with towers of perfumes.

His lips are like lilies, dropping liquid myrrh.

14 His hands are like rings of gold set with beryl.

His body is like ivory work overlaid with sapphires.

15 His legs are like pillars of marble set on sockets of fine gold.

His appearance is like Lebanon, excellent as the cedars.

16 His mouth is sweetness;

yes, he is altogether lovely.

This is my beloved, and this is my friend,

daughters of Jerusalem.

6

Friends

1 Where has your beloved gone, you fairest among women?

Where has your beloved turned, that we may seek him with you?

Beloved

2 My beloved has gone down to his garden,

to the beds of spices,

to pasture his flock in the gardens, and to gather lilies.

3 I am my beloved’s, and my beloved is mine.

He browses among the lilies.

Lover

4 You are beautiful, my love, as Tirzah,

lovely as Jerusalem,

awesome as an army with banners.

5 Turn away your eyes from me,

for they have overcome me.

Your hair is like a flock of goats,

that lie along the side of Gilead.

6 Your teeth are like a flock of ewes,

which have come up from the washing,

of which every one has twins;

not one is bereaved among them.

7 Your temples are like a piece of a pomegranate behind your veil.

8 There are sixty queens, eighty concubines,

and virgins without number.

9 My dove, my perfect one, is unique.

She is her mother’s only daughter.

She is the favorite one of her who bore her.

The daughters saw her, and called her blessed.

The queens and the concubines saw her, and they praised her.

10 Who is she who looks out as the morning,

beautiful as the moon,

clear as the sun,

and awesome as an army with banners?

11 I went down into the nut tree grove,

to see the green plants of the valley,

to see whether the vine budded,

and the pomegranates were in flower.

12 Without realizing it,

my desire set me with my royal people’s chariots.

Friends

13 Return, return, Shulammite!

Return, return, that we may gaze at you.

Lover

Why do you desire to gaze at the Shulammite,

as at the dance of Mahanaim?

7

1 How beautiful are your feet in sandals, prince’s daughter!

Your rounded thighs are like jewels,

the work of the hands of a skillful workman.

2 Your body is like a round goblet,

no mixed wine is wanting.

Your waist is like a heap of wheat,

set about with lilies.

3 Your two breasts are like two fawns,

that are twins of a roe.

4 Your neck is like an ivory tower.

Your eyes are like the pools in Heshbon by the gate of Bathrabbim.

Your nose is like the tower of Lebanon which looks toward Damascus.

5 Your head on you is like Carmel.

The hair of your head like purple.

The king is held captive in its tresses.

6 How beautiful and how pleasant you are,

love, for delights!

7 This, your stature, is like a palm tree,

your breasts like its fruit.

8 I said, “I will climb up into the palm tree.

I will take hold of its fruit.”

Let your breasts be like clusters of the vine,

the smell of your breath like apples.

9 Your mouth is like the best wine,

that goes down smoothly for my beloved,

gliding through the lips of those who are asleep.

Beloved

10 I am my beloved’s.

His desire is toward me.

11 Come, my beloved! Let’s go out into the field.

Let’s lodge in the villages.

12 Let’s go early up to the vineyards.

Let’s see whether the vine has budded,

its blossom is open,

and the pomegranates are in flower.

There I will give you my love.

13 The mandrakes produce fragrance.

At our doors are all kinds of precious fruits, new and old,

which I have stored up for you, my beloved.

8

1 Oh that you were like my brother,

who nursed from the breasts of my mother!

If I found you outside, I would kiss you;

yes, and no one would despise me.

2 I would lead you, bringing you into the house of my mother,

who would instruct me.

I would have you drink spiced wine,

of the juice of my pomegranate.

3 His left hand would be under my head.

His right hand would embrace me.

4 I adjure you, daughters of Jerusalem,

that you not stir up, nor awaken love,

until it so desires.

Friends

5 Who is this who comes up from the wilderness,

leaning on her beloved?

Beloved

Under the apple tree I awakened you.

There your mother conceived you.

There she was in labor and bore you.

6 Set me as a seal on your heart,

as a seal on your arm;

for love is strong as death.

Jealousy is as cruel as Sheol.[*]

Its flashes are flashes of fire,

a very flame of Yahweh.[†]

7 Many waters can’t quench love,

neither can floods drown it.

If a man would give all the wealth of his house for love,

he would be utterly scorned.

Brothers

8 We have a little sister.

She has no breasts.

What shall we do for our sister

in the day when she is to be spoken for?

9 If she is a wall,

we will build on her a turret of silver.

If she is a door,

we will enclose her with boards of cedar.

Beloved

10 I am a wall, and my breasts like towers,

then I was in his eyes like one who found peace.

11 Solomon had a vineyard at Baal Hamon.

He leased out the vineyard to keepers.

Each was to bring a thousand shekels[‡] of silver for its fruit.

12 My own vineyard is before me.

The thousand are for you, Solomon,

two hundred for those who tend its fruit.

Lover

13 You who dwell in the gardens, with friends in attendance,

let me hear your voice!

Beloved

14 Come away, my beloved!

Be like a gazelle or a young stag on the mountains of spices!

* 1:15 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

* 8:6 Sheol is the place of the dead.

† 8:6 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

‡ 8:11 A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces, so 1000 shekels is about 10 kilograms or about 22 pounds.

Titus

1
2
3

Paul’s Letter to Titus

1

1 Paul, a servant of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ,[*] according to the faith of God’s chosen ones and the knowledge of the truth which is according to godliness, 2 in hope of eternal life, which God, who can’t lie, promised before time began; 3 but in his own time revealed his word in the message with which I was entrusted according to the commandment of God our Savior, 4 to Titus, my true child according to a common faith: Grace, mercy, and peace from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ our Savior.

5 I left you in Crete for this reason, that you would set in order the things that were lacking and appoint elders in every city, as I directed you— 6 if anyone is blameless, the husband of one wife, having children who believe, who are not accused of loose or unruly behavior. 7 For the overseer must be blameless, as God’s steward, not self-pleasing, not easily angered, not given to wine, not violent, not greedy for dishonest gain; 8 but given to hospitality, a lover of good, sober minded, fair, holy, self-controlled, 9 holding to the faithful word which is according to the teaching, that he may be able to exhort in the sound doctrine, and to convict those who contradict him.

10 For there are also many unruly men, vain talkers and deceivers, especially those of the circumcision, 11 whose mouths must be stopped: men who overthrow whole houses, teaching things which they ought not, for dishonest gain’s sake. 12 One of them, a prophet of their own, said, “Cretans are always liars, evil beasts, and idle gluttons.” 13 This testimony is true. For this cause, reprove them sharply, that they may be sound in the faith, 14 not paying attention to Jewish fables and commandments of men who turn away from the truth. 15 To the pure, all things are pure, but to those who are defiled and unbelieving, nothing is pure; but both their mind and their conscience are defiled. 16 They profess that they know God, but by their deeds they deny him, being abominable, disobedient, and unfit for any good work.

2

1 But say the things which fit sound doctrine, 2 that older men should be temperate, sensible, sober minded, sound in faith, in love, and in perseverance, 3 and that older women likewise be reverent in behavior, not slanderers nor enslaved to much wine, teachers of that which is good, 4 that they may train the young wives to love their husbands, to love their children, 5 to be sober minded, chaste, workers at home, kind, being in subjection to their own husbands, that God’s word may not be blasphemed.

6 Likewise, exhort the younger men to be sober minded. 7 In all things show yourself an example of good works. In your teaching, show integrity, seriousness, incorruptibility, 8 and soundness of speech that can’t be condemned, that he who opposes you may be ashamed, having no evil thing to say about us.

9 Exhort servants to be in subjection to their own masters and to be well-pleasing in all things, not contradicting, 10 not stealing, but showing all good fidelity, that they may adorn the doctrine of God, our Savior, in all things. 11 For the grace of God has appeared, bringing salvation to all men, 12 instructing us to the intent that, denying ungodliness and worldly lusts, we would live soberly, righteously, and godly in this present age; 13 looking for the blessed hope and appearing of the glory of our great God and Savior, Jesus Christ, 14 who gave himself for us, that he might redeem us from all iniquity and purify for himself a people for his own possession, zealous for good works.

15 Say these things and exhort and reprove with all authority. Let no one despise you.

3

1 Remind them to be in subjection to rulers and to authorities, to be obedient, to be ready for every good work, 2 to speak evil of no one, not to be contentious, to be gentle, showing all humility toward all men. 3 For we were also once foolish, disobedient, deceived, serving various lusts and pleasures, living in malice and envy, hateful, and hating one another. 4 But when the kindness of God our Savior and his love toward mankind appeared, 5 not by works of righteousness which we did ourselves, but according to his mercy, he saved us through the washing of regeneration and renewing by the Holy Spirit, 6 whom he poured out on us richly through Jesus Christ our Savior; 7 that being justified by his grace, we might be made heirs according to the hope of eternal life. 8 This saying is faithful, and concerning these things I desire that you insist confidently, so that those who have believed God may be careful to maintain good works. These things are good and profitable to men; 9 but shun foolish questionings, genealogies, strife, and disputes about the law; for they are unprofitable and vain. 10 Avoid a factious man after a first and second warning, 11 knowing that such a one is perverted and sinful, being self-condemned.

12 When I send Artemas to you, or Tychicus, be diligent to come to me to Nicopolis, for I have determined to winter there. 13 Send Zenas the lawyer and Apollos on their journey speedily, that nothing may be lacking for them. 14 Let our people also learn to maintain good works to meet necessary needs, that they may not be unfruitful.

15 All who are with me greet you. Greet those who love us in faith.

Grace be with you all. Amen.

* 1:1 “Christ” means “Anointed One”.

Tobit

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14

TOBIT

Tobit is recognized as Deuterocanonical Scripture by the Roman Catholic, Greek Orthodox, and Russian Orthodox Churches.

1

1 The book of the words of Tobit, the son of Tobiel, the son of Ananiel, the son of Aduel, the son of Gabael, of the seed of Asiel, of the tribe of Naphtali; 2 who in the days of Enemessar[*] king of the Assyrians was carried away captive out of Thisbe, which is on the right hand of Kedesh Naphtali in Galilee above Asher.

3 I, Tobit walked in the ways of truth and righteousness all the days of my life, and I did many alms deeds to my kindred and my nation, who went with me into the land of the Assyrians, to Nineveh. 4 When I was in my own country, in the land of Israel, while I was yet young, all the tribe of Naphtali my father fell away from the house of Jerusalem, which was chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, that all the tribes should sacrifice there, and the temple of the habitation of the Most High was hallowed and built therein for all ages. 5 All the tribes which fell away together sacrificed to the heifer Baal, and so did the house of Naphtali my father. 6 I alone went often to Jerusalem at the feasts, as it has been ordained to all Israel by an everlasting decree, having the first fruits and the tenths of my increase, and that which was first shorn; and I gave them at the altar to the priests the sons of Aaron. 7 I gave a tenth part of all my increase to the sons of Levi, who ministered at Jerusalem. A second tenth part I sold away, and went, and spent it each year at Jerusalem. 8 A third tenth I gave to them to whom it was appropriate, as Deborah my father’s mother had commanded me, because I was left an orphan by my father. 9 When I became a man, I took as wife Anna of the seed of our own family. With her, I became the father of Tobias. 10 When I was carried away captive to Nineveh, all my kindred and my relatives ate of the bread of the Gentiles; 11 but I kept myself from eating, 12 because I remembered God with all my soul. 13 So the Most High gave me grace and favor[†] in the sight of Enemessar, and I was his purchasing agent. 14 And I went into Media, and left ten talents of silver in trust with Gabael, the brother of Gabrias, at Rages of Media.

15 And when Enemessar was dead, Sennacherib his son reigned in his place. In his time, the highways were troubled,[‡] and I could no longer go into Media. 16 In the days of Enemessar, I did many alms deeds to my kindred: I gave my bread to the hungry, 17 and my garments to the naked. If I saw any of my race dead, and thrown out on[§] the wall of Ninevah, I buried him. 18 If Sennacherib the king killed any, when he came fleeing from Judea, I buried them privately; for in his wrath he killed many; and the bodies were sought for by the king, and were not found. 19 But one of the Ninevites went and showed to the king concerning me, how I buried them, and hid myself; and when I knew that I was sought for to be put to death, I withdrew myself for fear. 20 And all my goods were forcibly taken away, and there was nothing left to me, save my wife Anna and my son Tobias. 21 No more than fifty five days passed before two of his sons killed him, and they fled into the mountains of Ararat. And Sarchedonus[*] his son reigned in his place; and he appointed Achiacharus my brother Anael’s son over all the accounts of his kingdom, and over all his affairs. 22 Achiacharus requested me, and I came to Nineveh. Now Achiacharus was cupbearer, keeper of the signet, steward, and overseer of the accounts. Sarchedonus appointed him next to himself, but he was my brother’s son.

2

1 Now when I had come home again, and my wife Anna was restored to me, and my son Tobias, in the feast of Pentecost, which is the holy feast of the seven weeks, there was a good dinner prepared me, and I sat down to eat. 2 I saw abundance of meat, and I said to my son, “Go and bring whatever poor man you find of our kindred, who is mindful of the Lord. Behold, I wait for you.”

3 Then he came, and said, “Father, one of our race is strangled, and has been cast out in the marketplace.” 4 Before I had tasted anything, I sprang up, and took him up into a chamber until the sun had set. 5 Then I returned, washed myself, ate my bread in heaviness, 6 and remembered the prophecy of Amos, as he said,

[✡]“Your feasts will be turned into mourning,

and all your mirth into lamentation.

7 So I wept: and when the sun had set, I went and dug a grave, and buried him. 8 My neighbors mocked me, and said, “He is no longer afraid to be put to death for this matter; and yet he fled away. Behold, he buries the dead again.” 9 The same night I returned from burying him, and slept by the wall of my courtyard, being polluted; and my face was uncovered. 10 I didn’t know that there were sparrows in the wall. My eyes were open and the sparrows dropped warm dung into my eyes, and white films came over my eyes. I went to the physicians, and they didn’t help me; but Achiacharus nourished me, until I went[*] into Elymais.

11 My wife Anna wove cloth in the women’s chambers, 12 and sent the work back to the owners. They on their part paid her wages, and also gave her a kid. 13 But when it came to my house, it began to cry, and I said to her, Where did this kid come from? Is it stolen? Give it back to the owners; for it is not lawful to eat anything that is stolen. 14 But she said, “It has been given to me for a gift more than the wages.”

I didn’t believe her, and I asked her to return it to the owners; and I was ashamed of her.

But she answered and said to me, “Where are your alms and your righteous deeds? Behold, you and all your works are known.[†]”

3

1 I was grieved and wept, and prayed in sorrow, saying,

2 “O Lord, you are righteous, and all your works and all your ways are mercy and truth, and you judge true and righteous judgment forever. 3 Remember me, and look at me. Don’t take vengeance on me for my sins and my ignorances, and the sins of my fathers who sinned before you. 4 For they disobeyed your commandments. You gave us as plunder, for captivity, for death, and for a proverb of reproach to all the nations among whom we are dispersed. 5 Now your judgments are many and true, that you should deal with me according to my sins and the sins of my fathers, because we didn’t keep your commandments, for we didn’t walk in truth before you. 6 Now deal with me according to that which is pleasing in your sight. Command my spirit to be taken from me, that I may be released, and become earth. For it is more profitable for me to die rather than to live, because I have heard false reproaches, and there is much sorrow in me. Command that I be released from my distress, now, and go to the everlasting place. Don’t turn your face away from me.”

7 The same day it happened to Sarah the daughter of Raguel in Ecbatana of Media, that she also was reproached by her father’s maidservants; 8 because that she had been given to seven husbands, and Asmodaeus the evil spirit[*] killed them, before they had lain with her. And they said to her, “Do you not know that you strangle your husbands? You have had already seven husbands, and you haven’t borne the name of any one of them. 9 Why do you scourge us? If they are dead, go your ways with them. Let us never see either son or daughter from you.” 10 When she heard these things, she was grieved exceedingly, so that she thought about hanging herself. Then she said, “I am the only daughter of my father. If I do this, it will be a reproach to him, and I will bring down his old age with sorrow to the grave.[†]” 11 Then she prayed by the window, and said, “Blessed are you, O Lord my God, and blessed is your holy and honorable name forever! Let all your works praise you forever! 12 And now, Lord, I have set my eyes and my face toward you. 13 Command that I be released from the earth, and that I no longer hear reproach. 14 You know, Lord, that I am pure from all sin with man, 15 and that I never polluted my name or the name of my father in the land of my captivity. I am the only daughter of my father, and he has no child that will be his heir, nor brother near him, nor son belonging to him, that I should keep myself for a wife to him. Seven husbands of mine are dead already. Why should I live? If it doesn’t please you to kill me, command some regard to be had of me, and pity taken of me, and that I hear no more reproach.”

16 The prayer of both was heard before the glory of the great God. 17 Raphael also was sent to heal them both, to scale away the white films from Tobit’s eyes, and to give Sarah the daughter of Raguel for a wife to Tobias the son of Tobit; and to bind Asmodaeus the evil spirit[‡]; because it belonged to Tobias that he should inherit her. At that very time, Tobit returned and entered into his house, and Sarah the daughter of Raguel came down from her upper chamber.

4

1 In that day Tobit remembered the money which he had left in trust with Gabael in Rages of Media, 2 and he said to himself, I have asked for death; why do I not call my son Tobias, that I may explain to him about the money before I die? 3 And he called him, and said,

“My child, if I die, bury me. Don’t despise your mother. Honor her all the days of your life, and do that which is pleasing to her, and don’t grieve her. 4 Remember, my child, that she has seen many dangers for you, when you were in her womb. When she is dead, bury her by me in one grave. 5 My child, be mindful of the Lord our God all your days, and don’t let your will be set to sin and to transgress his commandments: do righteousness all the days of your life, and don’t follow the ways of unrighteousness. 6 For if you do what is true, your deeds will prosperously succeed for you, and for all those who do righteousness. 7 Give alms from your possessions. When you give alms, don’t let your eye be envious. Don’t turn away your face from any poor man, and the face of God won’t be turned away from you. 8 As your possessions are, give alms of it according to your abundance. If you have little, don’t be afraid to give alms according to that little; 9 for you lay up a good treasure for yourself against the day of necessity; 10 because alms-giving delivers from death, and doesn’t allow you to come into darkness. 11 Alms is a good gift in the sight of the Most High for all that give it. 12 Beware, my child, of all whoredom, and take first a wife of the seed of your fathers. Don’t take a strange wife, who is not of your father’s tribe; for we are the descendants of the prophets. Remember, my child, that Noah, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, our fathers of old time, all took wives of their kindred, and were blessed in their children, and their seed will inherit the land. 13 And now, my child, love your kindred, and don’t scorn your kindred and the sons and the daughters of your people in your heart, to take a wife of them; for in scornfulness is destruction and much trouble, and in naughtiness is decay and great lack; for naughtiness is the mother of famine. 14 Don’t let the wages of any man who works for you wait with you, but give it to him out of hand. If you serve God, you will be rewarded. Take heed to yourself, my child, in all your works, and be discreet in all your behavior. 15 And what you yourself hate, do to no man. Don’t drink wine to drunkenness, and don’t let drunkenness go with you on your way. 16 Give of your bread to the hungry, and of your garments to those who are naked. Give alms from all your abundance. Don’t let your eye be envious when you give alms. 17 Pour out your bread on the burial[*] of the just, and give nothing to sinners. 18 Ask counsel of every man who is wise, and don’t despise any counsel that is profitable. 19 Bless the Lord your God at all times, and ask of him that your ways may be made straight, and that all your paths and counsels may prosper; for every nation has no counsel; but the Lord himself gives all good things, and he humbles whom he will, as he will. And now, my child, remember my commandments, and let them not be blotted out of your mind. 20 And now I explain to you about the ten talents of silver, which I left in trust with Gabael the son of Gabrias at Rages of Media. 21 And fear not, my child, because we are made poor. You have much wealth, if you fear God, and depart from all sin, and do that which is pleasing in his sight.”

5

1 Then Tobias answered and said to him, “Father, I will do all things, whatever you have commanded me. 2 But how could I receive the money, since I don’t know him?”

3 He gave him the handwriting, and said to him, “Seek a man who will go with you, and I will give him wages, whiles I yet live; and go and receive the money.”

4 He went to seek a man, and found Raphael who was an angel; 5 and he didn’t know it. He said to him, “Can I go with you to Rages of Media? Do you know those places well?”

6 The angel said to him, “I will go with you. I know the way well. I have lodged with our brother Gabael.”

7 Tobias said to him, “Wait for me, and I will tell my father.”

8 He said to him, “Go, and don’t wait. And he went in and said to his father, “Behold, I have found someone who will go with me.”

But he said, “Call him to me, that I may know of what tribe he is, and whether he be a trustworthy man to go with you.”

9 So he called him, and he came in, and they saluted one another. 10 And Tobit said to him, “Brother, of what tribe and of what family are you? Tell me.”

11 He said to him, “Do you seek a tribe and a family, or a hired man which will go with your son?”

And Tobit said to him, “I want to know, brother, your kindred and your name.”

12 And he said, “I am Azarias, the son of Ananias the great, of your kindred.”

13 And he said to him, “Welcome, brother. Don’t be angry with me, because I sought to know your tribe and family. You are my brother, of an honest and good lineage; for I knew Ananias and Jathan, the sons of Shemaiah the great, when we went together to Jerusalem to worship, and offered the firstborn, and the tenths of our increase; and they didn’t go astray in the error of our kindred. My brother, you are of a great stock. 14 But tell me, what wages shall I give you? A drachma a day, and those things that be necessary for you, as to my son? 15 And moreover, if you both return safe and sound, I will add something to your wages.”

16 And so they agreed. And he said to Tobias, “Prepare yourself for the journey. May God prosper you.” So his son prepared what was needful for the journey, and his father said to him, “Go with this man; but God, who dwells in heaven, will prosper your journey. May his angel go with you.”

Then they both departed, and the young man’s dog went with them. 17 But Anna his mother wept, and said to Tobit, “Why have you sent away our child? Isn’t he the staff of our hand, in going in and out before us? 18 Don’t be greedy to add money to money; but let it be as refuse compared to our child. 19 For what the Lord has given us to live is enough for us.”

20 Tobit said to her, “Don’t worry, my sister. He will return safe and sound, and your eyes will see him. 21 For a good angel will go with him. His journey will be prospered, and he will return safe and sound.”

22 So she stopped weeping.

6

1 Now as they went on their journey, they came at evening to the river Tigris, and they lodged there. 2 But the young man went down to wash himself, and a fish leaped out of the river, and would have swallowed up the young man. 3 But the angel said to him, “Grab the fish!”

So the young man grabbed the fish, and hauled it up onto the land.

4 And the angel said to him, “Cut the fish open, and take the heart, the liver, and the bile, and keep them with you.” 5 And the young man did as the angel commanded him; but they roasted the fish, and ate it. And they both went on their way, till they drew near to Ecbatana.

6 The young man said to the angel, “Brother Azarias, of what use is the heart, the liver, and the bile of the fish?”

7 He said to him, “About the heart and the liver: If a demon or an evil spirit troubles anyone, we must burn those and make smoke of them before the man or the woman, and the affliction will flee. 8 But as for the bile, it is good to anoint a man that has white films in his eyes, and he will be healed.”

9 But when they drew near to Rages, 10 the angel said to the young man, “Brother, today we will lodge with Raguel. He is your kinsman. He has an only daughter named Sarah. I will speak about her, that she should be given to you for a wife. 11 For her inheritance belongs to you, and you only are of her kindred. 12 The maid is fair and wise. And now hear me, and I will speak to her father. When we return from Rages we will celebrate the marriage; for I know that Raguel may in no way marry her to another according to the law of Moses, or else he would be liable to death, because it belongs to you to take the inheritance, rather than any other.”

13 Then the young man said to the angel, “Brother Azarias, I have heard that this maid has been given to seven men, and that they all perished in the bride-chamber. 14 Now I am the only son of my father, and I am afraid, lest I go in and die, even as those before me. For a demon loves her, which harms no man, but those which come to her. Now I fear lest I die, and bring my father’s and my mother’s life to the grave with sorrow because of me. They have no other son to bury them.”

15 But the angel said to him, “Don’t you remember the words which your father commanded you, that you should take a wife of your own kindred? Now hear me, brother; for she will be your wife. Don’t worry about the demon; for this night she will be given you as wife. 16 And when[*] you come into the bride-chamber, you shall take the ashes of incense, and shall lay upon them some of the heart and liver of the fish, and shall make smoke with them. 17 The demon will smell it, and flee away, and never come again any more. But when you go near to her, both of you rise up, and cry to God who is merciful. He will save you, and have mercy on you. Don’t be afraid, for she was prepared for you from the beginning; and you will save her, and she will go with you. And I suppose that you will have children with her.”

When Tobias heard these things, he loved her, and his soul was strongly joined to her.

7

1 They came to Ecbatana, and arrived at the house of Raguel. But Sarah met them; and she greeted them, and they her. Then she brought them into the house. 2 Raguel said to Edna his wife, “This young man really resembles Tobit my cousin!” 3 And Raguel asked them, “Where are you two from, kindred?”

They said to him, “We are of the sons of Naphtali, who are captives in Nineveh.”

4 He said to them, “Do you know Tobit our brother?”

They said, “We know him.”

Then he said to them, “Is he in good health?”

5 They said, “He is both alive, and in good health.” Tobias said, “He is my father.”

6 And Raguel sprang up, and kissed him, wept, 7 blessed him, and said to him, “You are the son of an honest and good man.” When he had heard that Tobit had lost his sight, he was grieved, and wept; 8 and Edna his wife and Sarah his daughter wept. They received them gladly; and they killed a ram of the flock, and served them meat.

But Tobias said to Raphael, “Brother Azarias, speak of those things of which you talked about in the way, and let the matter be finished.”

9 So he communicated the thing to Raguel. Raguel said to Tobias, “Eat, drink, and make merry: 10 for it belongs to you to take my child. However I will tell you the truth. 11 I have given my child to seven men of our relatives, and whenever they came in to her, they died in the night. But for the present be merry.”

And Tobias said, “I will taste nothing here, until you all make a covenant and enter into that covenant with me.”

12 Raguel said, “Take her to yourself from now on according to custom. You are her relative, and she is yours. The merciful God will give all good success to you.” 13 And he called his daughter Sarah, and took her by the hand, and gave her to be wife of Tobias, and said, “Behold, take her to yourself after the law of Moses, and lead her away to your father.” And he blessed them. 14 He called Edna his wife, then took a book, wrote a contract, and sealed it. 15 Then they began to eat.

16 And Raguel called his wife Edna, and said to her, “Sister, prepare the other chamber, and bring her in there.” 17 She did as he asked her, and brought her in there. She wept, and she received the tears of her daughter, and said to her, 18 “Be comforted, my child. May the Lord of heaven and earth give you favor[*] for this your sorrow. Be comforted, my daughter.”

8

1 When they had finished their supper, they brought Tobias in to her. 2 But as he went, he remembered the words of Raphael, and took the ashes of the incense, and put the heart and the liver of the fish on them, and made smoke with them. 3 When the demon smelled that smell, it fled into the uppermost parts of Egypt, and the angel bound him. 4 But after they were both shut in together, Tobias rose up from the bed, and said, “Sister, arise, and let’s pray that the Lord may have mercy on us.” 5 And Tobias began to say, “Blessed are you, O God of our fathers, and blessed is your holy and glorious name forever. Let the heavens bless you, and all your creatures. 6 You made Adam, and gave him Eve his wife for a helper and support. From them came the seed of men. You said, it is not good that the man should be alone. Let’s make him a helper like him. 7 And now, O Lord, I take not this my sister for lust, but in truth. Command that I may find mercy and grow old with her.”

8 She said with him, “Amen.” And they both slept that night.

9 Raguel arose, and went and dug a grave, 10 saying, “Lest he also should die.” 11 And Raguel came into his house, 12 and said to Edna his wife, “Send one of the maidservants, and let them see if he is alive. If not, we will bury him, and no man will know it.”

13 So the maidservant opened the door, and went in, and found them both sleeping, 14 and came out, and told them that he was alive.

15 Then Raguel blessed God, saying, “Blessed are you, O God, with all pure and holy blessing! Let your saints bless you, and all your creatures! Let all your angels and your elect bless you forever! 16 Blessed are you, because you have made me glad; and it has not happened to me as I suspected; but you have dealt with us according to your great mercy. 17 Blessed are you, because you have had mercy on two that were the only begotten children of their parents. Show them mercy, O Lord. Fulfill their life in health with gladness and mercy.

18 He commanded his servants to fill the grave. 19 He kept the wedding feast for them fourteen days. 20 Before the days of the wedding feast were finished, Raguel sware to him, that he should not depart till the fourteen days of the wedding feast were fulfilled; 21 and that then he should take half of his goods, and go in safety to his father; and the rest, said he, when my wife and I die.

9

1 And Tobias called Raphael, and said to him, 2 “Brother Azarias, take with you a servant and two camels, and go to Rages of Media to Gabael, and receive the money for me, and bring him to the wedding feast, 3 because Raguel has sworn that I must not depart. 4 My father counts the days; and if I wait long, he will be very grieved. 5 So Raphael went on his way, and lodged with Gabael, and gave him the handwriting; so he brought forth the bags with their seals, and gave them to him. 6 Then they rose up early in the morning together, and came to the wedding feast. Tobias blessed his wife.

10

1 Tobit his father counted every day. When the days of the journey were expired, and they didn’t come, 2 he said, “Is he perchance detained?[*] Or is Gabael perchance dead, and there is no one to give him the money?” 3 He was very grieved.

4 But his wife said to him, “The child has perished, seeing he waits long.” She began to bewail him, and said, 5 “I care about nothing,[†] my child, since I have let you go, the light of my eyes.” 6 Tobit said to her, “Hold your peace. Don’t worry. He is in good health.”

7 And she said to him, “Hold your peace. Don’t deceive me. My child has perished.” And she went out every day into the way by which they went, and ate no bread in the day-time, and didn’t stop bewailing her son Tobias for whole nights, until the fourteen days of the wedding feast were expired, which Raguel had sworn that he should spend there.

Then Tobias said to Raguel, “Send me away, for my father and my mother look no more to see me.” 8 But his father-in-law said to him, “Stay with me, and I will send to your father, and they will declare to him how things go with you.” 9 Tobias said, “No. Send me away to my father.”

10 Raguel arose, and gave him Sarah his wife, and half his goods, servants and cattle and money; 11 and he blessed them, and sent them away, saying, “The God of heaven will prosper you, my children, before I die.” 12 And he said to his daughter, “Honor your father-in-law and your mother-in-law. They are now your parents. Let me hear a good report of you.” Then he kissed her.

Edna said to Tobias, “May the Lord of heaven restore you, dear brother, and grant to me that I may see your children of my daughter Sarah, that I may rejoice before the Lord. Behold, I commit my daughter to you in special trust. Don’t cause her grief.

11

1 After these things Tobias also went his way, blessing God because he had prospered his journey; and he blessed Raguel and Edna his wife. Then he went on his way until they drew near to Nineveh. 2 Raphael said to Tobias, “Don’t you know, brother, how you left your father? 3 Let’s run forward before your wife, and prepare the house. 4 But take in your hand the bile of the fish.” So they went their way, and the dog went after them.

5 Anna sat looking around toward the path for her son. 6 She saw him coming, and said to his father, “Behold, your son is coming with the man that went with him!”

7 Raphael said, “I know, Tobias, that your father will open his eyes. 8 Therefore anoint his eyes with the bile, and being pricked with it, he will rub, and will make the white films fall away. Then he will see you.”

9 Anna ran to him, and fell upon the neck of her son, and said to him, “I have seen you, my child! I am ready to die.” They wept both.

10 Tobit went toward the door and stumbled; but his son ran to him, 11 and took hold of his father. He rubbed the bile on his father’s eyes, saying, “Cheer up, my father.” 12 When his eyes began to hurt, he rubbed them. 13 Then the white films peeled away from the corners of his eyes; and he saw his son, and fell upon his neck.

14 He wept, and said, “Blessed are you, O God, and blessed is your name forever! Blessed are all your holy angels! 15 For you scourged, and had mercy on me. Behold, I see my son Tobias.” And his son went in rejoicing, and told his father the great things that had happened to him in Media.

16 Tobit went out to meet his daughter-in-law at the gate of Nineveh, rejoicing and blessing God. Those who saw him go marveled, because he had received his sight. 17 Tobit gave thanks before them, because God had shown mercy on him. When Tobit came near to Sarah his daughter-in-law, he blessed her, saying, “Welcome, daughter! Blessed is God who has brought you to us, and blessed are your father and your mother.” And there was joy among all his kindred who were at Nineveh. 18 Achiacharus and Nasbas his brother’s son came. 19 Tobias’ wedding feast was kept seven days with great gladness.

12

1 And Tobit called his son Tobias, and said to him, “See, my child, that the man which went with you have his wages, and you must give him more.”

2 And he said to him, “Father, it is no harm to me to give him the half of those things which I have brought; 3 for he has led me for you in safety, and he cured my wife, and brought my money, and likewise cured you.”

4 The old man said, “It is due to him.”

5 And he called the angel, and said to him, “Take half of all that you all have brought.”

6 Then he called them both privately, and said to them, “Bless God, and give him thanks, and magnify him, and give him thanks in the sight of all that live, for the things which he has done with you. It is good to bless God and exalt his name, showing forth with honor the works of God. Don’t be slack to give him thanks. 7 It is good to keep close the secret of a king, but to reveal gloriously the works of God. Do good, and evil won’t find you. 8 Good is prayer with fasting, alms, and righteousness. A little with righteousness is better than much with unrighteousness. It is better to give alms than to lay up gold. 9 Alms delivers from death, and it purges away all sin. Those who give alms and do righteousness will be filled with life; 10 but those who sin are enemies to their own life. 11 Surely I will keep nothing closed from you. I have said, ‘It is good to keep close the secret of a king, but to reveal gloriously the works of God.’ 12 And now, when you prayed, and Sarah your daughter-in-law, I brought the memorial of your prayer before the Holy One. When you buried the dead, I was with you likewise. 13 And when you didn’t delay to rise up, and leave your dinner, that you might go and cover the dead, your good deed was not hidden from me. I was with you. 14 And now God sent me to heal you and Sarah your daughter-in-law. 15 I am Raphael, one of the seven holy angels which present the prayers of the saints and go in before the glory of the Holy One.”

16 And they were both troubled, and fell upon their faces; for they were afraid. 17 And he said to them, “Don’t be afraid. You will all have peace; but bless God forever. 18 For I came not of any favor of my own, but by the will of your God. Therefore bless him forever. 19 All these days I appeared to you. I didn’t eat or drink, but you all saw a vision. 20 Now give God thanks, because I ascend to him who sent me. Write in a book all the things which have been done.” 21 Then they rose up, and saw him no more. 22 They confessed the great and wonderful works of God, and how the angel of the Lord had appeared to them.

13

1 And Tobit wrote a prayer for rejoicing, and said,

“Blessed is God who lives forever!

Blessed is his kingdom!

2 For he scourges, and shows mercy.

He leads down to the grave,[*] and brings up again.

There is no one who will escape his hand.

3 Give thanks to him before the Gentiles, all you children of Israel!

For he has scattered us among them.

4 Declare his greatness, there.

Extol him before all the living,

because he is our Lord,

and God is our Father forever.

5 He will scourge us for our iniquities, and will again show mercy,

and will gather us out of all the nations among whom you are all scattered.

6 If you turn to him with your whole heart and with your whole soul,

to do truth before him,

then he will turn to you,

and won’t hide his face from you.

See what he will do with you.

Give him thanks with your whole mouth.

Bless the Lord of righteousness.

Exalt the everlasting King.

I give him thanks in the land of my captivity,

and show his strength and majesty to a nation of sinners.

Turn, you sinners, and do righteousness before him.

Who can tell if he will accept you and have mercy on you?

7 I exalt my God.

My soul exalts the King of heaven,

and rejoices in his greatness.

8 Let all men speak,

and let them give him thanks in Jerusalem.

9 O Jerusalem, the holy city,

he will scourge you for the works of your sons,

and will again have mercy on the sons of the righteous.

10 Give thanks to the Lord with goodness,

and bless the everlasting King,

that his tabernacle may be built in you again with joy,

and that he may make glad in you those who are captives,

and love in you forever those who are miserable.

11 Many nations will come from afar to the name of the Lord God

with gifts in their hands, even gifts to the King of heaven.

Generations of generations will praise you,

and sing songs of rejoicing.

12 All those who hate you are cursed.

All those who love you forever will be blessed.

13 Rejoice and be exceedingly glad for the sons of the righteous;

for they will be gathered together and will bless the Lord of the righteous.

14 Oh blessed are those who love you.

They will rejoice for your peace.

Blessed are all those who mourned for all your scourges;

because they will rejoice for you when they have seen all your glory.

They will be made glad forever.

15 Let my soul bless God the great King.

16 For Jerusalem will be built with sapphires, emeralds, and precious stones;

your walls and towers and battlements with pure gold.

17 The streets of Jerusalem will be paved with beryl, carbuncle, and stones of Ophir.

18 All her streets will say, “Hallelujah!”

and give praise, saying, “Blessed be God, who has exalted you forever!”

14

1 Then Tobit finished giving thanks. 2 He was fifty-eight years old when he lost his sight. After eight years, he received it again. He gave alms and he feared the Lord God more and more, and gave thanks to him.

3 Now he grew very old; and he called his son with the six sons of his son, and said to him, “My child, take your sons. Behold, I have grown old, and am ready to depart out of this life. 4 Go into Media, my child, for I surely believe all the things which Jonah the prophet spoke of Nineveh, that it will be overthrown, but in Media there will rather be peace for a season. Our kindred will be scattered in the earth from the good land. Jerusalem will be desolate, and the house of God in it will be burned up, and will be desolate for a time. 5 God will again have mercy on them, and bring them back into the land, and they will build the house, but not like to the former house, until the times of that age are fulfilled. Afterward they will return from the places of their captivity, and build up Jerusalem with honor. The house of God will be built in it forever with a glorious building, even as the prophets spoke concerning it. 6 And all the nations will turn to fear the Lord God truly, and will bury their idols. 7 All the nations will bless the Lord, and his people will give thanks to God, and the Lord will exalt his people; and all those who love the Lord God in truth and righteousness will rejoice, showing mercy to our kindred. 8 And now, my child, depart from Nineveh, because those things which the prophet Jonah spoke will surely come to pass. 9 But you must keep the law and the ordinances, and show yourself merciful and righteous, that it may be well with you. 10 Bury me decently, and your mother with me. Don’t stay at Nineveh. See, my child, what Aman did to Achiacharus who nourished him, how out of light he brought him into darkness, and all the recompense that he made him. Achiacharus was saved, but the other had his recompense, and he went down into darkness. Manasses gave alms, and escaped the snare of death which he set for him; but Aman fell into the snare, and perished. 11 And now, my children, consider what alms does, and how righteousness delivers.”

While he was saying these things, he gave up the ghost in the bed; but he was one hundred fifty eight years old. Tobias buried him magnificently. 12 When Anna died, he buried her with his father. But Tobias departed with his wife and his sons to Ecbatana to Raguel his father-in-law, 13 and he grew old in honor, and he buried his father-in-law and mother-in-law magnificently, and he inherited their possessions, and his father Tobit’s. 14 He died at Ecbatana of Media, being one hundred twenty seven years old. 15 Before he died, he heard of the destruction of Nineveh, which Nebuchadnezzar and Ahasuerus took captive. Before his death, he rejoiced over Nineveh.

* 1:2 That is, Shalmaneser. Compare 2 Kings 17:3, 23.

† 1:13 Gr. beauty.

‡ 1:15 Gr. his highways were troubled.

§ 1:17 Some ancient authorities read behind.

* 1:21 That is, Esar-haddon, and so in verse 22.

✡ 2:6 Amos 8:10

* 2:10 Some authorities read until he went.

† 2:14 Gr. all things are known with you.

* 3:8 Gr. demon.

† 3:10 Gr. Hades.

‡ 3:17 Gr. demon.

* 4:17 Or, tomb

* 6:16 Gr. if.

* 7:18 Many ancient authorities read joy.

* 10:2 Many ancient authorities read “Are they perchance put to shame?”

† 10:5 Some authorities read “Woe is me.”

* 13:2 Gr. Hades.

Zephaniah

1
2
3

The Book of

Zephaniah

1

1 Yahweh’s[*] word which came to Zephaniah, the son of Cushi, the son of Gedaliah, the son of Amariah, the son of Hezekiah, in the days of Josiah, the son of Amon, king of Judah.

2 I will utterly sweep away everything from the surface of the earth, says Yahweh. 3 I will sweep away man and animal. I will sweep away the birds of the sky, the fish of the sea, and the heaps of rubble with the wicked. I will cut off man from the surface of the earth, says Yahweh. 4 I will stretch out my hand against Judah and against all the inhabitants of Jerusalem. I will cut off the remnant of Baal from this place—the name of the idolatrous and pagan priests, 5 those who worship the army of the sky on the housetops, those who worship and swear by Yahweh and also swear by Malcam, 6 those who have turned back from following Yahweh, and those who haven’t sought Yahweh nor inquired after him.

7 Be silent at the presence of the Lord[†] Yahweh, for the day of Yahweh is at hand. For Yahweh has prepared a sacrifice. He has consecrated his guests. 8 It will happen in the day of Yahweh’s sacrifice that I will punish the princes, the king’s sons, and all those who are clothed with foreign clothing. 9 In that day, I will punish all those who leap over the threshold, who fill their master’s house with violence and deceit.

10 In that day, says Yahweh, there will be the noise of a cry from the fish gate, a wailing from the second quarter, and a great crashing from the hills. 11 Wail, you inhabitants of Maktesh, for all the people of Canaan are undone! All those who were loaded with silver are cut off. 12 It will happen at that time, that I will search Jerusalem with lamps, and I will punish the men who are settled on their dregs, who say in their heart, “Yahweh will not do good, neither will he do evil.” 13 Their wealth will become a plunder, and their houses a desolation. Yes, they will build houses, but won’t inhabit them. They will plant vineyards, but won’t drink their wine.

14 The great day of Yahweh is near. It is near and hurries greatly, the voice of the day of Yahweh. The mighty man cries there bitterly. 15 That day is a day of wrath, a day of distress and anguish, a day of trouble and ruin, a day of darkness and gloom, a day of clouds and blackness, 16 a day of the trumpet and alarm against the fortified cities and against the high battlements. 17 I will bring such distress on men that they will walk like blind men because they have sinned against Yahweh Their blood will be poured out like dust and their flesh like dung. 18 Neither their silver nor their gold will be able to deliver them in the day of Yahweh’s wrath, but the whole land will be devoured by the fire of his jealousy; for he will make an end, yes, a terrible end, of all those who dwell in the land.

2

1 Gather yourselves together, yes, gather together, you nation that has no shame, 2 before the appointed time when the day passes as the chaff, before the fierce anger of Yahweh comes on you, before the day of Yahweh’s anger comes on you. 3 Seek Yahweh, all you humble of the land, who have kept his ordinances. Seek righteousness. Seek humility. It may be that you will be hidden in the day of Yahweh’s anger. 4 For Gaza will be forsaken, and Ashkelon a desolation. They will drive out Ashdod at noonday, and Ekron will be rooted up. 5 Woe to the inhabitants of the sea coast, the nation of the Cherethites! Yahweh’s word is against you, Canaan, the land of the Philistines. I will destroy you until there is no inhabitant. 6 The sea coast will be pastures, with cottages for shepherds and folds for flocks. 7 The coast will be for the remnant of the house of Judah. They will find pasture. In the houses of Ashkelon, they will lie down in the evening, for Yahweh, their God,[*] will visit them and restore them. 8 I have heard the reproach of Moab and the insults of the children of Ammon, with which they have reproached my people and magnified themselves against their border. 9 Therefore, as I live, says Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, surely Moab will be as Sodom, and the children of Ammon as Gomorrah, a possession of nettles and salt pits, and a perpetual desolation. The remnant of my people will plunder them, and the survivors of my nation will inherit them. 10 This they will have for their pride, because they have reproached and magnified themselves against the people of Yahweh of Armies. 11 Yahweh will be awesome to them, for he will famish all the gods of the land. Men will worship him, everyone from his place, even all the shores of the nations.

12 You Cushites also, you will be killed by my sword.

13 He will stretch out his hand against the north, destroy Assyria, and will make Nineveh a desolation, as dry as the wilderness. 14 Herds will lie down in the middle of her, all kinds of animals. Both the pelican and the porcupine will lodge in its capitals. Their calls will echo through the windows. Desolation will be in the thresholds, for he has laid bare the cedar beams. 15 This is the joyous city that lived carelessly, that said in her heart, “I am, and there is no one besides me.” How she has become a desolation, a place for animals to lie down in! Everyone who passes by her will hiss and shake their fists.

3

1 Woe to her who is rebellious and polluted, the oppressing city! 2 She didn’t obey the voice. She didn’t receive correction. She didn’t trust in Yahweh. She didn’t draw near to her God.

3 Her princes within her are roaring lions. Her judges are evening wolves. They leave nothing until the next day. 4 Her prophets are arrogant and treacherous people. Her priests have profaned the sanctuary. They have done violence to the law. 5 Yahweh, within her, is righteous. He will do no wrong. Every morning he brings his justice to light. He doesn’t fail, but the unjust know no shame.

6 I have cut off nations. Their battlements are desolate. I have made their streets waste, so that no one passes by. Their cities are destroyed, so that there is no man, so that there is no inhabitant. 7 I said, “Just fear me. Receive correction,” so that her dwelling won’t be cut off, according to all that I have appointed concerning her. But they rose early and corrupted all their doings.

8 “Therefore wait for me”, says Yahweh, “until the day that I rise up to the prey, for my determination is to gather the nations, that I may assemble the kingdoms to pour on them my indignation, even all my fierce anger, for all the earth will be devoured with the fire of my jealousy.

9 For then I will purify the lips of the peoples, that they may all call on Yahweh’s name, to serve him shoulder to shoulder. 10 From beyond the rivers of Cush, my worshipers, even the daughter of my dispersed people, will bring my offering. 11 In that day you will not be disappointed for all your doings in which you have transgressed against me; for then I will take away out from among you your proudly exulting ones, and you will no more be arrogant in my holy mountain. 12 But I will leave among you an afflicted and poor people, and they will take refuge in Yahweh’s name. 13 The remnant of Israel will not do iniquity nor speak lies, neither will a deceitful tongue be found in their mouth, for they will feed and lie down, and no one will make them afraid.”

14 Sing, daughter of Zion! Shout, Israel! Be glad and rejoice with all your heart, daughter of Jerusalem. 15 Yahweh has taken away your judgments. He has thrown out your enemy. The King of Israel, Yahweh, is among you. You will not be afraid of evil any more. 16 In that day, it will be said to Jerusalem, “Don’t be afraid, Zion. Don’t let your hands be weak.” 17 Yahweh, your God, is among you, a mighty one who will save. He will rejoice over you with joy. He will calm you in his love. He will rejoice over you with singing. 18 I will remove those who grieve about the appointed feasts from you. They are a burden and a reproach to you. 19 Behold,[*] at that time I will deal with all those who afflict you; and I will save those who are lame and gather those who were driven away. I will give them praise and honor, whose shame has been in all the earth. 20 At that time I will bring you in, and at that time I will gather you; for I will give you honor and praise among all the peoples of the earth when I restore your fortunes before your eyes, says Yahweh.

* 1:1 “Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

† 1:7 The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

* 2:7 The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

* 3:19 “Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.